<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4418">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Henry Augustus Robinson to Matthew Nathan, 6 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Augustus Robinson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter refers to a dispute in Kilrush, County Clare, over a toll levied by the urban district council. Robinson argues that the toll is a fair one as the poor rate (a form of tax) was as high as it could go and the toll was needed for the council to fund its services. He believes the council should hold firm and keep the tax and expresses disappointment that the police had called for its withdrawal.

Enclosed is a petition from the Chairman of Kilrush Urban Council and its solicitor to Major General Friend, Commander in Chief of the Forces in Ireland, outlining their grievances. They describe agitation and intimidation by a small group of farmers and suggests means of overcoming the opposition.

Sir Henry Augustus Robinson (1857–1927) was an Irish public servant. He was primarily responsible for the drafting and implementation of the local government act of 1898, and shortly before the bill became law was appointed vice-president of the Local Government Board.

Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) was the under-secretary to the Chief Crown Secretary of Ireland Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Nathan was under-secretary until the 1916 Rising after which he offered his resignation.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/5596/1916/730/2-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4418</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1153">Henry Augustus Robinson</persName>
              <date>1916-01-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1284">The Local Government Board, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4418_img_377_1"  type="Letter"  url="21da99386a18b7b18d4e4e1118f047c0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4418_img_377_2"  type="Letter"  url="916fb844635c6cc2ee2b3b29c493c7ea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4418_img_377_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="f8066e9f990764f04d2b05109863b85d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4418_img_377_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="adf2179a3ce7674edcc015db6e73f8fe.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4418_img_377_1"/>
             Local Government Board, Dublin   6th January 1916.   My dear Nathan,   The rates in Kilrush have approached the <lb/>breaking point. They are 9/9 in the £, and even with this <lb/>crushing impost the town is in debt. Their method of meeting <lb/>their liabilities by a slight increase in the tolls is, in <lb/>my judgement, a fair and proper one. All these farmers <lb/>living outside the town use the roads for their carts going <lb/>to markets, use the churches, the schools and the railway <lb/>station, and make their living by their trade with the town <lb/>while they do not contribute one penny towards the upkeep and <lb/>maintenance of it. The only way they can be made to contri—<lb/>bute to the benefits which they enjoy is by means of these <lb/>small tolls which are no higher than those which exist in many <lb/>parts of Ireland.   The Council gave due notice of their intention to <lb/>make these tolls and no objection was raised. If there had <lb/>been we should have made inquiry before we sanctioned them.   I sincerely hope the Council will stand to their <lb/>guns. This agitation will not last very long, and if the out—<lb/>side farmers succeed in forcing the Council now to give way, <lb/>it will be the first to a strike against other tolls <lb/>and this will only mean a still greater burden upon the towns—<lb/>people, rich and poor. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4418_img_377_2"/>
             I do not think you are necessarily right in consid—<lb/>ering that the tolls are paid by the poorer purchasers. The <lb/> people will probably have to pay their tolls on the turf that <lb/>is exposed for sale before they sell it.   I do not believe they will be able to get more than <lb/>the present market price from the purchasers, at least for any <lb/>length of time.   The matter is one for the Urban District Council, re—<lb/>presenting the towns people, and the outside farmers to fight <lb/>out among themselves, and I sincerely hope the Council will <lb/>win. I much regret to see that Police are expressing the <lb/>opinion that the Council ought to withdraw the tax, and I hope <lb/>they will be asked to keep this opinion to themselves.   Yours sincerely,   <hi rend="underline">H O Robinson</hi>   The Right Hon. Sir Matthew Nathan, G.C.M.G., <lb/>Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4418_img_377_3"/>
             Major General Friend, <lb/>Commander in Chief of Forces in Ireland, <lb/>Military Headquarters, <lb/><seg type="del">DUBLIN.</seg>  Queenstown, Co.Cork    We the undersigned wish to bring the following matter <lb/>before the Military Authorities in Ireland with a view to <lb/>have the matter dealt with immediately by them.   There are over 400 labourers from the town of Kilrush <lb/>with the Colours and they have left behind them Wifes and <lb/>families depending on their Separation Allowances to keep <lb/>them. Lately an Agitation has sprung up among the Vendors <lb/>of Turf from Sragh and the neighbourhood against a small Toll <lb/>of 1d levied on Turf brought into the Kilrush Market the <lb/>result being that though <sic>attempss</sic> have been made by the <lb/>undersigned to procure <sic>waggons</sic> of Turf from the neighbourhood <lb/>of Sragh and Doonbeg still it has not been possible to get <lb/>people in the neighbourhood to supply same owing to the <lb/>intimidation of a few parties who are at the back of the <lb/>Agitation.   In these circumstances the small farmers from the <lb/>Sragh District have combined to prevent parties bringing Turf <lb/>in on their Cars or supplying <sic>waggons</sic> through the Railway <lb/>Company and the result is that the supply of Turf to Kilrush <lb/>is cut off and the poor people are suffering as a result as <lb/>they could not burn <seg type="del">turf</seg>  coal  in the open hearths!   There are two ways of dealing with this kind of <lb/>conduct. The first suggestion is that the Military <lb/>Authorities should Commandeer a supply of turf which is <lb/>always available at Sragh or Doonbeg on the W.C.R. and sell <lb/>same  to  a Fuel Committee in Kilrush who would in turn sell it to <lb/> the poor people or secondly without commandeering the turf <lb/>at all if the Military Authorities used their influence with <lb/>the Department of Agriculture for Ireland who own the <lb/>Kilrush Demesne to allow the poor people to take away the old <lb/>timber of which there is an abundance, this with a small supply <lb/>of Coal which the Fuel Committee would provide would carry the <lb/>people over the worst part of the winter. <note<p.t.o. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4418_img_377_4"/>
             Should the Military Authorities favourably consider this <lb/>Application the Fuel Committee of Kilrush and the S. Vincent de Paul <lb/>Society would give all the assistance possible. It should be <lb/>added that the parties who are instrumental in creating this impassé <lb/>have not sent one single man to the Colours.   Dated this 20th day of December I9I5.   Batt Culligan J.P.  (Chairman of the <lb/>Kilrush Urban Council)   <seg type="unclear"><hi rend="underline">M Comiskay</hi></seg> (Solicitor to the <lb/>Kilrush Urban Council) 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>