<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4129">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Carey to Alexander Barlas, 3 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Carey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Carey to Alexander Richard Barlas regarding a copy of the plans and specifications for the proposed new boiler in Killarney workhouse.

Patrick Carey (1853-1934) was the Union Clerk for the Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians. Poor law unions and their workhouses were established by the Poor Law (Ireland) Act, 1838, as a response to widespread poverty, and were each governed by a Board of Guardians. This letter comes from the Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians Minute Book.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians BG104/B/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4129</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1557">Patrick Carey</persName>
              <date>1915-12-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2102">Killarney, Co. Kerry, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1045">Alexander Barlas</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0429">Local Government Board, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4129_img_3503_1"  type="Letter"  url="4d608cff74156e09d097890579f608f0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4129_img_3503_1"/>
            <!-- Top right corner of the page> <lb/> 411   3rd December 5.  No. 47881. 1915. <lb/> <hi rend="underline"> Killarney Union. </hi>   Sir,     <seg type="del"> As requested in </seg>   With reference to   your letter of the 14th September <lb/> last, I beg to enclose, herewith, certified copy of <lb/> the plan and specification furnished by the Engineer <lb/> to the Board of Guardians in connection with the <lb/> proposed <seg type="del"> installation </seg>   erection   of the New Boiler at the Workhouse <lb/> and extension of the hot water supply to the Hospitals.    I am, Sir, <lb/> Your Obedient Servant,   Clerk of Union.   The Secretary, <lb/> Local Government Board, <lb/> Dublin.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>