<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4148">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 7 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/48</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4148</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-07</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4148_img_3522_1"  type="Letter"  url="007f22fffaeaa38556027bccf429ef9e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4148_img_3522_2"  type="Letter"  url="6da26d4064796b1809610736996b5e1b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4148_img_3522_1"/>
             7 Nov   My own pr.   I had intended to write quite a decent letter today , to smooth <lb/>some ruffled fur, but Russel is in bed with a bad cough,&amp; I have to <lb/>take his place with the General who is visiting the Corps Com .   I rather look forward to Miss L Dean's reply, &amp; wonder if the PR <lb/>has developed very stilted legs too, or whether she has learnt not to stir up growly bw. <lb/>Russel has been seedy for some days &amp; I have been trying to persuade him to go <lb/>to bed, but the <seg type="unclear">Genl's</seg> order today only had the desired effect. He looks so pale <lb/>as a rule that I imagine he will soon get over it.   A perfectly briliant day today after frosty weather last night &amp; <lb/>if only we could carry on like this with not more that 3 days wet, we should <lb/>get through the winter well, but we must I suppose be moved somewhere <lb/>in the next four weeks, but as there seems to be some chance of a <lb/>German attack, we may possibly be kept instead of going to Serbia which <lb/>I had looked upon as a certainty tho' not others. I can talk fairly <lb/>freely until we get any hint &amp; then it will be mum.    It is very curious that Ed has never referred to a letter I sent <lb/>him about rumours &amp; it is possible he hs not got it, but on <lb/>what grounds ist should be suppressed I cannot imagine.   You are rather naughty about your plans, not one of your letters <lb/>gives a hint as to your stay at Rugby whether for the night or <lb/>weekend or what , nor about  dates for  24 HPG tho miss says you go there next <lb/>Friday.   I did answer about the mattress , which is A 1 . It only has 2 <lb/>compartments to Col Russell's 3 but as my weight is less &amp; more distributed <lb/>this should not matter. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4148_img_3522_2"/>
             I argue about the splitting up of <lb/>the Div<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>but this is being done to others out here &amp; I really hope <lb/>only temporary. B Smith declares he is convinced that the RC influence <lb/>is being put in here on purpose tho I am sure that neither Carson nor <lb/>Maguire have anything to do with it. It certainly is curious that of the last <lb/>5 appointments 4 should have ben RCs! Many thanks for the Rubber <lb/>report which I return. I should like an account of the meeting. <lb/>Rubber is the one thing that is bouncing now &amp; if only one didn't <lb/>foresee that it will puncture after the heavy war demands cease, <seg type="del">I</seg> we <lb/>could face the future with equanimity. As it is we must use the <lb/>present fat years like Joseph &amp; the pr is most good in realizing this.   What a compliment I paid you in my remarks about Henry, but I <lb/>gather that your reply is that grey hairs have only begun to grow since you <lb/>were married !    Joy says that because she knows it is impossible to keep you in <lb/>your place, but I have better hopes of <seg type="unclear">Alice</seg>who knows from experience how <lb/>to deal firmly with children   What a nice letter of Mrs Richardson's ! I have heard from Craig <lb/>a very nice letter which I will forward later. He hints that the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> <lb/>is going to compromise with Germany. If so I am not sure that I would <lb/>not wish to be no longer an Englishman.  &amp; have <lb/>both written sadly: their own positions are most unsatisfactory, &amp; the <lb/> in which they are finding reserves for the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>&amp;not for <lb/>us is perfectly ---able  <lb/>I must be off now.  The  is still the entire stars of the p r espescially <lb/>at nights. More so than ever   Your <seg type="unclear">Own</seg>bw  <signed<Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>