<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0279">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William George Lyon to J. G. Swift MacNeill, 10 April 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William George Lyon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from William George Lyon (1868-1939), a publisher, to J. G. Swift MacNeill.The letter concerns the use of Robert Louis Stevenson&#39;s novel &#39;Kidnapped&#39; on the school syllabus. In the letter Lyon states the book is unsuitable for Irish children to read, stating that it has a Scottish atmosphere and language and the children would need to learn a new language to read it. He also highlights the fact that the profit from the sales of the book will go to English and not Irish publishers. He goes on to say that the issue is on the floor of the House of Commons and that he expects the Irish Party to support it. The letter encloses a list of words in the book that Lyon believes Irish children will not understand, also a newspaper cutting of a letter to the editor of the Irish Independent regarding the same issue.John Gordon Swift MacNeill (1849 - 1926) was a jurist and politician. He was MP for South Donegal from 1887 until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>National Archive of Ireland-Chief Secretary&#39;s Office-Registered Papers, NAI/CSO/RP/1916/5611/8225/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/279</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0798">William George Lyon</persName>
              <date>1916-03-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0763">87 Talbot Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">J G Swift MacNeill</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0062">17 Pembroke Road, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0279_img_1479_1"  type="Letter"  url="b4f382d499aa5a37e8a964be5bd6c2f7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0279_img_1479_2"  type="Letter"  url="68fe0c38579f10be3efa7d131bf93a3e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0279_img_1479_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="00e4c23adbf5456f44bdf7cda6ea81b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0279_img_1479_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="5f1ee1d86223a67f2a093b4add695c5b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0279_img_1479_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="e841f7adf51c48035382f268c3b0ff1a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0279_img_1479_1"/>
                10th April 1916.   J. G. Swift MacNeil, Esq., M.P.,   17, Pembroke Road ,  DUBLIN.   Dear Mr. Swift MacNeil.   As you are deeply interested in all that concerns <lb/> the literary and commercial welfare of Ireland, might I ask <lb/> your attention to the doings of the Intermediate Education <lb/> Board.  The enclosed letter (of which we know nothing) <lb/> appeared in the 'Independent' of the 1st inst., and I now <lb/> know that the book referred to is Stevenson's 'Kidnapped'. <lb/> To my mind , the book is wholy unsuited for Irish children, <lb/> and, as it is not in Stevenson's best style , the atmosphere <lb/> is so Scotch that I am afraid it would be uncongenial to the <lb/> vast majority of Irish boys and girls; and to read it with <lb/> understanding they would require to learn a new language.  I enclose a short selection of some of the words in <lb/> the only School Edition published, which is supposed to be an<lb/> expurgated edition for use in schools. Then of course, as <lb/> it is a copyright book, the whole of the profits on the sale <lb/> must go to England, and poor Irish publishers and printers <lb/> (like Mother Hubbard's dog) get none.   The Programme is on the Table of the House of Commons, <lb/> and there it lies for 40 days, during which time any Member of <lb/> Parliament can take exception to any of the conditions, and I <lb/> fancy that any question regarding a subject like this would be <lb/> supported by the whole of the Irish Party.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0279_img_1479_2"/>
               <hi rend="underline">J. G. Swift MacNeil, Esq., M.P</hi>  I should be very glad if you could see your way<lb/> to bring the matter before The Chief Secretary, because if <lb/> an alternative book is not allowed there will be a serious <lb/> revolt amongst the Principals of the Intermediate Schools.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0279_img_1479_3"/>
               DOUBTFUL WORDS AND PHRASES IN R. L. STEVENSON'S 'KIDNAPPED', TAKEN<lb/><hi rend="underline">FROM THE ONLY SCHOOL EDITION PUBLISHED:</hi><lb/><lb/> Page 92 (3rd line from top) 'Be damned to your word!' says he.<lb/><hi rend="underline">SCOTCH CONUNDRUMS:</hi><lb/> Argle-bargled Deave me Orra<lb/> Bauchled Dirdum Peewees<lb/> Begowk Dirl Pypats<lb/> Birling Donnered auld runt Redd up<lb/> Boggle  E  Dunt Roupet<lb/> Boumen Gars Shambles  E <lb/> Breeks Girning Spate  - Irish Spate <lb/> Buckie Gomeral Taigle<lb/> Canny goer Gyte Thole - E <lb/> Chancy Jouk Tirls<lb/> Chapping Kyte Tod<lb/> Clour Limmer Unco<lb/> Cocking Loon  (standard prose)  Wame<lb/> Collops Lug Whaups<lb/> Cutty Pipe Mair Wheen<lb/> Wits upon the honey<lb/> Wyte.<pb n="3824' facs="#L1916_1479_img_3824"/> THE INTERMEDIATE.<lb/> SCOTTISH TEXT-BOOKS.<lb/> To the Editor 'Irish Independent'.  Sir&amp;#8212;It is understood that in their programme<lb/> for 1917 the Commissioners of Intermediate Education<lb/> have gone out of their way, for the second<lb/> time within three years, to prescribe a Scottish<lb/> copyright novel as the prose text for study in<lb/> the Junior Grade. The result of this action is<lb/> to prevent the book from being published in<lb/> Ireland as a school edition, unless possibly in<lb/> some arrangement which would involve the payment<lb/> of considerable amounts to the English<lb/> holders of the copyright. This running after<lb/> novelties in the form of current Scottish fiction,<lb/> in preference to the approved standard material<lb/> which exists so abundantly, might easily be shown<lb/> to be unsound educationally. It looks like the<lb/> rather belated survival of a certain literary cult<lb/> which has already exhausted itself on the other<lb/> side of the Channel.  But, whatever be the intellectual motives, the<lb/> economic aspect of the matter is of more immediate<lb/> importance to the public. From that point<lb/> of view it is really intolerable that money which<lb/> might well be expended for the benefit of a<lb/> stricken Irish industry should be heedlessly sent<lb/> out of the country to swell the fees of London<lb/> copyright-owners and printers. The difficulties<lb/> of the present time are pressing with extreme<lb/> severity on the Irish printing and publishing<lb/> business. Unemployment exists on a grevious<lb/> scale; and now through the ill-advised decision<lb/> of the Intermediate Commissioners or their ad-<lb/> visers, numbers of Irish compositors, machinists,<lb/> bookbinders, girls engaged in folding and<lb/> stitching, and other workers will be deprived, this<lb/> season, of the much-needed earnings on which<lb/> they could hitherto count in the bringing out of<lb/> the Junior Grade English texts for the schools.  IRISH BOOK PRODUCTION.<lb/> No one can pretend that the Commissioners are<lb/> under any obligation to depart from an estab-<lb/> lished custom, or to look to Scotland and its<lb/> copyrights for any new literary inspiration. The<lb/> vast range of standard, non-copyright English<lb/> prose is still open to them as ever; and surely<lb/> this illimitable field is adequate enough to provide suffi-<lb/> client basis of selection to satisfy every possible<lb/> taste or requirement, and thus enable the books <lb/> to be produced in Ireland, as heretofore, in well-<lb/> edited texts.  Public opinion, it is hoped, will be strong <lb/> enough to induce the Commissioners to abandon<lb/> their present intention in this regard. But, if <lb/> necessary it ought to be made clear that Parlia-<lb/> ment, at the instance of the Irish members, will<lb/> refuse to sanction the new rules and regulations <lb/> of the Board until the Scottish copyright novel<lb/> is removed from the programme in favour of some <lb/> suitable non-copyright book which the Irish firms <lb/> will be at liberty to reprint and publish among <lb/> their Intermediate editions.  IRISHMAN <pb n="3825' facs="#L1916_1479_img_3825"/> <hi rend="underline">QUESTION.</hi> To ask The Chief Secretary for Ireland if his<lb/> attention has been called to the Intermediate Programme<lb/> for 1917, in which 'Kidnapped' is prescribed for study<lb/> by Junior Grade Pupils.  If so, is The Chief Secretary aware that the<lb/> book contains matter wholly unsuitable for<seg type="del">school study</seg>Irish children,<lb/> inasmuch as it has no educative tendencies, and is couched<lb/> in a language which will not be understood in Ireland.  Under these circumstances will The chief Secretary<lb/> recommend that an alternative book be prescribed.    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0279_img_1479_4"/>
            
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0279_img_1479_5"/>
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>