<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2039">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jessie Crofton to Lady Clonbrock, 23 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jessie Crofton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Jessie Crofton (1865-1923) to her aunt Augusta Caroline Dillon, Lady Clonbrock (1840-1928).  Clonbrock was a prominent member of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, founded to provide aid and assistance to Irish soldiers and prisoners of war and the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock.
Jessie&#39;s husband Arthur Edward Lowther Crofton (d. 1966) served as a lieutenant colonel in the Northumberland Fusiliers during the Great War. Jessie writes to inform Lady Clonbrock of the content of Arthur&#39;s last few letters. She describes the letters and gives an extract from one of the letters giving a detailed description of Arthur&#39;s experiences in the trenches.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,797 (2)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2039</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1191">Jessie Crofton</persName>
              <date>1916-02-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1838">Mote, Roscommon, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1923</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2039_img_1487_1"  type="Letter"  url="e6cb603ed88755b307c216d0815369a4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2039_img_1487_2"  type="Letter"  url="020cb8b68bc990f8a6ab9fa7f70a3106.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2039_img_1487_3"  type="Letter"  url="df1853b7a2d2a1656eb5f35ee27ca643.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2039_img_1487_4"  type="Letter"  url="2bb0467bcf7da33d4d91b21c6f53ebd4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2039_img_1487_5"  type="Letter"  url="ca3129f7e268a1a1d24eede4d6e12b5e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2039_img_1487_6"  type="Letter"  url="e4b324ac07852c4d77290d1be534fd63.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2039_img_1487_1"/>
                 23_2_16.   My dear Aunt <seg type="unclear">Luce</seg>,    Just a line to tell <lb/> you what was in Arthur's <lb/> last few letters. he came <lb/> out of the trenches on <lb/> Saturday after   <lb/> They did not take their <lb/>clothes  off  the whole time <lb/> &amp; Arthur was seedy <lb/> all the time. He has <lb/> He has a severe cough &amp; can't <lb/> shake it off. He says
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2039_img_1487_2"/>
            <sic>"there</sic> new trenches are <lb/> beastly the Germans blew <lb/> up two <seg type="unclear">mines</seg> about <lb/> two months ago in front <lb/> of <seg type="unclear">our</seg> line, with the result <lb/> that we both tried to get <lb/> the craters &amp; are <seg type="unclear">now</seg> <lb/> one on each side of it <lb/> only a few yards apart. <lb/> &amp; its <seg type="unclear">awfully lumpy earth</seg> <lb/> the Germans have the best <lb/> side &amp; have good parapet <lb/> &amp; we have <seg type="unclear">nothing.</seg> then there <lb/> are dead men in front <lb/> who cannot be touched by either side &amp; remains <lb/> of men in the parapet <lb/>etc. &amp; the most awful <lb/> stench &amp; you cannot show <lb/> <seg type="unclear">yourself</seg> or you get hit <lb/> at once, &amp; there is more <lb/> shelling here than in <lb/> the last trenches. I had <lb/> a better dugout &amp; can <lb/> stand up straight &amp; <lb/> Someone collected some chairs <lb/> from a farm <seg type="unclear">hence</seg> that <lb/>was shelled before the <lb/> people could remove their <lb/> furniture — Edward has
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2039_img_1487_3"/>
            been to see him &amp; looks <lb/>well, &amp; Arthur is expecting <lb/>him again. Arthur says <lb/>he heard from Captain White <lb/>who said Col <seg type="unclear">Sapte</seg> was <lb/>on his way home, because <lb/>he is <hi rend="underline">too old</hi>! he is a good <lb/>bit younger than Arthur. <lb/>Arthur likes his 2<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">nd</hi></hi> in <lb/>Command, so that is a good <lb/>thing — Arthur's <seg type="unclear">Batl<hi rend="superscript><hi rend="underline>n</hi></hi></seg> is the <lb/>13<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> so I suppose <seg type="unclear">young</seg>   <lb/>is  one of  his officers. he said the <lb/>last two who came out <lb/>were rankers, but as far <lb/>as he could see they <lb/>were no worse than a <lb/>lot of the others. he <lb/>has some gentleman still
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2039_img_1487_4"/>
            which is a good thing <lb/> <seg type="unclear">with</seg> most of them going. <lb/> His 2<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">nd</hi></hi> in C. is alright <lb/> so that is a comfort, I <lb/> expect Arthur knows <seg type="unclear">young</seg> <lb/> Haig by sight but I don't <lb/> think he knows him <lb/> by name. In any case <lb/> he would be nice &amp; <lb/> civil to him — <seg type="unclear">Markie</seg> <lb/> has a new <seg type="unclear">Cap &amp; Scarf <lb/> having been made a <lb/> Gym Officer —they played <lb/> Eton, at Eton on Saturday <lb/> &amp; beat them 3<seg type="del">5</seg>  35  to 6. <lb/> &amp; had a most enjoyable <lb/> day — they motored to <lb/> Eton at a tremendous
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2039_img_1487_5"/>
            pace &amp; turned all <lb/> the corners on one <lb/> wheel, so were quite <lb/> happy. Edward is so much <lb/> better since his <seg type="unclear">nose</seg> was <lb/> done. I suppose that is <lb/> why he passed the <lb/> Medical Board this <lb/> time. I found applications <lb/> he had sent in at <lb/> various times (among his <lb/> papers) to be sent out <lb/> to the front, had been <lb/> returned to him, saying <lb/> he could not go until <lb/> he had passed a <lb/> Medical Board. I thought he was applying <lb/> but he would not say <lb/> when I asked him if <lb/> he was. I'm very glad <lb/> he has gone to his <lb/> own Regt.    I am <lb/>Yours aff's  <lb/> Jessie C 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2039_img_1487_6"/>
             Feb:25  <lb/> Jessie 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>