<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3092">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 24 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie. The letter is filled with questions about life at home: the well being of his family, friends and the farm. He writes about his training schedule and about a Mass he attended. He closes by reminiscing on his time at home and writes about how much he misses those at home. 

Peter Mooney was born on 5th February 1886 in Folistown, Dunboyne. Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie (b. 1884) were brought up by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18th October 1915. 

He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St.Omer and Passchendael, in Belgium.Peter was an avid correspondent with his sister Kate and this letter is from a collection of over ninety surviving letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>Mooney Family Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3092</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1915-01-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1366">5th Reserve Brigade, Royal Field Artillery, Ballincollig, Co. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1461">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1970</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3092_img_2497_1"  type="Letter"  url="5f78320a4d61f466bcfe4824ddff2b7f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3092_img_2497_2"  type="Letter"  url="04a2b3420cacf8eba154e027fa3894ca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3092_img_2497_3"  type="Letter"  url="9b26053d5af77d88c4ecab9125b03fed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3092_img_2497_4"  type="Letter"  url="4e8d05043c273f0598a2943f6ef54a73.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3092_img_2497_1"/>
             5th Reserve Brigade R.F.A. <lb/>Ballincollig.   Jan 24<hi rend="superscript">th 1916</hi>  <lb/> Dear Katie.   You are indeed very <lb/>kind to write to me so <lb/>often I am glad to see <lb/>by your letters that <lb/>things are going on so well at home. I am <lb/>doing well &amp; getting the <lb/>very best of health. <lb/>The weather was very wet <lb/>this last few days
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3092_img_2497_2"/>
            <lb/>Tell her to pray for me <lb/> as her prayers should be <lb/> heard. The Majors name <lb/> here is Major Calvert &amp; <lb/>a strict old boy he is <lb/> Tell my Aunt she can <lb/>keep the money she got <lb/>for the heifer all I ask <lb/>in return is a few prayers. <lb/>Tell me if you want <lb/>anything &amp; I will see about <lb/>it. I do often think of <lb/>you all at home when <lb/>evening time comes I think <lb/>of the cows that I used <lb/>to milk. It will be <lb/> Heaven to me when I get <lb/>home to you all again. <lb/>We all go to 12.00 mass <lb/>at the Parish Chapel we have <lb/>to march about a quarter of <lb/>a mile. We did not get <lb/>much drill yet but we <lb/>have a lot to do with <lb/>horses cleaning them &amp; <lb/>walking them out every <lb/day. We are all sleeping on <lb/>straw stuffed into linen <lb/>bags. We have no sheets <lb/>nothing more than three <lb/>brown rugs. Still I am <lb/>happy &amp; doing well so <lb/>far <!-- to be read right to left -->
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3092_img_2497_3"/>
            <lb/>They seem to have forgotten <lb/> me altogether in the <lb/>Paddock I wonder why <lb/>it is. How is Paddy <lb/>I must give him a hand <lb/>to dress them sheep when <lb/>I get home. Tell Jimmy <lb/>Reilly I was asking for <lb/>him is Jim Mullally still <lb/>working the forge. I <lb/>have no more at present    <lb/>so I say Good Bye &amp; <lb/>may God Bless you all <lb/> pray for me.   Pr. Mooney 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3092_img_2497_4"/>
             11 JUL 16   Miss. K. Mooney <lb/>Caulstown <lb/>Dunboyne <lb/>County Meath <lb/>Ireland 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>