<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2661">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to her mother, Maria Duffin, 10 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

Celia Duffin was a VAD with the 3rd London General Hospital in Wandsworth which opened in 1914. She was an accomplished poet, publishing, amongst other volumes, a book of poetry with her sister Ruth.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2661</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0707">25 Nicosia Road, Wandsworth, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2661_img_2085_1"  type="Letter"  url="9e917275219e3376a981bd56a1f40d07.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2661_img_2085_2"  type="Letter"  url="71ff7e3f7c70c4e8d097855e0e693632.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2661_img_2085_3"  type="Letter"  url="b415661be8ee7dd68cf76b57363a7a54.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2661_img_2085_1"/>
             25 Nicoria Rd   Feb 10<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> 1916   Dearest Mamma   I find it is a week since I left <lb/> home and I have never written yet, but <lb/> I have spent my off duty time there <lb/> last 3 days hunting for Olive. I <lb/> have never had a more peaceful journey <lb/> no the least bit sick either on the <lb/> boat or the train, and fast asleep <lb/> all night. I had great greetings <lb/> with my friend the Captain and paraded <lb/> the deck with him until everybody <lb/> else had gone to bed, and he told <lb/> me all his adventures. I <seg type="del">always</seg> also <lb/> made friends with a young subaltern <lb/> going to join the Irish Fusiliers at Kent, <lb/> and a rather nice lady who
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2661_img_2085_2"/>
            took an interest in me because her two <lb/> daughters were V.A.D's at <seg type="unclear">Rowen</seg>. But <lb/> there was nobody interesting to talk to <lb/> in the train. I lunched at Victoria <lb/> before coming on here and found <seg type="unclear">Gosse</seg> <lb/> had an afternoon off, so we lit a <lb/> nice fire and I made some good tea <lb/> and fed her on currant loaf which <lb/> she thought awfully good.   It was awfully nice seeing you all again, <lb/> I felt as if I had been away for ages. <lb/> I got a message from Olive saying that <lb/> she and Marjorie had arrived at the <lb/> Strand Palace Hotel, and as I happened <lb/> to be off duty at 5, I hurried up <lb/> to train without waiting for tea. When I <lb/> arrived I could find no trace of them, <lb/> and after waiting some time <lb/> feeling very hungry, I had some tea <lb/> and returned home. The hotel was  full of new army men and their relations <lb/> and best girls. Next morning I got a <lb/>card saying they were at the <hi rend="underline">Regent</hi> <lb/> Palace Hotel and as I had 3 hours <lb/> off in the morning, I went in again, <lb/> and again couldn't find them, although <lb/> Olive says they were there all the time. <lb/> However, next day, I was off in the after-<lb/> noon, so <wired to Olive to meet me <lb/> at S. Rensington Station which is half <lb/> way here, and actually did - Marjorie <lb/> however had gone. We went to the muse-<lb/> um which is quite close and saw <lb/> such fascinating things there, especially <lb/> in the old furniture part, which is all <lb/> arranged in such charming old-fashioned <lb/> rooms, The old chaises are attractive <lb/> too, and we had a glimpse at the <lb/> minitures. Poor Olive had a bad cold <lb/> again.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2661_img_2085_3"/>
             I am awfully glad about your £500 but <lb/> wish <seg type="unclear">Jon</seg> had got the portrait, why did <lb/> Miss Munn make that up? Surely there <lb/> must have been more money than <seg type="unclear">Jon</seg> <lb/> thought? How nice of her to leave something <lb/> to us. I have just heard too that our <lb/> allowances are to be cut down. The War <lb/> Office is waking up.   I am just trying some of the soup for <lb/> supper, it is simmering at present and <lb/> smells good, I added a little milk <lb/> and butter and will keep some <lb/> hot when Gosse comes in late.   No news of any kind, I am back in <lb/> the same ward, so far, all is peace <lb/> with me, but the two staff nurses seem <lb/> to have had a row this morning and <lb/> the head sister is still away.   Many thanks for your and Helen's <lb/> letter. Ever your loving   Celia 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>