<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2470">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from F. T. Smyth to the county inspector, Cork, 20 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author> F. T. Smyth</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from F. T. Smyth to the RIC county inspector for Cork. The letter refers to an incident that took place near Charleville, county Cork, in May 1916. While passing through a field on his way home, Constable Prendergast  was fired at. However, he survived unharmed with a bullet piercing a hole in his police cap. 

Smyth states that Constable Prendergast is particularly unpopular with the local Irish Volunteers, due to his involvement in the arrests of leading Sinn Féiners in the district. Some of these detainees were mistreated while in custody, leaving the writer in little doubt that the shooting at the constable was carried out by a gunman with a ‘personal gripe’. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5620/13399</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2470</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0267"> F. T. Smyth</persName>
              <date>1916-07-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0753">Mallow, County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">county inspector</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0872">Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2470_img_1906_1"  type="Letter"  url="53219e61d93ba956ea3606a8654a9f59.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2470_img_1906_2"  type="Letter"  url="568152d11c850730c7620fdd7d197482.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2470_img_1906_3"  type="Letter"  url="ced11a3a9171be83def51a1cc7da2a8a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2470_img_1906_4"  type="Letter"  url="4f8e5448719b2c3d801b6b423f0dae36.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2470_img_1906_5"  type="Letter"  url="0ec3a013f7eae7a2a3235fd24b80f323.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2470_img_1906_1"/>
               Firing at the person <lb/><hi rend="underline">Const. Ed. Prendergast 65841</hi>   County of Cork <seg type="del">Cor</seg>   Mallow   20 July 1916    In reply to attached wire I beg to <lb/> state that when Constable Edmond <lb/> Prendergast of Charleville was <lb/> returning to his station across <lb/> the fields at 5¼pm on 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/> May 1916 and when about half <lb/> a mile from his Barracks, he <lb/> sat down on a bank to rest. <lb/> After about ten minutes, a shot <lb/> from a revolver was fired at him. <lb/> Immediately after a second shot <lb/> went through the top of his forage <lb/> cap (not through the peak,) <lb/> which was on his head, and <lb/> pushed well back at the time. <lb/>The Constable them threw himself <lb/> over the bank to the other side, and <lb/> while doing so a third shot was  C. F. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2470_img_1906_2"/>
             fired. The Constable, who had a<lb/>loaded revolver with him, went down<lb/>the field by the fence in the<lb/>direction whence the shots came from<lb/>but saw no person. On investigation<lb/>I found that the person who fired<lb/>the shots would have had time to<lb/>run along a bank - a fence - and<lb/>conceal himself from view<lb/>before the Constable reached his<lb/>point of observation.  This Constable is obnoxious to<lb/>members of the Charleville Irish<lb/>Volunteers, in consequence of<lb/>recent activity in arresting Sinn<lb/>Feinners there, and more particularly<lb/>in January last when three<lb/>leading Sinn Feiners were<lb/>arrested on suspicion re malicious<lb/>injury to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Maddens Hotel. While<lb/>those prisoners were in custody at<lb/>the police Barracks, Constable<lb/>Prendergast, who was Barrack<lb/>Orderly, declined to permit them<lb/>to have any intoxicating drink.  Between 7pm &amp; 11pm Lieut.<lb/>Underwood on the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 16 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2470_img_1906_3"/>
            <lb/> who was in charge of Military <lb/> detachment at Charleville, <lb/> accompanied by the police, <lb/> arrested on suspicion 14 Young <lb/> men — all Sinn Feiners — and <lb/> detained them in custody, until <lb/> the following day when Brigadier <lb/> General Stafford arriving at <lb/> Charleville Railway station, after <lb/> inquiring into the case, directed <lb/> Major Seymour Officer <lb/> Commanding troops at Mallow <lb/> to discharge all the prisoners.   Except for the fact that they belonged <lb/> to the Sinn Fein organisation <lb/> there was no evidence against <lb/> them.   After investigation and <lb/> inquiry I have no doubt but <lb/> that the shots were fired by <lb/> some Sinn Feiner and this <lb/> person may have had a personal <lb/> grudge against the Constable.   As I have said, the
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2470_img_1906_4"/>
            Constable while resting on the <lb/> bank had his cap pushed well <lb/> back on his head and the bullet <lb/> which passed through it could <lb/> do so without inflicting injury <lb/> to the Constable's head. The <lb/> allegation that he did it himself <lb/> is to my mind absurd. There was <lb/> no motive for it and there was <lb/> quite motive enough for some <lb/> Sinn Feiner to do it. Again <lb/> on the Constable's return to the <lb/> Barrack the revolver and <lb/> ammunition which he took <lb/> on duty with him  were examined by Const. , who found <lb/> both correct, the revolver not having <lb/> been used. The Constable had <lb/> no other revolver.   There was no doubt in my <lb/> mind, and I believe the military <lb/> were of the same opinion, but that <lb/> the Constable was deliberately <lb/> fired at.   The Sinn Fein Section in <lb/> Charleville allege that the
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2470_img_1906_5"/>
            Constable fired at his cap <lb/> himself but I doubt if they <lb/> really believe it.   Police inquiries continue <lb/> but nothing has transpired.  <closer F H Smyth </seg>  County Inspector's Office, <lb/>Cork 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> July 1916 <lb/>Submitted. <lb/>I made personal inquiry <lb/> into this matter at Charleville <lb/> on the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, visited the <lb/> scene and interrogated <lb/> several persons, but I gleaned <lb/> nothing to throw any light <lb/> on it. <lb/> T.A. Howe <lb/> CI 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>