<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4258">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 9 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/94</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4258</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4258_img_3624_1"  type="Letter"  url="ae059cc1ba7a7d927399080ea13a6d5c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4258_img_3624_2"  type="Letter"  url="8f1fca4457836f625118be110c8e9ab1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4258_img_3624_3"  type="Letter"  url="70f905916b72ba0de0ac7ed9d42383b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4258_img_3624_4"  type="Letter"  url="816dc701ab20db722351ef9396b9cd85.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4258_img_3624_5"  type="NULL"  url="2848e1a582cb18afcfd8a86d19b65a77.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4258_img_3624_6"  type="NULL"  url="7491f4cd87cd08baa2e8f3c7e4bbe352.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4258_img_3624_1"/>
             9 XII. 15   My P r.   Some nice &amp; ever welcome letters from you. I <lb/> am so glad you &amp; Mater have got on so well <lb/> together but I am not the least afraid that <lb/> you would outstay your welcome or that the <lb/> p r would cease to be a very dear 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>( ??3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>) <lb/> daughter to her.   I have written to Mr <seg type="unclear">Sclater</seg> &amp; said what <lb/> you wrote about not writing yourself, &amp; that <lb/> "She <seg type="del">was</seg> <hi rend="underline">is</hi>  one of those whose  simple  kindliness <hi rend="underline">has</hi> an <lb/> influence of which she was probably quite unaware" <lb/> &amp; that I had the most grateful recollections of their <lb/> goodness to you at the beginning of the war &amp; when
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4258_img_3624_2"/>
            you were sick.   I hope to hear tomorrow how your com- <lb/>mittee accept the results of your mission, but <lb/> unless I am mistaken "some" of them will say <lb/> that you have given way too much. I am quite <lb/> aware now that there is no animal who <lb/> can get her way with tigresses, Mrs Bears <lb/> or even b ws like a p r. I can see her <lb/>going up to a ferocious tigress — or a tiger still <lb/> more I fear ! — &amp; licking her nose &amp; then gambo l<lb/>ing like a too active puppy in order to attract <lb/> first an amused attention, &amp; at last an attentive <lb/> hearing when she sits up &amp; delivers a sermon !    I find it much harder to write to the family
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4258_img_3624_3"/>
            than used to be the case &amp; think I shall have to <lb/> go in for a greater extension of buff slips — not to them.    Please tell Mrs P KS that I will do what <lb/> I can — which is exactly nil — in regard to his <lb/> leave. No I will not put myself last for leave <lb/> but obviously I don't come first or the p r would <lb/> no doubt decide, &amp; it is possible that I might <lb/> let Rich.. precede me as a special cae in order to <lb/> see his little Jim.    For Xmas the best present you can get is <lb/> something which you want &amp; which will <hi rend="underline">last</hi> till <lb/> my return after the war.   No there is one thing, no 2 you can get me <lb/> a toothbrush a dose of salts either magnesia or <lb/> the 2 powders but only a very small quantity. We have <lb/> orders to be ready to move at shortest notice &amp; as it is
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4258_img_3624_4"/>
            Douglas may have to deposit some things for me or <lb/> I may have to send them home.   By the way I have cashed 2 cheques of <lb/> F125 + the first one of F 100 since I came out <lb/> in payment of mess-bills. I enclose a bill you <lb/> may pay if you like sometime but there ought <lb/> really to be more discount at any rate another <lb/> -/6 which please deduct !    Please make things quite clear to the Dean of Belfast <lb/> as you have spoken   Lord Farnham is responsible for HQ Units.   As the Division is getting out a private kine- <lb/>ma ( at £300) which however will probably soon be <lb/> repaid, you can see there is no lack of comforts <lb/> for the men. If only we could teach them to <lb/> think of the future it would be good work, but <lb/> the difficulties even for a p r are I fear too immense. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4258_img_3624_5"/>
             If Gen' <seg type="unclear">Friend</seg>did not remember the p r the b w <lb/> would like to eat him indeed.   Sorry to hear the Pater is only moderately well.   Please <hi rend="underline">Disabuse</hi> Mrs G of her idea about <lb/> Gen' N being a RC &amp; do it soon or you <lb/> will be held responsible. He has been extraordin- <lb/>arily friendly to me lately since my litlle flare up ! <lb/> <I don't think it will last very long.  <lb/>but I'm sorry to say he seems to be having a ten <lb/>dency to snub Russell. I do hope this is not <lb/> the case.    Very wet yesterday &amp; today &amp; both <lb/> days R wanted me to do long motor drives <lb/> with him on duty which either  one  could have done, so
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4258_img_3624_6"/>
            I haven't had much exercise.    Richardson as nice as ever but a <lb/> litlle gloomy.   Always <lb/> your b w    Wilfrid BSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>