<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5618">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Dillon to Lady Elizabeth Mathew, 25 April - 1 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Dillon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Irish Parliamentary Party leader and MP John Dillon (1851-1927) to his mother in law Lady Elizabeth Mathew (d. 1933). This is a 110 page letter written between 25 April (the second day of the Rising) and 1 May 1916 recounting events in during the Rising. The letter contains fascinating detail about the events in Dublin including those experienced by Dillon himself as well as news, reports, rumours and gossip given to Dillon by family and colleagues. Dillon was the only Irish Parliamentary Party leader in Dublin during the Rising and spent the week confined to his house in North Great George&#39;s Street, a short distance from the rebel headquarters in the GPO. He went on to denounced the execution of the leaders in Westminster in a now famous speech on 11 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>Ms. 9820</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5618</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date>1916-04-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1970">2 North Great George&#39;s Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Mathew</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_1"  type="NULL"  url="7170e970c88fb6bc76b190bfa801d850.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_2"  type="NULL"  url="142211eb7fb58b3974cc71700f0f68d6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_3"  type="NULL"  url="7b6ba76c2e12640053babfa0e06a0f39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_4"  type="NULL"  url="5bfae7d42205c5146c601df1b3a79975.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_5"  type="NULL"  url="9103335fac6444da051e4c8863c00d90.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_6"  type="NULL"  url="a6c664cc1465ba9af5f2b9ab40a8956f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_7"  type="NULL"  url="1f84f19350096f8dc6d7ce8543dc4719.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_8"  type="NULL"  url="55bcd7696424ad1977c9868b2220faeb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_9"  type="NULL"  url="309c0e4b555f7b0cb55ddbf1dfd707f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_10"  type="NULL"  url="62990f868c770529981c8e5a90b2a424.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_11"  type="NULL"  url="d1cab75041310d2597b6ab01528c0008.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_12"  type="NULL"  url="85201a2e6668f49d269474ac23e6a60a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_13"  type="NULL"  url="99b894ae3f9c520d32f6ff7d20b6539a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_14"  type="NULL"  url="a74f70f2e66bd9306861eadbcc4a3c97.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_15"  type="NULL"  url="98cdb10b5d9c7b3ef50df8ae855485f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_16"  type="NULL"  url="ad698c23803b49434fbe3037ed362cbf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_17"  type="NULL"  url="73131f2124ae001214f0db025cfc6201.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_18"  type="NULL"  url="12bd093d28cc0e7e95de5ed9fe4e8b5c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_19"  type="NULL"  url="f3a6f230ff0b606de8f984769ad6b72a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_20"  type="NULL"  url="c1793d4732b202c02589ca3cd1b92a34.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_21"  type="NULL"  url="14959e3f490ba3b068f5b04c897f8210.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_22"  type="NULL"  url="872a029a2380e1e0758369901acfe3e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_23"  type="NULL"  url="380a769a2bad7879985a20b3eed59031.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_24"  type="NULL"  url="47106e4791116deee00544eb761ef283.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_25"  type="NULL"  url="9c7f293b6c0b5de4da9869af04ee7433.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_26"  type="NULL"  url="5018db09fb2a25c10a08fb299765eba1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_27"  type="NULL"  url="3e3336341725a47dab792be9b4204c5b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_28"  type="NULL"  url="cb264849f960d8099852cf1d72c1d3b2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_29"  type="NULL"  url="7117a55a5c696937997672c268954fb2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_30"  type="NULL"  url="81172a82b19a261feb092cb880ce788c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_31"  type="NULL"  url="21df3c6a401fe0ad7d945e4fc7883d98.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_32"  type="NULL"  url="3d100f3f0fa2b54a578bc8f12e991939.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_33"  type="NULL"  url="0fb73c84d6f29228bda3df98cf31028a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_34"  type="NULL"  url="870770b69922f36d24897f6075c1c301.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_35"  type="NULL"  url="f1dce90098ada9566bdf9886c6a08702.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_36"  type="NULL"  url="54cf73ae8353d922b47e22e6736d63c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_37"  type="NULL"  url="bdc17a712b0cb42766dfda5dcd6d01b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_38"  type="NULL"  url="c4b1c3d90d765332422ddc88cacbaa63.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_39"  type="NULL"  url="c0d376b9a3018637223caff4c6014fe2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_40"  type="NULL"  url="6121f80f48728ef8bac4bbb58265d4e1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_41"  type="NULL"  url="69eaec9b2848fa1ef31e2e9ccfca0546.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_42"  type="NULL"  url="f82464746523e7ed2270b480f97ef034.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_43"  type="NULL"  url="10ae486224d7f5ad03f8de4f8a4552a8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_44"  type="NULL"  url="c6c8bca14eafea7438817e2666f2a73c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_45"  type="NULL"  url="27c7ac7a76c291377d7e0d503f4675bd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_46"  type="NULL"  url="7131950e65ae13851cdc651912a35c9b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_47"  type="NULL"  url="4ca606e92a2f8c0ce8cbf805ee2280aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_48"  type="NULL"  url="38e9007f90fbfc4ec2ed7ff4d638d92b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_49"  type="NULL"  url="0057a19d2c409e17b408f8f1196753f4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_50"  type="NULL"  url="49ef03428a76b46b702054ed7b43be92.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_51"  type="NULL"  url="8f3576a0fd2b94575c253bb460b626d6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_52"  type="NULL"  url="2957ff0b3168a6f0bf9532164fb84412.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_53"  type="NULL"  url="6a0f3e207668fbd7e7438ca28fcea6bf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_54"  type="NULL"  url="58d3b5b7bd5df83b110ed6df9d6825c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_55"  type="NULL"  url="37bcbbc7c4d5fc3ef8045a0d10a39bd3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5618_img_712_56"  type="NULL"  url="f208e2e0da4d7434feda30914bba7fbc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_1"/>
              2 North Georges Street. <lb/>Dublin   Monday 25 April 1916  <lb/> 4.30    My dear Lady Mathew  <lb/>We have had a <lb/>wild day here — But the <lb/>family are all safe — <lb/>and for the time being <lb/>out of the fighting zone. <lb/>At 12.30 Myles rushed <lb/>in very hot &amp; excited <lb/>and told me that 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_2"/>
             the Sinn Féiners — had <lb/>entrenched themselves in <lb/>Stephens Green — and <lb/>were marching on the Castle. <lb/>He had followed them <lb/>for some distance — <lb/>and then when firing commenced <lb/>very wisely ran away — <lb/>He also told us that <lb/>they were in possession <lb/>of the General Post Office    and that fighting was <lb/>going on in O'Connell <lb/>St. Standing at the <lb/>door here —we could hear <lb/>heavy firing going on <lb/>in various parts of the <lb/>City. Happily Nano <lb/>was at home — But <lb/><seg type="unclear">Jamie</seg> and Brian had <lb/> just gone out &amp; <seg type="unclear">proceeded</seg> <lb/>down O'Connell St. — <lb/>and Shaun was at 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_3"/>
             12o'c Mass at Adam &amp; Eve — <lb/>on the Quays — Jim <lb/>had gone out to the <lb/>Park with a school <lb/>friend — You may <lb/>imagine I was rather <lb/>unhappy till they all <lb/>returned safely — which they all <lb/>did in about half an <lb/>hour.   <seg type="unclear">Jamie</seg> &amp; Brian were <lb/>caught just below the Parnell    monument — and when <lb/>the firing began — they took <lb/>refuge in the <seg type="unclear">Hammam</seg> <lb/>Hotel — and then took <lb/>advantage of a lull to <lb/>escape home.   Shaun had various <lb/>adventures — but <lb/>finally got home <lb/>untouched — He had <lb/>walked up O'Connell St. — <lb/>to the corner of Abbey St — 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_4"/>
             before he realised that <lb/>there was any trouble <lb/>in the Post Office — <lb/>Theobald is spending <lb/>the day at Glenageary — <lb/>and I have sent him <lb/>a telephone message to <lb/>stay with his friends <lb/>for the night. So far <lb/>this street has been <lb/>perfectly quiet — <lb/>But the wildest rumours <lb/>reach us from time to <lb/>time — from passers by — <lb/>we are told that <lb/>the Castle has been taken <lb/>also the Bank of Ireland.   Tuesday  26 April    Here I was interrupted <lb/>yesterday — I find there is  no  <lb/>possibility of getting a letter — <lb/>or telegram through — <lb/>but I shall continue this
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_5"/>
             narrative as it may interest <lb/>you — when this miserable <lb/>business is all over —  At 4<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> <seg type="unclear">Mary</seg> Dillon <lb/>came in — she had made <lb/>her way down as far <lb/>as Nelson's Pillar — Shortly <lb/>before she got there a <lb/>squadron of the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Lancers <lb/>had gone down Rutland <lb/>Sq — towards O'Connell — <lb/> for which purpose Heaven — <lb/><hi rend="underline">9820 3</hi> <lb/>knows —<seg type="unclear">Mary</seg> saw two <lb/>dead horses lying in <lb/>front of the General Post <lb/>Office — and was <lb/>informed by a man in <lb/>the crowd — that the <lb/>Commanding Officer of the <lb/>Lancers had been shot <lb/>from the Post Office &amp; <lb/>carried off in a dying
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_6"/>
             condition —The man <lb/>then added that <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>the <lb/>Lancers turned tail.   O'Connell Street was <lb/>crowded by a perfectly <lb/>orderly crowd apparently <lb/>taking a big interest <lb/>in the proceedings.   The inhabitants of the <lb/>Slums were busy looting <lb/>the shops.    All <seg type="del">deleted text</seg><sic>yesterday</sic> afternoon <lb/>and again this morning <lb/>a steady stream of <lb/>women — girls &amp; young <lb/>children have passed <lb/>up the street laden with loot — clothes — <lb/>boots, boxes of sweets <lb/>  &amp;c. <seg type="del">It's</seg> <hi rend="superscript">It is</hi>  horrible <lb/>to see some well dressed <lb/>respectable looking <lb/>girls — laden with loot —
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_7"/>
            <lb/>Just now a woman passed <lb/>with a baby's perambulator <lb/>piled with boots. <seg type="unclear">Ismay</seg> <lb/>informed us that before <lb/>she left the Hospital a <lb/>child was brought in <lb/>with a bullet through <lb/>its arm &amp; the little <lb/>creature had collected <lb/>several boxes of sweets <lb/>at Noblets shop  <lb/>9820 4 <lb/>and was making off <lb/>with them when it was <lb/>shot. The man who <lb/>brought in the child <lb/>was careful to say that <lb/>it was shot by a <lb/>Sinn Féiner and not <lb/>by the soldiers.   Desultory firing all <seg type="del"></seg>round <lb/>this <seg type="del"></seg>house went on <lb/>all the afternoon and
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_8"/>
            <lb/>evening — and it was <lb/>impossible to get any definite <lb/>news of what is taking place.   At 5 <hi rend="superscript">o'c</hI> a lady — who <lb/>had an appointment with <lb/>Mr &amp; Mrs O'Farrell <lb/>called — She informed me <lb/>that she had motored <lb/>in from the country — <lb/>was stopped at a <lb/>barricade outside Dublin —  <lb/>by a youth with a <lb/>revolver — Her motor <lb/>was commandeered — <lb/>and when she asked <lb/>what had happened — <lb/>The youth replied — <seg type="del">he</seg>"<hi rend="superscript">we</hi> asked for a Republic. <lb/>They would not give it <lb/> so we took it"!    I should have said <lb/>that <seg type="unclear">Mary</seg> reported that <lb/>large placards were
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_9"/>
            <lb/>posted in O'Connell St. <lb/>announcing the foundation <lb/>of the Irish Republic. — <lb/>And the new Irish <lb/>Republican Tricolour was <lb/>flying over the G.P.O. <lb/>Harold <seg type="del"> </seg>Cochran - Mrs <lb/>Tuthill's grandson — came <lb/>in and <seg type="del">if</seg>informed that <lb/>they had a telephone message from his aunt — <lb/>9820 5 <lb/>from Vincent's Hospital to say <lb/>that 20 dead had been <lb/>carried into that hospital <lb/>already.   At seven oclock a <lb/>furious fusillade of rifle <lb/>fire &amp; machine guns <lb/>broke out and lasted <lb/>for almost twenty minutes <lb/> — we could get no information <lb/> where it was or what was the
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_10"/>
            <lb/>result.   I was very much afraid <lb/>that the slum people <lb/>would break into the <lb/>public houses and that <lb/>the city at night would <lb/>be in the hands of howling <lb/>drunken mob.   <seg type="del">All </seg>So I kept the children <lb/> all sitting up till <lb/>12.30 —Then the  <lb/>city was absolutely quiet — <lb/>we all went to bed — <lb/>About 1.30 a <seg type="del">furious</seg> <lb/>fusillade suddenly <lb/>broke out again — <lb/>machine guns &amp; rifles — <lb/>and some of the firing <lb/>seemed to be quite <lb/>close in Gardiners Row — <lb/>or Rutland Sq. — <lb/>We were all out <lb/>of bed again &amp;
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_11"/>
            <lb/>assembled in Nano's <lb/>room &amp; you would <lb/>really imagine that you <lb/>were in the middle of a battle.   The appearance of the <lb/>street as <seg type="del"> </seg>viewed from <lb/>this house has been <lb/>most extraordinary — <lb/>a constant flow of <lb/>people - largely women &amp; young girls — <lb/>9820 6 <lb/>going &amp; coming without <lb/><hi rend="underline">the slightest appearance</hi> <lb/> of excitement — more <lb/>than double as many <lb/>people as one would <lb/>see in these streets on any <lb/>ordinary day — The only <lb/>thing remarkable being their <lb/>absolute silence — No <lb/>one seems to speak. <lb/>In the intervals between <lb/>the outbursts of firing
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_12"/>
            <lb/>there is almost eerie <lb/>silence — you could hear <lb/>a pin drop — <seg type="del"><seg type="unclear"> </seg></seg>Then <lb/>a few scattered shots — <lb/>Then a fierce fusillade — <lb/>Then again silence — <lb/>And occasional <seg type="del"></seg><hi rend="superscript">shrieks</hi> <lb/>&amp; shots in the distance. <lb/>At 2<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> we all went <lb/>to bed again &amp; slept <lb/>soundly till 7<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> — when  <lb/>we were roused by <lb/>a terrific fusillade — <lb/>This time there was <seg type="del"></seg>the <lb/>sound of heavy guns — <lb/>and something that <lb/>sounded like a big <lb/>explosion.    On looking out while <lb/>dressing I was amazed <lb/>to see the bread cart <lb/>— milk cart going <lb/>round as usual —
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_13"/>
            <lb/>Our milk man came at <lb/>9.15 —and brought <lb/>a budget of news — <lb/>he was driving along <lb/>behind two bread <lb/>vans &amp; the Volunteers <lb/>held up the bread vans <lb/>and while the men <lb/>  with the bread <lb/>vans he turned tail <lb/>&amp; made off pursued  <lb/>9820 7 <lb/>by the Volunteers. <lb/>We laid in an extra <lb/>supply. He told us <lb/>that <seg type="del"> </seg>  a racing man  had come <lb/>up <seg type="unclear">of</seg> from Cork yesterday <lb/>in a motor all the <lb/>way - that the insurrection <lb/>has broken out in Cork <lb/>and in Kerry — and <lb/>that on his way he <lb/>was held up at <lb/>several barricades —
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_14"/>
            <lb/>He also told us that <lb/>all thro the night <lb/>the Sinn Féiners had been <lb/>firing on the Constabulary <lb/>Barracks in Phoenix <lb/>Park — and that <lb/>they had taken the <lb/>barracks this morning. <lb/>After breakfast I took <lb/>stock of provisions in the <lb/>house &amp; sent out Lizzie <lb/> to buy all she could get <lb/>&amp; and I am glad to say <lb/>she has just arrived <lb/>accompanied by two <lb/> boys with large stores —   3<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi>   Theo arrived safely at <lb/>1<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> — He had a <lb/>rather adventurous journey — <lb/>had to go round by Bray and <lb/>Harcourt Street — as <lb/>Westland Row in the hands <lb/>of the enemy. When he reached
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_15"/>
            <seg type="del">Do</seg>College Green — he found <lb/>the Military in possession <lb/>of T.C.D. — firing out <lb/>of the windows up Dame <lb/>Street — and had to wait <lb/>for a lull in the firing <lb/>before he crossed — <seg type="del">St</seg>At <lb/>Nelsons Pillar two barbed <lb/>wires were stretched across the <lb/>Street — and he had to <lb/>stoop under the wires to <lb/>pass. <lb/>9820 8 <lb/>O'Connell Street was <lb/>still crowded with <lb/>people.   At 2.30 Christie <lb/>Redmond M - Devlin's Sec — <lb/>called — He had collected <lb/>a great mass of information — <lb/>Had witnessed some severe <lb/>fighting — in which the soldiers <lb/>suffered severely.   Among the items of information <lb/>he brought me was that <lb/>two priests had been shot.
            <pb n="16" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_16"/>
            <lb/>That it was rumoured that <lb/>at Beggars Bush Barracks <lb/>the Sinn Féiners had occupied <lb/>a row of houses opposite <lb/>the Barracks and were <lb/>firing into it — And <lb/>that inside the Barracks <lb/>the two Irish Regiments <lb/>occupying the Barracks <lb/>the Royal Irish and <lb/> the Connaught Rangers — <lb/>had fallen out and were  <lb/>firing on each other. <lb/>He told me that the Castle <lb/>had <hi rend="underline">not</hi>been taken — <lb/> but was still occupied <lb/>by the Military — and <lb/>that he had seen the <lb/><seg type="del">Military</seg>soldiers on top <lb/>of the City Hall — from <lb/>which they had driven the <lb/>Sinn Féiners. <lb/>That the S.F. s had <lb/>blown up a bridge on
            <pb n="17" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_17"/>
            <lb/>the Great Northern line <lb/>at Donabate —and had <lb/> there  met the troops coming <lb/>from Belfast by rail — <lb/>and driven them back <lb/>and taken a machine <lb/>gun from them.   We are now informed on <lb/>fairly good authority that <lb/>there are two Warships <lb/>in the Bay — and that <lb/>the Authorities have <lb/>concentrated 9000 troops — <lb/> and are going to clear <lb/>the streets with Artillery <seg type="del"> </seg> <lb/>commencing at 4<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> this afternoon —   Many wild rumours are <lb/>flying about — That <lb/>500 men from Kerry arrived <lb/>this morning to reinforce <lb/>the Volunteers — that <lb/>6000 Kerry men &amp; 500 from <lb/>Waterford are marching <seg type="del">from</seg> <lb/>on Dublin. That the <lb/>Germans landed in Tralee
            <pb n="18" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_18"/>
            <lb/>yesterday — that the German <lb/>submarines are in Belfast <lb/>Lough — and landed in Belfast <lb/>yesterday — and attacked <lb/>the Belfast Post Office.   Wednesday 10.30   Wasn't up till 12<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> — <lb/>last night — then as the <lb/>city was fairly quiet we <lb/>all went to bed — looters <lb/>continued to stream up <lb/>Georges Street — far into the night <lb/>laden with <seg type="unclear">bacon</seg> <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>- <lb/>— fruit etc. — and <lb/>could be heard discussing <lb/>their booty with great <lb/>satisfaction — a considerable <lb/>number of drunken women <lb/>and girls were heard in <lb/>the street.   I slept soundly &amp; was <lb/>woken shortly after seven <lb/>by firing — at about <lb/>a quarter to 8<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> — a violent
            <pb n="19" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_19"/>
            <lb/>fusillade broke out — <lb/>machine guns, rifle &amp; <lb/>field guns — It appeared <lb/>to be very near — lasted <lb/>for about half an <lb/>hour — then died away. <lb/>When I came down Mrs. <lb/>Dolan told me that a <lb/>woman had just told <lb/>her that about Jacobs <lb/>factory the City was in <lb/>9820 10 <lb/>ruins.   Standing at the door <lb/>a man passing on the <lb/>opposite side of the <lb/>street saluted me &amp; <lb/> asked me — How are <lb/>you Sir"   "Very well I replied — <lb/>as well as one can be <lb/>in such times — <lb/>To which he replied —
            <pb n="20" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_20"/>
            <lb/>If you keep your head <lb/>it will be all right. <lb/>Large numbers of people <lb/>walking about — without <lb/>slightest <seg type="del"></seg>appearance of <lb/>fear or panic — A <lb/>good many apparently <lb/>going down towards Marlboro <lb/>Street and O'Connell St. <lb/>to see what is going <lb/>on. Desultory firing has  <lb/>been going on ever since <lb/>8<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi>. Jim was told <lb/>by Blake next door <lb/>neighbour that his <lb/>brother had been down <lb/>to the Quays — that <lb/>Liberty Hall was laid flat — and <lb/>that there was a gunboat in the <lb/>Liffey — which had bombarded <lb/>the Hall.   What an extraordinary <lb/>experience it is — to be
            <pb n="21" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_21"/>
            <lb/>isolated from the whole <lb/>world — not to be able <lb/>to get the slightest atom <lb/>of reliable information <lb/>as to what is going on. <lb/>Not to know what <lb/>has happened in streets <lb/>within a few hundred <lb/>yards — and to listen <lb/>for two days to the <lb/>firing close at hand <lb/>without being able  <lb/>9820 11 <lb/>to ascertain where it <lb/>has taken place or what <lb/>has been the result.   Found last night that <lb/>Lizzie really obtained <lb/>very little supplies — <lb/>We have sent her &amp; <lb/>Dolan out again in <lb/>search of supplies. <lb/>Last night the gas was cut <lb/>off — and we were reduced
            <pb n="22" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_22"/>
            to lamps &amp; candles.   Friday 28<hi rend="superscript">th   Wrote nothing yesterday — <lb/>It was one of the worst <lb/>days we had — <lb/>About <seg type="del">6.30</seg> 4.30  there was <lb/>a tremendous fusillade — <lb/>accompanied by a good deal <lb/>of firing from field <lb/>guns. Large fires in <lb/>O'Connell Street during  <lb/>the night - Lawrences <lb/>has been burned — during <lb/>the day the fires spread <lb/>and the D.B.C — <lb/> fell in. Fortunately the <lb/>wind was not blowing <lb/>in this direction.   Did not allow any of <lb/>children out to Mass <lb/>as there was continuous <lb/>desultory firing all round. <lb/>In the course of the day <lb/>we were told that
            <pb n="23" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_23"/>
            <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>the authorities <lb/>had given the Insurgents <lb/>in the G.P.O. up to <lb/>3.30 to surrender - after <lb/>that they would proceed <lb/> to shell the G.P.O.   In the course of the <lb/>forenoon — there were <lb/>a succession of <hi rend="underline">furious</hi> <lb/>fusillades in Great Britain <lb/>Street direction — and  <lb/>from the steps I  9820 12  <lb/>could see <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>a picket <lb/>of Soldiers with fixed <lb/>bayonets moving about <lb/>in Great Britain Street <lb/>at foot of this street. <lb/>I sent Theo over to Belvedere <lb/>to find out whether <lb/>Jesuits had any news — <lb/> Father Fahey S.J. <lb/>called about 12<hi rend="superscript'oc</hi>.
            <pb n="24" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_24"/>
            <lb/>He had been a good deal <lb/>round the city — and <lb/>was the first man <lb/> from whom I got <lb/>definite news. He is <lb/>in charge of Dressing <lb/>Station in Dorset Street — <lb/> which was established in <lb/> Chemist shop Cahills at <lb/>corner of Dorset St — and Nth Circular. <lb/>The proprietor of which <lb/>is out with the Volunteers. <lb/>I was very much <lb/>alarmed — thinking the <lb/>military had selected the <lb/>house on purpose — <lb/>Father Fahey reassured <lb/>me — and said the <lb/>selection of house was <lb/>a mere fluke— <lb/>A machine gun was <lb/>placed on roof — and <lb/>then the officer in <lb/>charge proposed to
            <pb n="25" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_25"/>
            <lb/>hang out the Red Cross <lb/>flag — Father Fahey <lb/>remonstrated — and the <lb/>officer said — Oh — I <lb/>forgot all about the <lb/>gun. Afterwards they <lb/>moved the dressing station <lb/>to another house.   Father <seg type="del">Cahill</seg>Fahey informed <lb/>me that up to the present <lb/>the casualties were not all that heavy — <lb/>9820 13 <lb/>and bore no appreciable <lb/>proportion to the prodigious <lb/>expenditure of ammunition. <lb/>Two cases had been treated <lb/>in the Dorset Street dressing <lb/>station. George Fothell <lb/>told me on Wednesday that <lb/>up to then only two dead <lb/> had been brought into <lb/>Vincents.   Father Fahey said that <lb/>several dead bodies were <lb/>lying in Stephens Green — 
            <pb n="26" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_26"/>
            <lb/>He confirmed the story of <lb/>priests <seg type="del">going</seg>having gone <lb/>into the G.P.O. — heard <lb/>confessions of all <lb/>the Garrison — found them <lb/>full of enthusiasm and <lb/>confidence — quite convinced <lb/>that they were in the right <lb/>fighting for Ireland — <lb/>and ready to die for <lb/>the cause. One <seg type="del">man</seg> <lb/>dying man was  <lb/>anointed - and said to <lb/>the priest who anointed <lb/>him that he was proud <lb/>to die for Ireland. <lb/>Father F. told me that <lb/>when he first met the <lb/><seg type="del"> </seg>Officers &amp; soldiers <lb/>coming into Dublin — <lb/>they were in a <seg type="del">very great </seg> <lb/><seg type="del"> </seg> state of extreme <lb/>nervousness — under the <lb/>impression that they <lb/>were coming amongst
            <pb n="27" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_27"/>
            <lb/>a solidly hostile population <lb/>— that they would be <lb/>sniped from every house — <lb/>and would be attacked <lb/>by hostile crowds on all <lb/>sides. He Father F. had <lb/>assured them that they <lb/>were under a wholly false <lb/>impression — that they <lb/>would find the great <lb/>majority of the population <lb/>friendly — and he said  <lb/>that the officers had <lb/>now come to realise that <lb/>in this respect he was quite right.   At 4.30 the big guns <lb/>began —one from Parnell <lb/>Monument — and others <lb/>from other side of <seg type="unclear">river</seg> — <lb/>shelling the G.P.O. <lb/>This was accompanied <lb/>by firm machine gun <lb/>firing — all the <lb/>evening we could get 
            <pb n="28" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_28"/>
            <lb/>no definite or reliable <lb/>information as to results. <lb/>At about 7<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi>  there was  a ring <lb/>at the hall door — and <lb/>on opening it — I found <lb/>a correspondent of the Manchester Guardian — <lb/>He had left Manchester <lb/>on Tuesday evening — <lb/> and survived after many <lb/>difficulties in reaching <lb/>Dublin by way of  <lb/>Belfast &amp; Drogheda — <lb/> by road from Drogheda to Dublin — <lb/>From him I heard some <lb/>outside news — up to <lb/>Tuesday evening &amp; including <lb/>news of  naval  raid on Lowestoft — <lb/>and naval engagement <lb/>resulting which appears <lb/>to have been uncertain. <lb/>First news of Dublin <lb/>outbreak reached <lb/>Manchester at midday
            <pb n="29" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_29"/>
            <lb/>Tuesday — very brief account <lb/>from official Press bureau — <lb/>followed by a statement <lb/>from Mr. Birrell.    Saturday 29 April <lb/>At night the fires in 8.15 <lb/>O'Connell St — and <lb/> Dominic St Church <lb/> in the direction of Linen Hall <lb/>Barracks were so terrible <lb/>that I did not let the <lb/>children go to bed —  <lb/>9820 15 <lb/>we all sat up till <lb/>3<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> — I then arranged <lb/>with the   to sit <lb/>up in relays till full <lb/>daylight — At six <lb/><seg type="unclear">Kevin</seg> called me to say <lb/>that fires were dying down <lb/>and there was no danger <lb/>to house —and we <lb/>slept till 9 — breakfast <lb/> at 9.45 — About <lb/>8oc there was a <seg type="unclear">raging</seg>
            <pb n="30" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_30"/>
            <lb/>fusilade — the big guns <lb/>going again.   <seg type="del">George</seg> On Friday (yesterday) <lb/>foreman of <seg type="unclear">Fothell</seg> called <lb/>in &amp; told me that <lb/>the authorities had given <lb/>up to 4.30 to the <lb/>garrison in G.P.O. <lb/>to surrender — after that <lb/>they proposed to shell <lb/>the place. <lb/>At <seg type="del">four</seg> 4.30  <lb/>there was a tremendous <lb/>rattle of machine guns <lb/>and — considerable <lb/> firing of field guns — <lb/> then a lull — Later <lb/>we could see the G. <lb/>P.O. burning fiercely . <lb/>The firing round this <lb/>house was much <lb/>more constant &amp; violent <lb/>on Friday — than on <lb/> any previous day — <lb/>A proclamation had
            <pb n="31" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_31"/>
            <lb/>been issued on Thursday <lb/>— warning people not to <lb/>congregate on the streets and <lb/>to be in doors between <lb/><sic>between</sic><seg type="del">6am and</seg> <lb/>7.30P.M. &amp; 6A.M. <lb/>And on yesterday for <lb/>the first time the streets <lb/>became very deserted. <lb/>About 5<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> — sitting in <lb/>the study — a quantity of <lb/>9820 16 <lb/>bullets passed the windows <lb/>&amp; struck Belvedere <lb/>College — After a bit <lb/>there was a lull and a <lb/>ring came to the door <lb/>— I opened it — and <lb/>found a small boy from <lb/>the Plaza Hotel — <lb/>who said I was called <lb/>up to the Castle — <lb/>After some hesitation <lb/>I decided to go —
            <pb n="32" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_32"/>
            <lb/>I was called in at Moloney's <lb/>Hotel — next door — <lb/>men standing in the <lb/>hall begged me not <lb/>to venture — saying <lb/>that bullets were coming <lb/>up Georges St — and <lb/>also over the wall <lb/>at the back of the houses <lb/>— and along Gardiners <lb/>Row from Findlater's Church. <lb/>I tried to use the <lb/>telephone at Moloney's <lb/> — but failed to connect. — <lb/> So I ran across <lb/>the Plaza — where I <lb/>had a short talk with Nathan — He   Sunday 30 April <lb/>10<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> <lb/>I was interrupted yesterday — <lb/>Nathan told me he had <lb/>an urgent message from <lb/>Redmond saying he was
            <pb n="33" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_33"/>
            <lb/>eagerly awaiting Miss O'Brien <lb/>with important message from <lb/>Dillon — and asking Castle <lb/>whether they could communicate <lb/>with Dillon — I said I <lb/>had sent Miss O'Brien <lb/>on Tuesday night —Nathan <lb/>replied he knew that — but <lb/>she had been quite unable <lb/>to get across town.   I asked him to repeat <lb/>to R my urgent request  <lb/>9820 17 <lb/>that he should remain <lb/>in London until I had <lb/>an opportunity of communicating <lb/>fully with him   He told me Birrell was <lb/>in the Castle — <lb/>Asked me how are you? <lb/>I replied all right — <lb/>The fires in the City are <lb/> terrible — To which he replied <lb/>I know that — I then said
            <pb n="34" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_34"/>
            <lb/>they have been firing up <lb/>Georges Street <seg type="del">all</seg>this <lb/>afternoon, to which he replied <lb/>I am aware of that also. <lb/>No further communication passed.   A man in the Hall of <lb/>the Plaza told me <lb/>that Verdun had fallen. <lb/>I had a few words with <lb/>Radcliffe of the M.G. <lb/>He seemed very much <lb/>depressed — disheartened <lb/>at his position — had not <lb/>been able to collect any <lb/>news.   A young lady spoke to <lb/>me — and said that <lb/>in Barry's Hotel — they <lb/>were in a terrible position. <lb/>There were 30 people in the <lb/> Hotel and only one <lb/>loaf —and they could
            <pb n="35" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_35"/>
            <lb/>not get any bread — <lb/>she had succeeded in <lb/>getting into communication <lb/>with Captain Kelly on <lb/>the telephone — and he <lb/>had promised to have <lb/>either bread or flour <lb/>delivered in this quarter <lb/>tomorrow Saturday — While <lb/>I was speaking at <lb/>telephone some bullets had  <lb/>9820 18 <lb/>passed up Gardiners Row. <lb/> After waiting for a bit <lb/> in the hall I made a <lb/> bolt for home. On my <lb/>way I enquired at Moloneys <lb/>Hotel as to possibility of <lb/>communicating with <seg type="del">West of</seg> <lb/>Mayo — But was told <lb/>it was absolutely impossible <lb/> to do so.   10.20 <lb/>Just at the moment the
            <pb n="36" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_36"/>
            <lb/>milkman arrived — he said <lb/>he was talking to a <lb/>Major on his way in <lb/>and was told by him that <lb/>the troops were now getting <lb/>ready to sweep the <lb/>country — and that the <lb/>worst thing they had to <lb/>face was Dolphins Barn. <lb/>As I was going to the <lb/>door to open it to speak <lb/>to the milkman a posse <lb/>of about 10 policemen  <lb/>came down Gardiners Row <lb/>and passed on towards <lb/>Findlaters Church — The <lb/>first sight of a policeman's <lb/>uniform I have <lb/><seg type="del">seen</seg> had  since Monday <lb/>morning last. Very strange <lb/>the feeling of satisfaction <lb/>and joy with which I <lb/>saw the uniforms — as a <lb/> sign of returning security <lb/> and peace.—
            <pb n="37" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_37"/>
            <lb/>The milkman said that <lb/> there had been a terrible <lb/>naval battle off Lowestoft <lb/> that 14 German and <lb/>8 British Ships had <lb/>been sunk. — That fifteen <lb/>Zeppelins had attacked <lb/>London — and that <lb/>London was a wreck.   So far I have not got <lb/><seg type="del">a scrap of</seg> any  news of the <lb/>outside world — except <lb/>scraps — rumours collected in this way. <lb/>982019 <lb/>Shawn came in just now. — <lb/> I had sent him to Dominic <lb/>St. to ascertain whether the <lb/>Church is open &amp; whether <lb/>it is quiet &amp; safe in that <lb/>region — He reported the <lb/>Church open — morning <lb/>congregation — all quite <lb/>peaceable — He saw Father <lb/>Costelloe — who was eager <lb/>to learn whether I knew <lb/>what had really happened.
            <pb n="38" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_38"/>
            <lb/>Shawn said I knew nothing <lb/>more than the ordinary <lb/>man in the street. <lb/>Father Costelloe said that <lb/>he was informed that the <lb/>casualties amongst the <lb/>soldiers were enormous.   I take up again the <lb/>narrative at Friday evening <lb/>where I broke off to deal <lb/>with the arrival of the milkman. <lb/>On Friday night the <lb/>fires were still raging <lb/> in O'Connell Street <lb/> &amp; in two or three other <lb/>places in the distance. <lb/>But as there was <lb/><seg type="del">not</seg>no apparent danger <lb/>of their spreading to <lb/>this Street — we <lb/>went to bed early . <lb/><seg type="del">during the night</seg> <lb/>At night - <seg type="del">bef</seg> <lb/>we sat in the parlour
            <pb n="39" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_39"/>
            <lb/>as the firing continued in <lb/>Georges St -—except <lb/>from desultory firing the <lb/>street was as silent <lb/>as a Churchyard. <lb/>During the night I <lb/> slept soundly — But <lb/>in the morning I was <lb/>informed by Nano — that <lb/>there had been a fierce <lb/>battle in the street.  <lb/>9820 20 <lb/>It seems the soldiers had <lb/>during the night opened <lb/>fire on some of the houses <lb/> in Georges Street in which <lb/>snipers were lodged. <lb/>Fortunately no bullets <lb/>struck this house.   Saturday morning was <lb/>as usual — with a good <lb/>deal of firing . <lb/>About 12oc Father Fahy
            <pb n="40" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_40"/>
            <lb/>called, and said he had come <lb/>to consult me — as to what <lb/>could be done to get bread <lb/> for the people . The women <lb/>were rushing to him from all <lb/>sides calling for bread <lb/>and saying that their <lb/>children were dying of <lb/>hunger. He told me <lb/>a long tale of his adventure <lb/>with the Military Officer <lb/> — It seems they will not  <lb/>allow anyone to pass the <lb/>cordons — except under <lb/>very strict conditions — <lb/> and it has not been <lb/>possible for <seg type="del">an</seg>a great <lb/>many   to get to <lb/>Kennedys shop . I advised <lb/>him on a course of <lb/>proceeding — During his <lb/> visit he told me a <lb/>very pathetic story — A <lb/> young man had stopped him <seg type="del">shortl</seg>during his morning
            <pb n="41" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_41"/>
            <lb/>his morning round &amp; saying I <lb/>want to shake hands with <lb/>you — aren't we doing <lb/>splendidly? — he <lb/>then explained that he had been <lb/>at home to spend the night <lb/>with his family and was now <lb/>on his way to relieve <lb/>Guard — Father Fahy <lb/>remonstrated with him using <lb/>very strong — <seg type="del"></seg> and in  rather <lb/>cruel language — said <lb/>he regarded their conduct  <lb/>9820 21 <lb/>as murder — asked him <lb/>was he married — To this <lb/>the man replied that he had <lb/>a wife &amp; three young children. <lb/>And you are leaving them <lb/> to fight for a lost cause <lb/>— said Father Fahy — <lb/>a cause in which you can <lb/> do no good — but a vast <lb/>deal of mischief — <lb/>At this <seg type="del">the</seg>tears streamed <lb/>down the face of the <lb/>unhappy youth —
            <pb n="42" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_42"/>
            <lb/>But he was quite fine <lb/> —said he must do his duty — <lb/> that spiritually he was <lb/>all right and ready to <lb/>die — as he had been <lb/>to the sacraments and <lb/>was doing no wrong — <lb/>and what object can <lb/>you hope to achieve <lb/> said Father F. — "Some <lb/>of us must die — But <lb/>we shall save Ireland <lb/>from Conscription. <lb/>Father F. then pressed him <lb/>to come into Berkeley <lb/>St. Church and say <lb/>three Hail <sic>Maries</sic> — But <lb/>he refused to and <lb/>went on his way.   All seemed going <lb/> usual till <seg type="del">lunch</seg> dinner  time. <lb/>1.30 — After that <lb/> there was a complete <lb/>cessation of firing <lb/>and something had
            <pb n="43" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_43"/>
            <lb/>happened - people began <lb/>to emerge from the houses — <lb/>and gradually the streets <lb/>became almost crowded <lb/> — groups eagerly talking — <lb/>women moving about <lb/> looking for bread &amp; <lb/> provisions of all kinds. <lb/>At various times through <lb/>the forenoon milk <lb/>carts had appeared in the <lb/>Street —the arrival of each  <lb/>9820 22 <lb/>cart being the occasion <lb/>of an extraordinary scene — <lb/> women &amp; girls &amp; <seg type="del"></seg> servant-maid  <lb/> rushing at the cart with <lb/>bowls — jugs etc. — and <lb/>scrambling for milk.   About 3<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> standing on <lb/>the steps — <seg type="unclear">Jemma</seg> who <lb/>had been out for milk <lb/>called — look — look <lb/> the soldiers are advancing <lb/> up the Street with bayonets
            <pb n="44" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_44"/>
            <lb/>fixed — I looked and <lb/>saw an extraordinary sight <lb/>three soldiers — two <lb/>of them <seg type="del">bo</seg>diminutive boys — <lb/>with arms of any <seg type="unclear">kind</seg> — <lb/> and the third carrying a <lb/> rifle and bayonet in an <lb/>awkward fashion as <lb/> if half afraid of it <lb/> walked up past our <lb/>door — and turned into  <lb/>Gardiners Place — some <lb/>one than told us that <lb/>a woman asked one of <lb/>the soldiers as they <lb/> passed — Is it peace? <lb/>and he replied <lb/>Yes peace has been <lb/>proclaimed. For a <lb/>considerable time we <lb/>got no more news — <lb/> but the streets became <lb/>more &amp; more crowded
            <pb n="45" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_45"/>
            <lb/>And there was a <lb/>perfect cessation of firing <lb/> at about 5<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi>. <seg type="unclear">Hannon</seg> <lb/> &amp; McMahon came in — <lb/> They had little news — <lb/><seg type="unclear">Hannon</seg> told me of <lb/>his wholly unsuccessful <lb/>attempts to reach me <lb/>during the last three <lb/>days — There had been <lb/>a great deal of fighting <lb/> out his way — in the <lb/>9820 23 <lb/>direction of Fairview. <lb/>He had had a talk over <lb/>the telephone with <lb/>Lord Basil Blackwood — <lb/>who told him that <lb/>there was trouble in <lb/>several parts of the <lb/>Country — mentioned <lb/>Louth, Meath (!!!) — <lb/>But said the most <lb/>serious case was in <lb/>Galway. 
            <pb n="46" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_46"/>
             Miss O'Brien called up at <lb/>6<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi>. She informed me <lb/>that she had several <lb/> attempts to get across <lb/>town — but had failed — <lb/> had each time to come <lb/>back — she had been <lb/> fired at twice. She <lb/>had determined however <lb/>to <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>try again that <lb/>night — and was <lb/>confident of success — <lb/> I went over again the <lb/>message I wanted her to give <lb/>R.   Miss O'B. told me <lb/>that fight in Dublin <lb/>was abandoned —the <lb/>Volunteers having <lb/>surrendered unconditionally. <lb/> This she had been told <lb/>by officers in the <lb/>Gresham — There are <lb/>several officers staying <lb/> at the Gresham —
            <pb n="47" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_47"/>
            <lb/>No more definite news <lb/>last night — but the <lb/>usual crop of rumours. <lb/>I sent out the boys <lb/>to collect news from <lb/> groups in the Street <lb/> They brought in the <lb/>most contradictory  . <lb/>Some said that the <lb/>fight was not at all <lb/>over — that it was <lb/>only a 24 hour truce <lb/>9820 24 <lb/> to<seg type="del"> </seg>bury the dead. <lb/>Father Costelloe the <lb/>Dominican told Theo <lb/>that there was no truth <lb/>in statement of unconditional surrender — <lb/> In the country the <lb/>Volunteers had no idea <lb/>of surrendering . But <lb/>were determined to fight to <lb/>the last.   In one group  
            <pb n="48" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_48"/>
            <lb/>was informed by a man <lb/>that Mr John Dillon <lb/>had gone down and <lb/>got between the opposing <lb/>forces and made <lb/>peace. — Another <lb/> man standing by <lb/>said there was not a <lb/>word of truth in the <lb/>statement —and that <lb/> if M.Dillon had <lb/>gone down his brains  <lb/>would have been blown out. <lb/>At 9<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> Mr.Radcliffe <lb/>of the M.G. called <lb/>in. He was in a <lb/>very nervous and depressed <lb/>condition and very <lb/>anxious to get out of <lb/>Dublin except to <lb/>confirm <seg type="del"> </seg>statement that <lb/>the Volunteers at G. <lb/>P.O. had surrendered <lb/>unconditionally. We had a <lb/> general talk over the
            <pb n="49" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_49"/>
            <lb/>situation, and I asked <lb/>him to let Scott know <lb/>my views as to future <lb/>policy — And as to <lb/>genesis of present situation. <lb/> So far as it is possible <lb/>to form a view at <lb/>present stage.   A ferocious fire <lb/>was raging between <lb/> the Rotunda &amp; Arnotts — <lb/>9820 25 <lb/> and it seemed that <lb/>the whole of the block <lb/>between Great Britain <lb/>Street —Henry Street <lb/>must have been burned out. <lb/>But for this the night <lb/>passed quietly and we <lb/>all <seg type="del">passed</seg>went to bed <lb/>early &amp; slept soundly. <lb/>I got up at 5<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> and <lb/> looked out. A most <lb/>lovely Spring morning —
            <pb n="50" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_50"/>
            <lb/>Everything quiet and <lb/>peaceful — as if nothing <lb/>had happened out of the <lb/>normal.   At 11.10 — we started <lb/>for <seg type="del"> </seg>11.30 Mass at <lb/>Dominick — I never <lb/>saw a more delightful <lb/>Spring day —the Green <lb/>leaves just bursting out <lb/> in the Square - the old <lb/>pear tree on the C.D. <lb/>Office looking more  <lb/>beautiful than it ever <lb/>looked before. The <lb/>Street, crowded with <lb/>people — for the most <lb/>part looking quite <lb/> cheerful &amp; unconcerned — <lb/> screams of children — <lb/> rushing about in high <lb/>spirits at recovered <lb/>liberty — coming out <lb/> of the Church after Mass <lb/>Father Masterson spoke to me
            <pb n="51" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_51"/>
            <lb/>and I <seg type="unclear">leaned</seg> against the <lb/>Church &amp; spoke to him <lb/>for some time. He <lb/> told me had himself <lb/>witnessed the <seg type="del"> </seg>Volunteers <lb/>surrendering on Saturday <lb/>evening. They were <lb/>marched up to  the  Parnell <lb/>Monument with a white <lb/>flag flying — At the <lb/>Monument they laid <lb/>down their arms &amp; <lb/>9820 26 <lb/>accoutrements and <lb/>were then marched off <lb/>as prisoners — in custody <lb/> of soldiers &amp; police. <lb/>He said the fight was <lb/><hi rend="underline">not</hi>all over as — <lb/> The Four Courts, the <lb/>College of Surgeons — and <lb/>other places were holding <lb/>out — But he thought <lb/>that practically the fight <lb/>in Dublin was at an end
            <pb n="52" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_52"/>
            <lb/>At 12.20 Father Masterson <lb/>called — and we had <lb/> a further talk — He <lb/> was anxious as to executions <lb/> etc.   Theo brought in a rumour <lb/>during the morning that <lb/> 60 prisoners had been shot <lb/>in the Castle early this <lb/>morning ; later on this <lb/>rumour was disposed of <lb/> by an interview between <lb/>Eily <seg type="unclear">Cochran</seg> and the  <lb/>officer in charge of the <lb/> Barracks at the bottom of <lb/>this Street — He told <lb/>her that they had <lb/>taken 400 Sinn Féin <lb/>prisoners last night <lb/>and that he would <lb/>have shot them all <lb/>immediately — but this <lb/>would not be allowed <lb/> by the Government — <lb/> two of his fellow <lb/>officers had been killed.
            <pb n="53" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_53"/>
            <lb/>About 12.45 — came <lb/> a soldier from the Castle <lb/>with a letter for me    Monday 1 May 1916 <lb/>10<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> <lb/>The night has been absolutely <lb/>quiet — we went to bed <lb/>at 11<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> — and I slept soundly <lb/> till six o clock.   I resume the narration of <lb/>yesterday — <lb/>Nathan's letter covered <lb/>a letter from R. asking for  <lb/>9820 27 <lb/>information. I wrote <lb/>at some length in reply — <lb/>asked the soldier whether the <lb/>City was quiet between here <lb/>and the Castle - He replied <lb/>perfectly quiet 'Sir'.   At about 4<hi rend="superscript">oc</hi> Hannon <lb/>&amp; McMahon came — <lb/>they had no fresh news — <lb/>Hannon has now got a <lb/>general pass to enter &amp; leave <lb/>Dublin. I arranged with
            <pb n="54" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_54"/>
            <lb/>him to tell Flynn to call to <lb/>see me — also to see <lb/>Muldoon with message <lb/>from me — Muldoon <lb/>is at Sutton. Hannon <lb/>is to call again today . <lb/>I think I shall not let <lb/>him go to London till <lb/>Tuesday. As Miss O'Brien <lb/>did not communicate with <lb/>me yesterday, I conclude <lb/>she got away on Saturday <lb/> night. <lb/>While we were at tea — <lb/>6.30 — George Fottrell <lb/>came in &amp; told us that <lb/>the College of Surgeons <lb/>had surrendered during the <lb/>day. Also that he had <lb/>seen a copy of the Sunday <lb/>pictorial — That Verdun <lb/>had not fallen — and <lb/> there was no reference <lb/>in that paper to the <lb/>Zeppelin raid — nor
            <pb n="55" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_55"/>
            <lb/>to the battle in North Sea.  <lb/>10.30  The milkman arrived — <lb/> He reported the military <lb/>cordons more strict than <lb/>ever. Large bodies of <lb/>soldiers went out last <lb/>night in direction of Swords <lb/><seg type="del">and then</seg> accompanied <lb/>by Guinness Lorry Wagons <lb/>who had been commandeered.  9820 28   There was a short <lb/>burst of firing in that direction <lb/>during the night — <lb/>He also said there was <lb/>heavy firing out at sea <lb/> off Clontarf.   James informed me this <lb/>morning that he had <lb/> overheard men in several <lb/>groups <seg type="del">statin</seg> yesterday <lb/> stating confidently that it <lb/>was Mr John Dillon who
            <pb n="56" facs="L1916_5618_img_712_56"/>
            <lb/>made the peace — God <lb/>bless him — sure he is a <lb/>great man — he went <lb/> down to the G.P.O. <lb/>and arranged for peace. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>