<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3454">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nina Boyle to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nina Boyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Nina Boyle (1865-1943) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946). Boyle writes to apologise for not writing earlier, and to ask if any of the trouble she has read about in the papers has touched Skeffington. While writing that she is not Skeffington&#39;s &#39;shade of politics&#39; Boyle has no doubt that Skeffington will put up a brave fight if one does occur.

Constance Antonia &#39;Nina&#39; Boyle was a British journalist and radical suffragist. She established the first woman&#39;s voluntary patrol group in order to protect young women and prostitutes near rail stations and to work with women to protect them from sexual harassment and assault. Her attempts to stand for the British parliament were denied. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,604/16-22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3454</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0099">Nina Boyle</persName>
              <date>1916-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1819">20 Talbot House, St. Martin&#39;s Lane, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3454_img_2863_1"  type="Letter"  url="7b7e21f391e5e2d66af0ee7684f72e35.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3454_img_2863_1"/>
             20 Talbot House <lb/>S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Martin's Lane   Thursday   Feb? 1916    Dear Mrs Skeffington   You must think me <lb/>most discourteous . I have lived in a great <lb/>rush since getting back, or I should have <lb/>written you before. I left Dublin on <lb/>the Wednesday, after a wild day racing <lb/>after my dear old man out at the Curragh — <lb/>&amp; had managed — or rather he had managed <lb/>for me — to get very little done or fitted in.   Thank you so much for all your <lb/>kindness. I enjoyed the day I spent <lb/>with you very much.   I wonder whether any of the <lb/>trouble I read about after I got back has <lb/>touched you? I should like to know, <lb/>if I may. I know you won't want <lb/>sympathy &amp; of course you also know that <lb/>I am not of your shade of politics, but <lb/>I know you will put up a brave fight <lb/>if it <hi rend="underline">is</hi> a fight. My heart goes out to <lb/>a "bonny fechter"!  <salute.With Kind regards I am <lb/>Sincerely yours   <hi rend="underline">C. Nina Boyle</hi>   I shall be having another <lb/>hurried visit to Dublin soon <lb/>I believe. Will let <lb/>you know if I have <lb/>spare time? <lb/> Our conference <lb/>was a great <lb/>success 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>