<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1845">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman, 16 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Martin Mahoney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman. Mahoney, a parish priest in Minnesota, edited the Catholic weekly &#39;Manifestos&#39;. Sweetman (1844-1936) was a member of Sinn Féin and patron to Arthur Griffith. In 1915 he spoke out against conscription and was arrested in the aftermath of the 1916 Rising. The letter refers mainly to business and religious matters. It is written on the back of an older, typed letter by Mahoney relating to church collections.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sweetman Collection, Collection List 154; MS. 47,604/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1845</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0410">Fr. Martin Mahoney</persName>
              <date>1916-02-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1659">Mendota, Minnesota, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0883">John Sweetman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0439">Drumbaragh Estate, Kells, County Meath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1845_img_130_1"  type="Letter"  url="e04d332998688b0b8bf518013460d3af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1845_img_130_2"  type="Letter"  url="10907d31d48047a16fc35b26ed26cf06.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1845_img_130_3"  type="Envelope"  url="35d3ca0a3026494ce81c0a8de0c5dfd3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1845_img_130_4"  type="Envelope"  url="111815433ea457c8a24dbda7efa11efe.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1845_img_130_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">Mendota. Minn  2 16 16   Dear Mr. Sweetman:   Yours came maybe 2 weeks ago, but<lb/> some rush that made set aside the little pamphlet, which<lb/> only today did I turn up, &amp; read. And reading it I culled back <lb/> all the blame I had planned giving you for the fresh indulgence<lb/> of the pamphlet habit. For it is very good, very effective; so much<lb/> so that I've enclosed it to the editor of the I.M saying I felt he<lb/> too would judge it "good stuff".   As to your boy I almost dread to provoke your contrariness<lb/> by saying how much better I believe the packing business. Like<lb/> fast horses, the devil's due to to'em, University graduates are<lb/> already too numerous, and no account, but an Irish Swift<lb/> or <seg type="unclear">Adenauer</seg>, there will be a man to deserve a national statue!<lb/> Only, let a most unbusiness man say it, that splendid scheme<lb/> to get a fair show, to get started in modern fashion should have<lb/> many interested &amp; involved in it, furnishing the capital, and<lb/> the widespread interest, and manifold boosting necessary<lb/> not only for its adequate start, but as I conceive for the much<lb/> sharper,  later  trial <seg type="del">of</seg> from the inevitable efforts of rivals to kill it<lb/> &amp; also  . Father Condon, now I think in Tramore, once my fellow<lb/> assistant in Preston, Eng, amazed me by the account of how a<lb/> cotton mill of 5000 operatives at Thomastown,   Tipp or Kilkenny,<lb/> got bought, undersold and Killed by a combine of Laws,<lb/> concerns in that line, &amp; so for years that everso lively plant is<lb/> a ruin. There's a matter where the people need a thoro <lb/> anti-toxining to be made to "look before &amp; after and<lb/> think of what's not", the years of two prices. That would<lb/> follow the wily wreckers "cuts" and bargains. What an<lb/> infinite lot people can be shown, as we are shown from<lb/> the Brothers. Agricult Mill — why is it not more widely advertised <lb/> and known, how we may have whole wheat flour at the store<lb/>. I'll send herewith some cuttings held over for a good while.  Mrs S. ought collect the specially good &amp; helpful things in those. <lb/> <seg type="unclear"> Leave a help</seg> and letters on Irish Music, harp, tuning etc. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1845_img_130_2"/>
            Also you might usefully abridge the Rigg showings on crops acreage; <lb/> and give a good document on the several better and more paying uses<lb/> of barley than to make booze.<lb/>  Very sincerely,<lb/> M Mahoney .  Mendoza, Minn Dec 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1915.  Dear Sirs:   With the report of last Easter Collection, I am enclosing<lb/> the little envelope for the Fall collection which ought to come<lb/> in next Sunday. This Fall collection serves to meet two of the <lb/> largest Parish outlays, the Seminary assessment and the Fuel, both<lb/> of which used to be, and are yet in many places two distinct collections<lb/> some times kept up for several Sundays. What an awful<lb/> punishment it would be of my desire to spare people that unpleasant <lb/> music, if anyone were to confine himself for this one Fall collection<lb/> to only such an offering as he would feel bound to make for each <lb/> of these old style levies. This is a good occasion for a worthy<lb/> thanks offering toi the Lord for the bounties of this year.   Sincerely,<lb/> Martin Mahoney.<lb/>   Easter 1915 Collection. <lb/> 5.00 James Scott.<lb/> 3.00 D. Tousignant.<lb/> 2.00 J.J. Beaudette, Arthur Dernier, Ed Dupuis, Jos Fee, Mrs Pat <lb/>Fee, James McCarthy &amp;Family, Perron.<lb/> 1.50 Mick Welch,   Jms &amp; Mrs Shields.<lb/> 1.00 Alex <seg type="unclear">Enge</seg>, Fred  , M Barry, L. Beaudet, .... einier,<lb/> Frank Bouthiler, Fred Bouthiler, Mrs Anne Burne, Chas Burns, <lb/> Geo Burns, Hugh Burns, James Burns. M. Burns, Wm Callahan.<lb/> Alex Charderdelain, Desire Chardelain, Louis Chardelain,<lb/> E Coffee, Thos. Connolly, Jne Cunningham, M. Cunningham<lb/> Wm, Deslaurier, Mrs Violet Evans, Agnes Fee, Hugh Fee,<lb/> James Fee, Wm Fee, Mrs T. Fisher, l. Gosselin, M. Haggerty,<lb/> T. Kenneally, Mrs  Kennedy, M. Kennedy, Ed Kearns,<lb/> Jno Kearns, <seg type="unclear">.Kester, Jos Lebbey, Whos Lebboy, J.M.Liebel,</seg><lb/> Dug Lemay, J.Lemay, J..Lomay, J.J.Lemay, Mor Levendro,<lb/> J..Lexandre, F.McCarthy, M.O'Connor, ..O'Moill, dolard,<lb/> Permxon, Dolph Pollon, Jos Quigley, M Lovan, A. Moran,<lb/> M. Kied, H..Shields, Lillian Shields, M. Shields, Jas Slaton,<lb/> Felix <seg type="unclear">joisignant</seg>, Matt Walsh, E. Walsh, Gus Weber, L. Weber<lb/> Mrs Weber   .75 T.F. Bagan, Mrs Fred Lecleure.   .50 Matt Beaudette, James Burns, Julia Burns, D. Clemens,<lb/> Felix Deslaudier, Louis Fisher, P. Hurley, Mrs P Kaufhold,<lb/> M. <seg type="unclear">Luer,</seg> Emmanuel <seg type="unclear">Letendro</seg>, . Lohendie, Mrs. M. Miller,<lb/> P. Mooney, J. O'Neill, Kye Perron, Omar Perron, R. Reid,<lb/> Mrs Rhos Ryan (R.I.P.), Renie Shields, J.J. Slater,<lb/> Thomas Slater, <seg type="unclear">V. Tonsignant, L Vainencourt</seg>, Emily Weber,<lb/> Mary Weber, J. Williams, P. Williams.   .25 <seg type="unclear">Jos. Urvine</seg>, Paul  ane, Francis Cayan, Carroll Callahan,<lb/> Hugh Callahan, Omar Deslaurier, Joe Fee, K Lemay,<lb/> Chas <seg type="unclear">Langer</seg>, Jno Slater.  Plate $4.02 Total $120.27<lb/>
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1845_img_130_3"/>
             Feb<lb/> 17<lb/> 9AM<lb/> 1916   Mr. John Sweetman<lb/> Drumbaragh, Kells<lb/> Ireland 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1845_img_130_4"/>
            Agnes Swee
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>