<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3286">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to the Under Secretary from Edward O'Farrell, 20 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10412-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3286</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1926</item>
               <item n="tag">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3286_img_2701_1"  type="Letter"  url="52e11a8faf40c3a3a121a1f8b1ca0553.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3286_img_2701_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="0a41afd677c641b1cfd72b56d2bf0b17.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3286_img_2701_1"/>
             The Under Secretary <lb/>Chief Secretary's Office <lb/>Dublin Castle   20th June, 1916  <lb/>the following number quoted <lb/>9729 <seg type="head"><hi rend="underline">CIRCULAR TO CROWN AND SESSIONAL CROWN SOLICITORS.</hi></seg>  Sir,   With a view to avoiding unecessary expenditure in <lb/>the service of Crown Summonses, Crown and Sessional Crown <lb/>Solicitors should comply, whenever possible, with the <lb/>following instructons, which have been approved by the <lb/>Attorney-General: -   I. A summons for a witness in the civil or Military <lb/>service of the Crown should be sent by registered <lb/>letter address to the Head of the Department, or <lb/>the Commanding Office of the Unit, to which the <lb/>witness belongs. An acknowledgement of the letter <lb/>should be requested.   II. Where a constable has made a Deposition in a case, <lb/>he should be employed to serve the summonses on <lb/>witnesses residing in his or an adjoining Sub- <lb/>District. All other summonses for witnesses resident <lb/>in Ireland should be served by the Constabulary of <lb/>the Sub-District wherein the witnesses reside. No <lb/>Constable who has not made a Deposition in the case <lb/>should attend the Court to prove service unless he is <lb/>required to do so by the Crown Solicitor.   III.A summons for a witness resident in Great Britain <lb/>should be sent for service to the Chief Constable of <lb/>the District in which the resident resides, with a <lb/>request for an acknowledgement. An intimation <lb/>should be sent to the Constable serving the summons <lb/>should not attend in Ireland to prove service unless <lb/>required to do so by the Crown Solicitor.  <<lb/> In reference to Circular of 19th May, 1915, notify- <lb/>ing that the Writs of Habeas Corpus are no longer necessary, the# <lb/>Attorney-General directs that the Circular in question is not <lb/>to be treated as applicable in Change of Venue Cases, and <lb/>that, in future, in these cases, the former practice is to <lb/>be followed and Writs of Habeas Corpus applied for to bring <lb/>Defendants to Dublin in order that they may plead.   I am <lb/> <lb/> Sir, <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  <lb/>   E.O'FARRELL. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3286_img_2701_2"/>
            <seg type="head">CIRCULAR TO CROWN <hi rend="underline">AND SESSIONAL</hi> CROWN SOLICITORS</seg>  Dublin Castle,   June, 1916   Sir,   With a view to avoiding unnecessary expenditure in <lb/>the service of Crown Summonses, Crown and Sessional Crown <lb/>Solicitors should comply, whenever possible, with the <lb/>following instructions, which have been approved by the <lb/>Attorney-General—   I. A summons for a witness in the civil or Military <lb/>service of the Crown should be sent by registered <lb/>letter address to the Head of the Department, or <lb/>the Commanding Office of the Unit, to which the <lb/>witness belongs. An acknowledgement of the letter <lb/>should be requested.   II. Where a constable has made a Deposition in a case, <lb/>he should be employed to serve the summonses on <lb/>witnesses residing in his or an adjoining Sub- <lb/>District. All other summonses for witnesses <lb/>resident in Ireland should be served by the Con- <lb/>stabulary of the Sub-District wherein the witnesses <lb/>reside. No Constable who has not made a Deposition <lb/>in the case should attend the Court to prove service <lb/>unless he is required to do so by the Crown Solicitor.   III.A summons for a witness resident in Great Britian <lb/>should be sent for service to the Chief Constable of <lb/>the District in which the resident resides, with a <lb/>request for an acknowledgement<seg type="del">: but in Liverpool, <lb/>Glasgow, and the summons should be <lb/>sent through the County Inspector, R.I.C. for service <lb/>by a member of the Irish Police resident in the <lb/>places named. </seg>. An intimation should be sent that the <lb/>Constable serving the summons should not attend in <lb/>Ireland to prove service unless required to do so by <lb/>the Crown Solicitor.   In reference to Circular of 19th May, 1915, notify- <lb/>ing that Writs of Habeas Corpus are no longer necessary, <lb/>the Attorney-General directs that the Circular in question <lb/>is not to be treated as applicable in Change of Venue cases, <lb/>and that, in future, in these cases, the former practice is <lb/>to be followed and Writs of Habeas Corpus applied for to <lb/>bring Defendants to Dublin in order that they may plead.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   E. O'Farrell 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>