<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3173">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Margaret Donnan to Jane Donnan, 28 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Margaret Donnan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Margaret Donnan, a 50 year old mother to her 24 year old daughter who was working in Post Office in Killyleagh Co Down, urging her to apply for work in the Ballymena Cottage Hospital.

This letter tells of events that Margaret and her 10 year old daughter witnessed from her upstairs window in Castlebellingham Co Louth and information she gathered from neighbours. 

It also tells of her husband volunteering to guard the railway bridge with other men from the village. This letter also gives news of two sons that had enlisted and were in France, a 17 year old daughter who had recently gone to work in the post office in England, and another son at home taking food to his father guarding the bridges from being blown up.

The Donnan family were Presbyterian.  Members of the family, including Margaret, had worked for the Bellingham family. Margaret was a cook. The family would not have been sympathetic to the Rising.  

Enclosed is a very sad photograph. Three years before it was taken, in 1905, they had lost two children, a baby boy aged one year and a little girl who died aged two, just 4 months before the youngest child in the photograph was born.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3173</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1072">Margaret Donnan</persName>
              <date>1916-04-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0792">Castlebellingham Co Louth, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Jane Donnan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1636">43 High Street, Killyleagh, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1950</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_1"  type="Letter"  url="8f7fbe7c04c8855321722d0facbbf0fd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_2"  type="Letter"  url="0f082e733cca6c69f2c14c62e9ca7354.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_3"  type="Letter"  url="762b1b4d6d70f086e01052a95a6b5329.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_4"  type="Letter"  url="4539caa033bf579d4edbbcd6a16b5ed6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_5"  type="Letter"  url="79c4054c3ff3b876b1913f8e53b85c72.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_6"  type="Letter"  url="2917a092b060a3856f7a44c3dba8fd0a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_7"  type="Letter"  url="80582806baab26417c98e9e705b8f500.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_8"  type="Letter"  url="78daead56fffd4b529c0546deafe4055.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_9"  type="Photograph"  url="aa42ff04758e7f55a6daf00eeebe2dff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_10"  type="Letter"  url="dd60a13c07a7d71c4ae44403a07864cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_11"  type="Letter"  url="95c1aea153c3cc4a946721b62c201b18.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3173_img_2594_12"  type="Letter"  url="44380df0a35293162e7f51c3b331e9e7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_1"/>
             Castle Bellingham Co Louth   April 28   Dear Jane.   your card this <sic>morng</sic>. I hope you have got my letter. <lb/>I wrote you on Wed. and sent you an advertisement of <seg type="unclear">Ballamin a </seg> <lb/>Hospital. It is in this weeks  Witness  also — asking you to send <sic>Apalication</sic> <lb/>to <sic>materon.</sic> If you did not get my letter of Wed last, if you <lb/>get this <hi rend="underline">one</hi> be sure to send applications to the matron <lb/>of <sic>Ballymina</sic> Hospital — here is a Copy of advertisement, <lb/>Wanted Probationer for the Ballymena Cottage Hospital <lb/>Apply at once with testimonials to the Matron the Cottage <lb/>Hospital Ballymena. <seg type="del">6493</seg> <seg type="del">Witness Office</seg>   I hope you will get this. Our letters are going by <seg type="unclear">Bepost</seg>. I <sic>wrot</sic> <lb/>to Peg. and sent her money last night. I hope she <lb/>will get it. I am sure she knows how they are over here. <lb/>We got no letters or Papers since Monday — no Post went out or <lb/>in from Dublin. a few from Belfast might come — <lb/>they have make arrangements to send by Belfast. Now <lb/>on Monday. a lot of Volunteers marched past here to DMG Side <lb/>about 4. 2 Police guarding them a brake —Cars — <sic>the</sic> only went <lb/>to Lurgan when <sic>the</sic> <sic>stoped</sic> every Motor-Car coming from the <lb/>races — and Put the People out of them into a House and <lb/>took the Car and Driver. <sic>the</sic> were all armed. Pistols and <lb/>rifles they took 8 motors &amp; several cases — took Kings Horse <lb/>out of the break Car and 10<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> worth  of bread  3 lbs worth of Bacon in <lb/>the Car in on the road side at Lurgan. got also a <lb/>horse from Jamie Ned Langan because he refused. <sic>The</sic> <lb/>shot his arm nearly off. I hear it will be taken off. <lb/>Only for Oswild Mc Dowl <sic>stoped</sic> Carlow and sent him back to DMG <lb/>for help — he would have lost his motor or his life. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_2"/>
             2   <sic>the</sic> came up to Bellingham &amp; <sic>stoped</sic> outside of our House <seg type="unclear">believe</seg> <lb/>Butterley, Burns — all got out started running away Miss B. goods — <lb/>Putting them in the Motors from her they took 6 tins of biscuits 8 tins <lb/>of salmon. Bread, Milk from <seg type="unclear">Lotus</seg> Cheese from barn. Bread. <lb/>when that was over or during the time they were talking the <lb/><sic>tings</sic>some of them was <sic>buisy</sic> <sic>the</sic> put out <sic>Sargant</sic> Donavan. <lb/>Standing at the rails at the end of the rail opposite Burns <lb/>and a fellow stood before the with a Pistol all the time <sic>the</sic> were <lb/><sic>serched.</sic> and other Police man from Gilbertstown came up <lb/>on Bike to post a letter he was put beside our men, searched <lb/>Pistol held up to their Chests. up comes a young officer in <lb/>a grand motor Car. Ltf Dunville from Belfast Distillery <lb/>whiskey man from Belfast <sic>stoped</sic> to ordered but put standing <lb/>beside the Police also his man Driver. 5 in a row <lb/>as helpless as babes. revolvers. &amp; pistols pointed at <lb/>them all all sides the officer was going to Kingstown <lb/>to catch a boat for France. when they had the shops <seg type="del">stacked</seg> stacked <lb/>they got ready blew up the officer motor <seg type="unclear">tiers</seg> shot him self <lb/>Two places in the Chest shot the Constable Charles Magee <lb/>3 places as much stuff in him as would kill 3 men <lb/>when <sic>the</sic> Shot the Police. man our men run across and in to Burns <lb/>and the Driver, Magee . run. to Kelly fell on the road was <sic>Draged</sic> <lb/>in to Kelly archway. the officer remained standing with his <lb/>arms up, for mercy. a fellow called out to him hands up <lb/>we will not shoot you in Cold Blood the fellow was Dying at <lb/>the time and very soon fell forward on his side in a Puddle <lb/>of water. and the Sinn Feiners looking on at him falling <lb/>shot 2 Places in the Chest. the Motors left them then and <lb/>two fellows. ran. and <sic>draged</sic> him to Kelly. where the Dr. <lb/>was Dressing Magees wounds. the Priest was got for Magee sent <lb/>to Hospital died at the door of Hospital going in — L 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_3"/>
             3   On Monday, evening at 7 all this Happened, opposite our <lb/>House. I was up stairs looking out all this time seen all — <lb/>only got muddled. Hilda was with me Father was just <lb/>gone to the cattle gong Joe Hand Caney Carroll Burn me <lb/>Lilly Kelly. Sarah Conaton all seen what went on. <lb/>everyone on was Powerless afraid to move or <sic>the</sic>would <lb/>fire on any one like a Dog. <sic>the</sic> got up and drove <lb/>away towards Dublin about 11 the military  . Come <lb/>back about one. <sic>The</sic> were gone on in their hurry <lb/>they forgot a motor Load of <sic>amination</sic> in the Street <lb/>Bandages water bottles all thing really. So father Willee <lb/>Mc Kinney James Carson 'Heron' Lowe all carried the <lb/>stuff to the Barrick Pushed the motor to the Barricks <lb/>the <sic>soulders</sic> took It away. at 1 Ocloc in the night <lb/>to Dmg. their is 8 of our gang arrested sent to Belfast jail <lb/>Mr. Leslie seen them they are Dundalk men. Machtee <lb/>Hughes. Karney. — all well known to all. <sic>the</sic> will leaving <lb/>today. On yesterday I had a drive to Dmg. to give <seg type="unclear">experience</seg> <lb/>at the Hospital. Sarah Conaton. Lily Kelly. me Joe. Carney. Carroll. <lb/>when we got down we were not wanted fro some time longer. <lb/>Hilda went to   in the <sic>main</sic> time Father all the fellows <lb/>had to leave out of the <sic>brewry</sic> and go guard bridges <lb/>Father was at   a lot of other from here — and some <lb/><sic>souldiers</sic>, Cranson. Some and some soldiers at CBH   <lb/>from Dublin to Dunleen is  . and lined up with <lb/><sic>souldiers</sic>   across the  . there was word yesterday <lb/>the   broke out. and was coming down the line Matilda Kelly <lb/> . On Monday the <seg type="del"></seg> took the P.O. Dublin and the could not   <lb/>got out. <sic>the</sic> were to <sic>gass</sic> them out last night. I see in to days Belfast <lb/><sic>their</sic> is a good many   of course <sic>the blew up a Bridge <lb/>this side of Dublin and that what they are afraid of.   3 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_4"/>
             4   I need hardly tell you about Dublin as if you see <lb/>the Belfast Paper you will see. All. Since <lb/>Monday all our men are doing Police work. <lb/>Of course <sic>theer</sic> is no Police all away — our men <lb/>was  releived  by Police at <seg type="unclear">Drumin</seg> yesterday <lb/>Joe McMahons motor went up with them. a special <lb/> came down with them at 10 last night 12 hours <lb/> Edward went up with some grub to Father yesterday <lb/> to Drumin he was <sic>stoped</sic> by <lb/>Dundalk. men are guarding <sic>Stabannon</sic> <lb/> after some time you get searched. and let pass on <lb/> Oswald <sic>McDowl</sic> is a Dispatch rider from Dundalk <lb/> to Dunleer reporting from one to the<lb/> other barriers how things are getting on. <lb/> in the streets of Dundalk. Yesterday <sic>the</sic> were <lb/> <seg type="unclear">lorry drew</seg> across them one care at a <lb/> time can only pass — did you see where <lb/> Sir Roger Casement came in in the west of Ireland <lb/> to help the Sinn Feiners. I see a bit in the Belfast <lb/> Paper. Mrs W. <!-- Auntie Jane Wilson nee Donnan - shopkeeper and postmistress --> sends us down to Belfast paper for 5 minutes <lb/> in the morning to have a look. this is all we see — <lb/>so content yourself if you do not hear from us. <lb/> no word of the boys lately of course. I am not annoyed. <lb/>the are on the road some place — Good by — <lb/> you know the wires are all cut. 15 motor loads of police <lb/> went by to Drogheda on Wednesday    Mother Donnan  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_5"/>
            <!‐‐ Photograph ‐‐>
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_6"/>
            <!‐‐ Photograph ‐‐>
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_7"/>
            <!‐‐ Photograph ‐‐>
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_8"/>
            <!‐‐ Photograph ‐‐>
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_9"/>
             Page 2    they came up to Bellingham stopped outside of our house below(?) Butterly, Burns <lb/>(these were the names of shops) all got out started running away ? ? goods putting <lb/>them in motors from her they took 6 tins of biscuits, 8 tins of salmon, bread milk <lb/>from ? Toties cheese from ? Bread When that was over or during the time they <lb/>taking the things some of them was busy(?) they put our Sergeant Donovan standing <lb/>at <sic>tha</sic> rails at the end of the rail opposite Burns and a fellow stood before them with <lb/>a pistol all the time they were searched and another police man from Gilbertstown <lb/>came up on bike to post a letter he was put beside our men searched, pistol held up <lb/>to their chests, --- up comes a young officer in a grand motor car. Lft Dunville from <lb/>Belfast Distillery whisky man from Belfast stopped to order(ed) but put standing <lb/>beside the police also his man Driver. 5 in a row as helpless as babes. revolvers and <lb/>pistols pointed at them at all sides the officer was going to Kingstown to catch a <lb/>boat for France when the had ??? ??? they got ready blew up the officers motor <lb/>tyres shot himself two places in the chest shot the Constable Charles Magee 3 places <lb/>as much stuff in him as would kill 3 men   when they shot the police man our men ran across and into Burns and the Driver, <lb/>Magee run to Kelly fell on the road was dragged into Kelly archway. the officer <lb/>remained standing with his arms up --for mercy. a fellow called out to him, "hands <lb/>up we will no shoot you in cold blood" the fellow was dying at the time and very <lb/>soon fell forward on his side in a puddle of water and the Sinn Fieners looking on at <lb/>him falling shot 2 places in the chest the motors left then and two fellows ran and <lb/>dragged him to Kelly where the Dr was dressing Magee's wounds the priest was <lb/>got to Magee sent to hospital died at the door going in  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_10"/>
             Page 2   they came up to Bellingham stopped outside of our house below(?) Butterly, Burns <lb/>(these were the names of shops) all got out started running away ? ? goods putting <lb/>them in motors from her they took 6 tins of biscuits, 8 tins of salmon, bread milk <lb/>from ? Toties cheese from ? Bread When that was over or during the time they <lb/>taking the things some of them was busy(?) they put our Sergeant Donovan standing <lb/>at <sic>tha</sic> rails at the end of the rail opposite Burns and a fellow stood before them with <lb/>a pistol all the time they were searched and another police man from Gilbertstown <lb/>came up on bike to post a letter he was put beside our men searched, pistol held up <lb/>to their chests, --- up comes a young officer in a grand motor car. Lft Dunville from <lb/>Belfast Distillery whisky man from Belfast stopped to order(ed) but put standing <lb/>beside the police also his man Driver. 5 in a row as helpless as babes. revolvers and <lb/>pistols pointed at them at all sides the officer was going to Kingstown to catch a <lb/>boat for France when the had ??? ??? they got ready blew up the officers motor <lb/>tyres shot himself two places in the chest shot the Constable Charles Magee 3 places <lb/>as much stuff in him as would kill 3 men   when they shot the police man our men ran across and into Burns and the Driver, <lb/>Magee run to Kelly fell on the road was dragged into Kelly archway. the officer <lb/>remained standing with his arms up --for mercy. a fellow called out to him, "hands <lb/>up we will no shoot you in cold blood" the fellow was dying at the time and very <lb/>soon fell forward on his side in a puddle of water and the Sinn Fieners looking on at <lb/>him falling shot 2 places in the chest the motors left then and two fellows ran and <lb/>dragged him to Kelly where the Dr was dressing Magee's wounds the priest was <lb/>got to Magee sent to hospital died at the door going in 
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_11"/>
             Page 3   On Monday evening at 7 all this happened opposite our house I was up stairs <lb/>looking out all the time, seen all only got muddled. Hilda was with me Father was <lb/>just gone to the cattle. Johnny Hand (taxi driver) Joe Cerney Carroll Burn me Lily <lb/>Kelly Sarah Conaton all seen what went on everyone one was powerlee afraid to <lb/>move or they would fire on anyone -- like a dog they got up and drove away <lb/>towards Dublin about 11 the military??? come back about one they gone on in <lb/>their hurry they forgot a motor load of ammunition in the street Bandages water <lb/>bottles all things ready so Father Willie McKinny James Crason Aeron Tome all <lb/>carried the stuff to the Barracks Pushed the motor to the Barracks the soldiers took <lb/>it away at 1 o'clock in the night to Dmg there is 8 of our gang arrested sent to <lb/>Belfast Jail   Mr Leslie (Canon Leslie C of I minister) seen them They are Dundalk men <lb/>Machtree (McAtee later an Irish government minister) Hughes Karney all well <lb/>known to all They will swing surely And yesterday I had a drive to Dundalk to <lb/>give evidence at the hospital Sarah Conaton Lily Kelly me Jo Carney Carroll when <lb/>we got down we were not wanted for some time longer. Hilda went to Hosies in <lb/>the meantime Father was at Drumin a lot of others from here and some soldiers <lb/>Cranson Tome and some soldiers at Castlebellingham Station from Dublin to <lb/>Dunleer is? trenched and lined up with soldier's lorry across the road. there was <lb/>word yesterday that? broke out and was coming down the line Matilda Kelly <lb/>wrote home yesterday come to Drogheda took the train down on Monday the <lb/>??Sinn took the PC Dulin"? and they could not be got out they were to gas them out <lb/>last night. I see in To-days Belfast (paper?) there is a good many dead of course <lb/>they blew up a bridge this side of Dublin and that is what they are afraid of. 
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_3173_img_2594_12"/>
             Page 4   I need hardly tell you about Dublin as if you see Belfast paper you will see all <lb/>Since Monday all our men are doing police work of course there is no police all <lb/>away-- our men was relieved by police at Dreemin ? yesterday Joe McMahons <lb/>motor went up with them   a special came down with them at 10 last night 12 hours Edward went up with <lb/>some grub to Father yesterday to Drumin he was stopped by Dundalk. men are <lb/>guarding Stabanon after some time you get searched and let pass on  <lb/>Oswald McDowell is a dispatch rider from Dundalk to Dunleer reporting from one <lb/>to the other barriers how things are getting on in the streets of Dundalk. Yesterday <lb/>there was a lorry drawn across them one car at a time can only pass did you see <lb/>where Sir Roger Casement came in the west of Ireland to help the Sinn Feinners. <lb/>I see a bit in the Belfast paper. Mrs W.(Auntie Jane Wilson nee Donnan shop keeper <lb/> postmistress) sends us down the Belfast paper for 5 minutes in the morning to have <lb/>a look this is all we see — so content yourself if you do not hear from us No <lb/>word from the boys lately of course I am not annoyed they are on the road some <lb/>place —Goodbye —you know the wires are all cut 15 motor loads of police <lb/>went by to Drogheda on Wednesday   Mother Donnan 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>