<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3681">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Henry Thompson to the President & Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 8 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Henry Thompson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir William Henry Thompson (1861-1929) offering himself as a candidate for re-election to the Chair of Institutes of Medicine in the School of Physic.  

The letter has been initialled by Ephraim MacDowel Cosgrave (1853-1925). Cosgrave served as president of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland in 1914 and held the position until 1916. Aside from his dedication to medicine Cosgrave was also a member of the Royal Society of Antiquities of Ireland, treasurer of the Royal Zoological Society of Ireland and a founder and secretary of the Georgian Society of Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T54</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3681</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0877">William Henry Thompson</persName>
              <date>1916-01-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1510">School of Physiology, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ephraim MacDowel Cosgrave </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="death">1929</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3681_img_3074_1"  type="Letter"  url="2237ced19ec56449ed3c9a431d16e3b7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3681_img_3074_1"/>
             School of Physiology <lb/>Trinity College. Dublin.   8<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> Jan 1916   M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> President &amp; Gentlemen   I beg to offer myself <lb/>as a candidate for re-election to the <lb/>Chair of Institutes of Medicine in the <lb/>School of Physic in Ireland.   I am <lb/>Your obed<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>   W.H. Thompson   To <lb/>The President &amp; Fellows of the Royal <lb/>College of Physicians of Ireland.   Macd.C <lb/>10.I.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>