<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4455">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegraph from Frongoch to Sir Robert Chalmers, 2 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Telegraph to Sir Robert Chalmers regarding release of 35 Irish prisoners.

In 1916 Col. F.A. Heygate Lambert (1857-1929) was serving as the Commandant of Frongoch Internment Camp. Lambert served in the camp until the last of the prisoners were released in December 1916. In the Spring of 1917 he went to Ypres to command a battalion of the Labour Corps.

Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) was appointed under-secretary of Ireland in 1916, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the aftermath of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection> NAI/CSO/RP/1916/13324/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4455</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-08-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1722">Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_1"  type="Letter"  url="ae539544a361bff925527d40c5ea863d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_2"  type="Letter"  url="b5fae752bf0012b16c6b0a54807e701f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_3"  type="Letter"  url="fc71e8ec50083c22af5566b0cf44eaf5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="010714a8523fcb3c07617a94a26650c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="5bfb3f2c2aa792f97494934fbcd376f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="772a5461d42d168f12809796a5bd241e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="46cacf446b71ec06d899aa1880979f2f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="523b3778a586d59e7fa70563f7e89903.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_9"  type="Enclosure"  url="e7391073c7416e4ac512f2f111d4a4d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4455_img_3803_10"  type="Enclosure"  url="588f8b6b0643dc1b1cf6df135c9bb63d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_1"/>
              Inspector General     To see return     Chief      08-02-16   Message Received in Chief Secretary's Office    Under Secretary Dublin Castle  <lb/>Dublin    The Under Secretary <lb/>noted + Returned <lb/>  <lb/>Comm 3/8   <lb/>C362 following 11 Irish prisoners <lb/>will be released at 8 <lb/>pm tonight in addition to <lb/>list already sent you aaa <lb/>They will travel by Holyhead <lb/>— Kingstown route by the <lb/>midnight service aaa list of <lb/>35 to be released tomorrow <lb/>by express post tonight 1043 <lb/><hi rend="underline"><sic>sargent</sic></hi> P. a. 59 Hollybank Rd Drumcondra 884 <hi rend="underline">Garrett   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_2"/>
             (2)   J. 2 Shannon Street Enniscorthy <lb/>1166 <hi rend="underline">Howley was Limepath   <lb/>1783 <hi rend="underline">Millen Patk 9 Emerald <lb/>Lee Cork st Dublin 1096 <lb/><hi rend="underline">Higgins</hi> w. Cashla athenry galway <lb/>1306 <hi rend="underline">Costello mc glenscaul oranmore <lb/>Co galway 54 <hi rend="underline">Connell John <lb/>Clarenbridge Co galway 1397 = B. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Rongham</hi> B. Derrough Colemanstown 1471 = <lb/>B. <hi rend="underline">quinn g. 61 Cork st <lb/>Dublin 411 <hi rend="underline">Cooper John 33
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_3"/>
             (3)   Lennox St Dublin 1445 = a <lb/><hi rend="underline">Waters John 8 <seg type="del"></seg> (or 6) <lb/>East James St Dublin.   Prison warden Frongach 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_4"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Miscellaneous cases. Exemptions</hi>   <hi rend="underline">Galway</hi>    28/7/16  1306 Higgins, Patrick Lisheenkyle; Athenry   <hi rend="underline">Dublin City. (S.O.)</hi>    26/7/1916 582 BERMINGHAM, John James. St. Ignatius Rd. <lb/> 26/7/1916 1162 C BILLINGS, Joseph Patrick. <lb/> 26/7/1916 1155 CANNEY, Daniel. North Strand road <lb/>do 1528 C GREGORY, John Fairview. <lb/> 28/7/1916 525 A HEGARTY, John. Kingstown.   <hi rend="underline">Cork. (S.O.)</hi>    28/7/1916 917 HEGARTY, Daniel .J. Mallow  <lb/> 28/7/1916 917 O'CONNELL, Christopher. Mallow <lb/>do 922 SPILLANE, John Fermoy <lb/>do 1297 O'DONOVAN, John James Clonakilty <lb/>do 1325 O'SULLIVAN, Patrick Mitchellstown <lb/>do 1325 O'SULLIVAN, Michael Mitchellstown <lb/>do 1087 MANNING, Daniel Kilbrittain. <lb/>do 1087 MANNING, Denis. Kilbrittain.   <hi rend="underline">Galway. (S.O.)</hi>  <lb/> 28/7/16  587 D LEECH. Stephen Kinvara <lb/>do 1030 O'LEARY, Cornelius Costello <lb/>do 1485 A WARD, James Athenry   <hi rend="underline">Wicklow. (S.O.)</hi>  <lb/> 28/7/16 1091 B FORD, William Bray   <hi rend="underline">Dublin County. (S.O.)</hi>    27/7/16 608 B GIBBONS, Peter Skerries <lb/> 27/7/16 706 A BOWEN, Bartholomew P. Howth   <hi rend="underline">Tyrone. (S.O.)</hi>    28/7/16  1279 B Hart, Henry Dungannon <lb/>do 1279 C Hughes, William Donaghmore <lb/>do 773 MacElvogue, James Donaghmore <lb/>do 1279 McGuirk, Patrick Dungannon. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_5"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Dublin City Exempt.</hi>   763 A HENRy, Francis. <lb/>1568 B HENRY, Frederick <lb/>1267 E HOLLAND, Robert <lb/>1212 C HUNTER, James <lb/>1442 D IRWIN, Samuel Patrick <lb/>1046 A IVERS, Thomas <lb/>1588 D JOYCE, Edwad <lb/>1129 B KAVANAGH, Pat. <lb/>1501 C JUDGE, John Pat. <lb/>1499 B KEARNS, John <lb/>1596 A KEARNS, Pat. <lb/>1212 KEATING, Cornelius <lb/>1588 C KELLY, Joseph <lb/>1583 B KELLY, Pat. <lb/>699 B KELLY, Wm. <lb/>1144 B KENNEDY, Joseph <lb/>1499 A KERR, Michael <lb/>1266 B LEAHY, Thoams <lb/>485 McKENNA, John <lb/>1456 LOWE, Arnold <lb/>1478 A LYNCH, Wm. <lb/>1551 A MACDONALD, John <lb/>1409 D MAGUIRE, James <lb/>1597 C McKEOWN, Owen <lb/>1597 A MEADE, Walter <lb/>1597 A MEADE, Wm. <lb/>1597 A MEADE, Henry <lb/>1581 B MEAGHER, Pat. <lb/>1551 C MELDON, John <lb/>1585 D MITCHEL, Pat. <lb/>1538 D MORAN, Pat. 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_6"/>
             1a.   <hi rend="underline">DUBLIN CITY EXEMPT </hi> (cont.)   22 B MORAN, Wm. <lb/>1565 MULLEN, Douglas French <lb/>1118 MUNRO, Thomas 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_7"/>
             2.   1264 B MURPHY, John <lb/>1518 B HOLOHAN, Pat. <lb/>1595 C NOONAN, Chris <lb/>1190 B O'BRIEN, <sic>Mathew</sic> <lb/>159 E O'BRIEN, Thomas <lb/>1257 C O'HANLON, Pat. <lb/>1384 B OMAN, Robert <lb/>1440 D O'MOORE, Pat Michael <lb/>1576 O'NEILL, Joseph <lb/>1583 C O'NEILL, Michael <lb/>1586 D O'NEILL, Timothy <lb/>9 C O'REILLY, Joseph <lb/>1582 C O'REILLY, Joseph 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_8"/>
             <hi rend="underline">DUBLIN CITY EXEMPTY</hi>   1116 O'REILLY, Desmond <lb/>549 O'REILLY, Kevin <lb/>627 O'REILLY, Thomas <lb/>1116 O'ROURKE, Joseph Francis <lb/>170 O'SHEA, John <lb/>1524 D O'SHEA, Robert <lb/>999 POLLARD, Francis <lb/>1456 PARRY, Wm. <lb/>1402 A PORTER, Owen <lb/>636 A RAUL, Laurence <lb/>1202 RING, Joseph <lb/>1325 A RING, Pat. <lb/> 711 E RIORDAN, Michael <lb/>1471 C RYAN, Cornelius <lb/>1146 D RYAN, Wm. <lb/>1595 D SHELLAN, Charles <lb/>1592 B SKEILS, T. <lb/>1378 SMITH, Albert <lb/>1574 B SULLIVAN, John <lb/>1134 SWAN, Pat. <lb/>1590 TURNER, Henry <lb/>1112 WALPOLE, Henry <lb/>811 WALSH, James <lb/>1559 A WARD, P. <lb/>998 WHELAN, George <lb/>1182 A WHITE, John Joseph <lb/>1560 A YOUNG, Robert <lb/>1026 B NICHOLAS, Alexander <lb/>990 BREEN, Wm. <lb/>1157 A BYRNE, Joseph <lb/>1353 C CLIFFORD, Thomas (OR D) <lb/>1220 FEANEY, Gerald <lb/>673 C FOX, Michael <lb/>1598 A GERAGHTY, Chas. <lb/>1598 B GRAHAM, Matthew <lb/> NB 838 HILTON, Thomas 
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_9"/>
             2.   1587 A JACKSON, Peter <lb/>1575 KENNY, John <lb/>1579 C BEGLEY, T. or Devey <lb/>1111 C BYRNE, James <lb/>1606 D COYLE, Thomas <lb/>1583 A DEVINE, Paul <lb/>978 FLANAGAN, Maurice <lb/>1605 A GIBSON, M. <lb/>898 GIBSON, Richard <lb/>443 GOULDING, John <lb/>1210 KING, George <lb/>1602 D LACEY, Philip <lb/>1607 E McCARTHY, D. <lb/>1581 C. MCGEE, Richard. (Michael ?) <lb/>1584 C MASON, Thomas <lb/>1606 C O'GORMAN, Joseph <lb/>976 O'GORMAN,Wm. <lb/>801 O'NEILL, John <lb/>1608 A O'REILLY, Thomas <lb/>1601 STAINES, Wm. 
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_4455_img_3803_10"/>
             <hi rend="underline">DUBLIN CITY.</hi> <lb/>987A BURKE, Thomas F. <lb/>501 BYRNE, Alphonsius <lb/> Not in list already on card 1269C CONNOLLY, Joseph  <hi rend="underline">Not counted</hi>  <lb/>507c CUFFE, Thomas S <lb/>1432A DALY, James <lb/>440 FULLAM, Thomas <lb/> Not in list 838 HILTON, Thomas Counted already  <lb/>1433C HENDERSON, Leo James S. <lb/>530A LARKIN, Joseph <lb/>530A LARKIN, John <lb/>976D O'CONNOR, Bart <lb/>1095B O'MAHONY, John <lb/>1095 MURRAY, Joseph <lb/> Not in list 1134A O'BRIEN, William <lb/>1371A RYAN, James <lb/> Not in list 699 SARGENT, Philip A. <lb/>896B STRITCH, James <lb/>1494A REYNOLDS, P. <lb/>1133C WHELAN, Jas. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>