<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5384">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Colonel Maurice Moore, 29 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter reflecting the author&#39;s opinions of the ruling of Ireland. Mention of northern situation and Irish peers. 

Colonel Maurice George Moore (10 August 1854 – 8 September 1939) was an Irish author, soldier and politician. Born in Co Mayo, he was the younger brother of the writer George Moore.  He reached the rank of colonel in 1902. He resigned his commission in 1906 over matters of principle during the Boer War. 

A member of the provisional committee of the Irish Volunteers in 1913, he was made the organisation&#39;s Inspector General, spending much of 1914 organising the troops in Ireland.[3]  In 1916 he he collected a petition with Agnes O&#39;Farrelly asking for a reprieve of the death sentence against Roger Casement. Later Moore was elected to the Senead. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NLI10561/6/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5384</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0479">Coole, Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0505">Maurice Moore</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5384_img_467_1"  type="Letter"  url="c243e53fc97d6d3e0e5778ffdb4e70ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5384_img_467_2"  type="Letter"  url="b92b80319a3e4d53da34cf28fd8595f2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5384_img_467_3"  type="Letter"  url="af0337ea86167977e85763aa9b6f3ec5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5384_img_467_4"  type="Letter"  url="ff2b2204c84b0466046491557195c55a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5384_img_467_5"  type="Letter"  url="3c45e700b348c546a0e132affd98d357.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5384_img_467_6"  type="Letter"  url="99fea91ae3f95f8e13857f242d8f656a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5384_img_467_1"/>
             TURBOTSTOWN, <lb/>COOLE, <lb/>WESTMEATH.   29/6/16   My dear Maurice  <P>The Southern <lb/> Unionists may go <lb/>to hell for a sop! <lb/>That arrangement <lb/> should be kept for <lb/> a clincher on <lb/> Ireland one and <lb/> undivided. —  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5384_img_467_2"/>
             If the "country" applied <lb/>the same amount of <lb/> common sense &amp; dis- <lb/>-cernment to the question <lb/> of the Irish peers <lb/> that it has done to <lb/> the question of exclusion <lb/> of the Northern counties <lb/> any difficulty they <lb/>now experience w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. <lb/> vanish. - The real <lb/> aristocracy (such <lb/> as it is) of Ireland <lb/>are not as a rule <lb/> anti-Irish. - They <lb/>have been made <lb/> stalking horses &amp; <lb/> figureheads by the <lb/> wire pullers, who <lb/> are middle class <lb/> bounders who make <lb/> use of politics as a <lb/> means of hobnobbing <lb/> now &amp; then with a <lb/> lord! — As long as <lb/> the "unionists", North <lb/> &amp; South, allow them- <lb/>selves to be run by
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5384_img_467_3"/>
            Craig &amp; George Stuart <lb/>&amp; that sort they <lb/> are <hi rend="underline ">hopeless</hi> &amp; not <lb/> worth taking on as <lb/> a corporate body <lb/> to have <hi rend="underline">any</hi> dealings <lb/> with; but the day <lb/>that a few strong <lb/> men in the South, <lb/> &amp; the genuine men <lb/> of business in the <lb/> North rebel against <lb/> the extremist gang
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5384_img_467_4"/>
            &amp; have the pluck <lb/> to declare their <lb/> genuine senti- <lb/>ments, the whole <lb/>"Unionist" plan <lb/> of campaign will <lb/> go pop, &amp; <seg type="del">&amp; be</seg> its <lb/> "organisers" will <lb/> most of them tumble <lb/> over each other
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5384_img_467_5"/>
            for a chance of <lb/>licking Redmond's <lb/>boots. — You <lb/> wait &amp; see!   If the English Gov<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> <lb/>. are idiots enough <lb/> to be humbugged <lb/> by that crew any <lb/>longer it means <lb/>goodbye to any <lb/> sane government <lb/> in England, &amp; <lb/> after all, that <lb/> only means <lb/> hurrying on by <lb/> a few years the <lb/>debacle that has <lb/> been inevitable <lb/> for the last <lb/> generation. - It
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5384_img_467_6"/>
            was the necessity <lb/> that I recognised <lb/> for Ireland to have <lb/> her own legs to <lb/> stand on when the <lb/> smash comes at the <lb/> other side of the <lb/> water that made <lb/> me first take up <lb/> Home Rule.   I think we are going <lb/> to come out on top <lb/> this time   Yrs. ever   <seg type="unclear">G.Dease</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>