<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4447">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Colonel F.A. Heygate Lambert, 20 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Colonel F.A. Heygate Lambert regarding the release of 152 Irish prisoners.

In 1916 Col. F.A. Heygate Lambert (1857-1929) was serving as the Commandant of Frongoch Internment Camp. Lambert served in the camp until the last of the prisoners were released in December 1916. In the Spring of 1917 he went to Ypres to command a battalion of the Labour Corps.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI/CSO/RP/1916/13321/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4447</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-20</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0929">F.A. Heygate Lambert</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1722">Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_1"  type="Letter"  url="f1ec4b2e121941b2243e2526785a9af5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="588a9f52022bc0de9127ffbc55c312fb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="9a8664c3300bd61f9c82ebdd014a06bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="6ee1256d7a5395611a6b3187cf91aa9f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="8e9a48c97a590fce94c93fc016e9b17a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="d508050e892a08e8db1f66bee469d22f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="b484c666663fcb8ca12446d51a6f5b4e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4447_img_3797_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="d9619386a87a4505e65d7a84f9758371.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_1"/>
             <lb/>313106   20th July 1916.    Sir,   I am directed by the Secretary of State to inform<lb/>you that, on the recommendatio of the Advisry Committee,<lb/>he authorises the release from internment of the 152 persons<lb/>names in the accompsnying lists, this being the fourth<lb/>group of prisoners whose release he has authorised.  These releases should be carried out in accordance<lb/>with the instructions already sent you.  I am,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,   The Commandant,<lb/>Prisoners of War Camp,<lb/>Prongoah.<lb/>nr. Bala,<lb/>N. Wales  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_2"/>
            <lb/>LIMERICK CASES EXEMPT. <lb/>945 McINERNEY, Thos. A. <lb/>452 QUIGELY, Jas. <lb/>947 RUTTLE, Samuel.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_3"/>
            <lb/>CORK 2 EXEMPT. <lb/>1463 BUCKLEY, Wm. Banteer <lb/>552 O'CALLAGHAN, Corn. Mill Road <lb/>1104 CASEY, Wm. Mitchellstown <lb/>1104 ROCHE, Pat. F. " <lb/>913 FOLEY, Joseph Castletownbere <lb/>1060 HARRIS. Thos. F. Cork <lb/>1294 HEALY, Matthew Bandon <lb/>923 KINIVY, Martin Fermoy <lb/>919 LYNCH, Tim. Tracton Ballyfeard <lb/>1327 MEADE, Jas. Clonakility <lb/> 1327 MEADE, Wm. " <lb/>1087 MURPHY, Eugene Innisshannon <lb/>923 O'SHEA, Pat. J. Fermoy <lb/>920 REARDON Tim. Ballinhassig <lb/>379 WALSH, Redmond Kilmore <lb/>1594 WALSH, Thos. Cork
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_4"/>
            <lb/>GALWAY 2 EXEMPT. <lb/>1251 A BYRNES, Pat. ORANMORE <lb/>1490 D CALLAHAN, Pat. ATHENRY <lb/>1463 B CALLINAN, Thos. ATHENRY <lb/>1173 A CARR, Martin CASTLEGAR <lb/>1251 G CASSILEY, Peter GLAIR <lb/>1312 B COLLINS, John GLAIR <lb/>1307 D COMMONS, Edward TARRANUD <lb/>1167 CONNOLLY, Terrence ORANMORE <lb/>1397 D COMMONS, Edward TARRANUD <lb/>1167 CONNOLLY, Terrence ORANMORE <lb/>1397 B CONNORS, Joseph COLMANSTOWN <lb/>1315 CORBETT, Dominick KILLENEIN <lb/>1295 A COUGHLAN, Charles LOUGHRAE <lb/>1131 VREAVEN, John CLONSHECAHILL <lb/>1307 CUMMINS, Michael ATHENRY <lb/>1273 B CUMMINS. Jospeh TUIAN <lb/>1304 E CUNNIFFE, Michael ATHENRY <lb/>1310 A CORREEN, Joseph ATHENRY <lb/>1075 EGAN, Thomas ATHENRY <lb/>1260 FAHY, Peter ATHENRY <lb/>1599 FAHY, Thomas CRAUGHWELL <lb/>1174 FLAHERTY, Micheal KILLOME <lb/>1180 FORD, Pat. KILCOLGAN <lb/>1361 FURY, Michael CRAUGHWELL <lb/>1039 GOULDING, Pat. CRAUGHWELL <lb/>1174 B GRALISH, Pat. CARNMORE <lb/>1591 B HALLORAN, Denis KILTULLA <lb/>1175 B HELLY, Thomas SKEHENAGH <lb/>1173 HANLEY, John CASTLEGAR <lb/>1252 HAWLINS, Thomas ORANMORE <lb/>1197 C HOLLAND, Pat. BALLINCOURTY <lb/>1262 B KEATING, Joseph ATTYMON <lb/>1170 F KEIGHRY, Martin ARDRAHAN <lb/>1599 B KENNEDY, Michael BOYHILL. <lb/>1167 KING, John KILTULLA, ORANMORE <lb/>1167 KING, Pat. KILTULLA
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_5"/>
            <lb/>1055 LOUGHREY, John BALLYKILLIN <lb/>1131 MELODY, Michael CLOOMSHECAHILL <lb/>1360 MOLONEY, John CRAUGHWELL <lb/>1518 MOLONEY, John MONIVEA <lb/>1073 MONAGHAN, John ORANMORE <lb/>1196 D MORAN, John CLAREGALWAY <lb/>1040 C MORRISSEY, Pat ATHENRY <lb/>1040 C MORRISSEY, Richard ATHENRY <lb/>1308 B MULIN, Thomas ATHENRY <lb/>1199 MULROYAN, Bartley ORANMORE
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_6"/>
            <lb/><hi rend=”underline”></ Dublin City 2 exempt <lb/>369 BANKS, Henry <lb/>1495 BERRY, Wm <lb/>497 BEVAN, Joseph <lb/>1222 BRENNAN, Edward <lb/>380 BRENNAN, Pat. Milltown <lb/> 1 BRESLIN, T. <lb/>
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_7"/>
            <lb/>2. <lb/>1141 DOYLE, Thomas NORTH WALL <lb/>1101 DELEMERE, Edward <lb/>1596 DUFFEY, John <lb/>1428 DUNN, Frank. BALLBOUGH <lb/>1089 DUNN, Pat <lb/>1219 EARLY, John <lb/>1597 EDWARDS, Michael <lb/>1218 ENNIS, Thomas <lb/>1201 FARRELL, Michael <lb/>1503 FARRELL, Michael <lb/>1218 FARRELLY, John BROADSTONE <lb/>1378 FITZGERALD, Lear <lb/>1475 FLANAGAN, Pat <lb/>1159 FLANAGAN, Francis <lb/>1217 FLANAGAN, George <lb/>1217 FLANAGAN, Michael <lb/>438 FLEMING, Michael Pat. <lb/>1316 FLOOD, John. <lb/>1584 FOX, James <lb/>1142 FURLONG, Mathew <lb/>1159 GARLAND, Pat. <lb/>1215 GAVAN, John <lb/>1295 GEOGHEHAN, John <lb/>1215 GLEESON, Tom <lb/>447 GUILFOYLE, Jos <lb/>1552 HANNON, James <lb/>1542 HARNETT, John A <lb/>1160 HAYES, John or James CLONTARF <lb/>1584 HEALY, Jeremiah J.F <lb/>1567 HENDERSON, Thomas <lb/>1567 HENDERSON, Michael <lb/>996 HENDRICK or HENRY, Edward.
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_4447_img_3797_8"/>
            Kerry Exempt 958 SLATTERY, Thos. Tralee
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>