<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2361">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from a member of the Shackleton family, 25 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Rebecca Shackleton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter written by occupant of Anna Liffey House, Lucan during the Easter Rising. The author is one of the three Shackleton family members, John, George or perhaps Rebecca. The recipient is unknown.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Shackleton Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2361</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0605">Rebecca Shackleton</persName>
              <date>1916-04-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2068">Anna Liffey House, Lucan, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName >None</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName >None</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_1"  type="Letter"  url="874a75d10bd5a13dc8ad5d7d63b1099e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_2"  type="Letter"  url="33ebe88e77bbc5edcb5f028d90b05fec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_3"  type="Letter"  url="e10deaf97ff3b99d7afd9b0fdc1dbe39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_4"  type="Letter"  url="c07fc5a685550a6dae5ea8ecc50cfe8f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_5"  type="Letter"  url="63c7b4698dd4792a16dcf9bf9abeb15c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_6"  type="Letter"  url="a66157a1cfec6641d17f0ab2dfe47351.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_7"  type="Letter"  url="27c9ee7febd53fae14070170c1295cad.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_8"  type="Letter"  url="11b441b2684af1971e8a783394ba260d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_9"  type="Letter"  url="e8460a8124d0b0404e59d951667c78f0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2361_img_1807_10"  type="Letter"  url="23b94e711bab1a843769c7b6003cb355.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_1"/>
             Anna Liffey House,<lb/> Lucan   Tuesday 25.4.1916   Dear C   There may be a letter from you now in the G. P. O. but its unlikely<lb/> that I'll ever get it. At this present moment the G P O is in the <lb/> possession of <seg type="foreign">the Sinn Feiners</seg> (Irish Volunteers) — the Sinn Fein flag<lb/> is flying and Civil War reigns in Dublin.   An Irish Republic has been proclaimed. W. Connolly (Larkin's right<lb/> hand man) — ;<hi rend="underline">as President.</</hi><hi rend="underline"></hi>hi>    <hi rend="underline">Later</hi>. I have since learned Connolly was Vice President commander-in-chief<lb/> and H P Pearse was President.   This sounds very melodramatic, but it is true nevertheless - yest-<lb/> erday (Easter Monday) when most of the decent populace of Dublin (includ-ing <lb/> the Military) were away at Fairy<seg type="del">tho</seg>house Races — the rebels began their <lb/> work.   By 3.o'clock they had taken all the railway stations and all the <lb/> principal buildings in the city, including the General P. O. the Four<lb/> Courts, the S D Union, the Royal College of Surgeons, etc, they had <lb/> surrounded the Castle and had placed armed sentries at all<lb/> the bridges.   They have also taken Jacob's Biscuit Factory and yesterday there<lb/> was talk that they were going to blow the place up; they shot the sentry<lb/> and took the Powder Magazine in the Park.   I <sic>couln't</sic> believe my ears yesterday afternoon when a man telephoned<lb/> out from town and imparted all this news .   My brother and sister had gone to Fairyho, so I was alone, and had <lb/> to possess my soul in patience till they returned some hours later. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_2"/>
             They had heard rumours of rioting in town, but did not think much <lb/> of it as there does  be  such wild talk going these times but they did notice <lb/> that soldiers before returning to town in motors, were all trying to get <lb/> a hold of caps and hats to hide their identity.   Lots of troops have arrived in town from the Curragh and there is <lb/> talk of machine guns being brought into the city, but the train service <lb/> is much dislocated; the rebels have blown up parts of the Midland line; <lb/> the telephone may  not now be used except for military purposes and for calling <lb/> doctors so we are very much cut off - no telegrams - no letters- no telephone <lb/> calls.   Rumour has it that the city of Cork is in the hands of Sinn <lb/> Feiners and that 30,000 Germans (first it was 10,000) have landed <lb/> in Kerry. This last tit-bit was from our breadman's boy, so from that <lb/> unreliable authority I take it with a grain of salt! Be that as it <lb/> may, the serious side of the thing is that German money is at the back;<lb/> and also we fear German organisation.   <hi rend="underline">Later.</hi> This evening we hear that the G. P. O. is now in the hands of the <lb/> military ( A false report The Sinn Feiners held the G P O until the end) <lb/> and that many Sinn Feiners have been taken prisoners — Thank goodness —<lb/> but there's been a deal of blood-shed and many and many soldiers killed, <lb/> including a Colonel, officers and many men of the 5th Lancers.   The rebels have entrenched themselves in Stephen's Green and the <lb/> Military are now firing from the Shelbourne Hotel — my nephew cycled into <lb/> town today to see what he could see; he did not get further than Parliam-ent<lb/> St they were firing out of the City Hall, but he could not make out <lb/> whether Sinn Feiners or soldiers were in possession. He was told soldiers
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_3"/>
            but only rifles sticking out of the windows were visible. No police-men<lb/> anywhere about; one was killed yesterday at the Custom House and one <lb/> at the Castle of course they haven't a chance against rifles.   We've been to the village of Lucan this evening; there are couples <lb/> of mounted infantry stationed at different points and we understand there<lb/> are many more in ambush. It is rumoured the Sinn Feiners are likely<lb/> to give trouble in this district.   Leixlip (about a mile from Lucan) has for long been a hot-bed of <lb/> Sinn Feminism and Larkinism rather a deadly combination. About a<lb/> month ago some live bombs were discovered there in a drain by some child-ren <lb/> playing. There was a bit of excitement about it at the time, but<lb/> as usual no serious investigations were made and the scare died out.   The Leixlip bombs were evidently for blowing up the railway viaduct <lb/> when the time arrived.  <hi rend="underline">Wednesday A M </hi><lb/>  The news this A M is not cheering; Halligan's Mills (Flour Mills <lb/> in the city corresponding to ours) have been blown up; as my informant <lb/> remarked 'Halligan's Mills are as if they had never been'. (I saw <lb/> Halligan's Mills later; it was intact, as far as the building itself went.)   Bolands Mills (Boland's was taken early on by the rebels, who kept <lb/> the bakers there making bread for them), are also being shelled; I believe <lb/> by the Military to get out the rebels.   As against this is the good news that Liberty Hall has been shelled to <lb/> pieces by the Military big guns ranging from Phibsboro. Even here, at the <lb/> bottom of our garden (and sometimes from the house too) the guns can be <lb/> heard. On Thursday the rebels were given the chance to surrender but, <lb/> as they refused, they began to hammer them at 2 o'clock and they have been <lb/>  at it ever since.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_4"/>
             A great part of the city is fenced in barbed wire and now not only <lb/>unsafe but impossible to get in or out. The carnage in Sackville St<lb/> is something dreadful; picture to yourself trenches and barbed wire <lb/> fences in Sackville St. The Sinn Feiners have taken possession of <lb/> the houses on each side and without knocking down the houses and killing <lb/> quantities of women and children they cannot be got out. The women and <lb/> children refuse to go out; so you may imagine what is happening.  <hi rend="underline">Thursday.</hi><lb/>  We have been to Howth to visit two aunts who live there, taking <lb/> a circuitous route thro' the country. We found them in a bad way.   Food is getting very scarce and Howth is completely <sic>cur</sic> off from <lb/> supplies. While at Howth we heard that 10,000 troops have arrived <lb/> from England and that two battleships are in the Bay, but we are hearing <lb/> all sorts of things. One thing I've just heard with sorrow, is that the <lb/> G P O has been blown up (We hear different stories about the G P O every <lb/> day. The truth is the Rebels held it <seg type="del">all through</seg>  although  the shell (granite) of <lb/> the outer walls is standing and the pillars of the portico are intact.The <lb/> roof is gone).   It had to be done, it was so strongly held by the rebels; I'm <lb/> afraid lots of the buildings will have the same fate. Dublin will present <lb/> a very ruined appearance when the turmoil has subsided. It may be days <lb/> and it may be weeks before they get the rebels under. We hear a great <lb/> many of the National Volunteers (John Redmonds) have gone over to the side <lb/> of the Irish Volunteers and we have also heard a rumour that the rebels <lb/> have bombarded <sic>Tallamore</sic> Goal and liberated a couple of thousands of German <lb/> who were imprisoned there; and these have been added to their forces.   Certain it is that among the killed are some German officers. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_5"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Friday A.M.</hi><lb/>  Things are going on much the same; neither better or worse; but its <lb/> almost impossible for us to judge. The whole countyside from far and <lb/> wide are flocking to the mill for flour; there is always a long queue <lb/> outside the mill-gate; rich and poor all have to take their turn; they are <lb/> now let in singly or they would storm the place.   We hear that Sir Thomas Myles has been shot (our leading Dublin <lb/> surgeon) and when all is over, I'm afraid we'll hear of many more civilians <lb/> who have been killed or wounded. Up till now the number <lb/> of <sic>casualities</sic> of the British Army's as against the Irish Volunteers is I'm afraid much <lb/> bigger. As the troops were marching into Dublin they were being potted <seg type="del">out</seg> pat  <lb/> all the time by the rebels from the houses. It is terrible to think these <lb/> English soldiers who were training to fight the Germans abroad have had to <lb/> come over to Dublin to be shot down in such a way. It is unbearable to <lb/> think of; We, in Ireland, can never hold our heads up again. The Irish <lb/> Regiments (of the B Army) who are in Dublin are all confined to barracks.   They could not be asked to fight against their own; and it is feared <lb/> they would side with the rebels. (This is only true in part; The Irish <lb/> Regts have done well in putting down the Rebels.)   We are now under Martial Law and all must be in their houses by 6 30 <lb/> P M The other evening, when our cook was on her way home from the village <lb/> she heard one of the Village brats playing on a tin whistle 'A Nation once <lb/> Again'. I would have made short work of him if I had heard him!   My brother, George, went into Marlboro' Barracks last evening with <lb/> the motor lorry to take flour to the soldiers, they were living on biscuits.   The rebels are armed many of the them with up-to-date German rifles and <lb/> ammunition and they have plenty of machine guns.The other day a <hi rend="underline">hearse</hi> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_6"/>
            was let into the city and because it was a hearse and it was found to be <lb/> full of ammunition for the Sinn Feiners. Stephen's green is now clear <lb/> (except for a certain number of rebels, led by Countess <sic>Markievins</sic>) <lb/> in the Royal College of Surgeons, and the hottest part of the fight is in <lb/> Sackville St, Abbey St, and along the Quays, particularly about the Four <lb/> Courts. The Military are firing from the south side across the river <lb/> to the Four Courts and Four Courts Hotel which is packed with rebels.  <hi rend="underline">Sunday A.M </hi>  30. 4. 1916. <lb/>  Last evening at about 5 30 the Sinn Feiners surrendered uncondition-ally<lb/> (the Sinn Feiners under Pearse had surrendered but Connolly's gang were <lb/> still at large from their fortress, the G P O and about 150 rebels were <lb/> still in Jacob's sniping away as hard as they could).   We heard the news at Clonsilla (on my way home from a second <lb/> expedition to Howth). The past week seemed like an awful dream; particle-arly<lb/> out here at Anna Liffey this lovely Spring morning. I was almost <lb/> afraid just to believe the truth of the message for fear it was only a false <lb/> report but it was <sic>corrobarated</sic> last night. My brother and sister have <lb/> motored this morning to Sandymount to look after an uncle and aunt who live <lb/> there. They were in a very hot spot, I shouldn't be a bit surprised if <lb/> word comes that Uncle Richard is dead. <hi rend="underline">Later.</hi> (I saw Uncle Richard later <lb/> he is looking well, Their one servant had been marooned at Killiney and I <lb/> think the extra work helped them. They had had 6 soldiers in to tea one <lb/> night 'bayonets and all' as Uncle R. said. I don't think Uncle R will <lb/> ever speak of soldiers again as 'Hired assassins'. Their house has been <lb/> searched as were all the houses. Their sweep, a Sinn Feiner, was shot close <lb/>by.)   He is a serious man with a weak heart. They tell me that the
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_7"/>
            women were fighting as well as the men. The shop girls were firing <lb/> out from the houses at the soldiers; one girl shot a priest who was <lb/> supporting a wounded officer. Even after the surrender one could hear <lb/> the guns firing and we were told that was in the outlying districts in town, <lb/> where the news had not yet reached.   Yesterday a lot of policemen were killed up at <sic>Garrystown</sic> in County <lb/> Meath, the rebels have been seizing the Barracks in country districts <lb/> using them as a forte or carrying away ammunition they could find. Many <lb/> Sinn Feiners fled to the mountains yesterday and one district there was a <lb/> scrimmage with the soldiers among the hills.   I wonder what sort of news you in England are getting about Dublin; <lb/> the Government have only themselves to thank for the whole trouble.   <hi rend="underline">Birrell</hi> is the man who is chiefly responsible for this terrible <lb/> <sic>calmination</sic> and if Sir- Maxwell with full plenary power had not been sent <lb/> across on Thursday there would have been no surrender today.   One cannot help thinking great pity for the country lads belonging <lb/> to the Irish Volunteers army who were decoyed up to Dublin by hundreds <lb/> on Easter Monday, thinking they were merely coming for the usual parade <lb/> and then forced to take part. They were kept in ignorance of the plans for <lb/> two good reasons. They would never have come if they had known what was <lb/> likely to happen and also assuredly would have let out the secret and <lb/> spoilt all. However I suppose they have had some comfort in the thought <lb/> that they were laying down their lives for their country, the unfortunate, <lb/> misguided lads.  <hi rend="underline">"Eoin Mac Neill".</hi><lb/>  It seems that John Mc Neill, Head of the 'Irish Volunteers' and <lb/> Professor of the National University, did not intend this rising to take 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_8"/>
            place now. He wished to postpone it for 6 months in order to make <lb/> further and better preparations; but James Connolly (member of the D<lb/> Corporation, head of the Larkinites and Editor of the Workers Republic) <lb/> was anxious to carry it off now and Mc Neill was out voted.  <hi rend="underline">Monday.</hi><lb/>  They were unable to reach Sandymount yesterday. They were away <lb/> many hours and I was very anxious as two men bicycled out from <seg type="unclear">Foremore</seg> <lb/> and told me that though the Sinn Feiners under H. Pearse had surrendered <lb/> the citizen army (Larkinites) under James Connolly had refused to <lb/> surrender and were still at it. Later in the evening from the garden <lb/> we could hear the incessant booming of the big guns; G &amp;C.brought back <lb/> English papers from town; we could see by now you'll have some idea of <lb/> whats going on over here; but the casualties are grossly underestimated.   Yesterday in the R C Chapel here at both masses, Father Harly <lb/> offered prayers for the dead and dying Irish Volunteers and never a word <lb/> about all the soldiers and policemen who have fallen.   Ellen, our cook said it was most pointed. Its a grave scandal, <lb/> several other R C's have made the same complaint, most likely that old <lb/> Harly brute is a Pro-German.  <hi rend="underline">Monday  May 1  </hi><lb/>  We were over at Dunshaughlin today posting letters; we hear that <lb/> they go to England via Navan and Belfast. In the post office window <lb/> was the full notice in writing probably written out by a policeman——   'The Sinn Fein Leader, James Connolly unconditionally surrendered <lb/> to the General Officer, Commanding - in -Chief in Ireland.   Those leaders anxious to avoid further bloodshed have signed a <lb/> notice to the other Leaders and their parties both in Dublin and in the
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_9"/>
            country calling on them to surrender as their cause is hopeless".   The post mistress said this was the latest news and it came this <lb/> A M. In spite of the two surrenders, the guns are heard again this <lb/> evening. On the way home, we heard with much sorrow that the Co-Inspector<lb/> of Meath, Alex Gray, has died today from the wounds he received <lb/> in the Garristown affray.   We had heard that his hands were very badly shattered, he must, I <lb/> fear, have suffered horribly. He was D I some years ago in Lucan.   Smith, the D I of Navan was killed out right at the same time.   Sir Thos Myles has not been killed after all; but he was captured <lb/> by the Sinn Feiners and taken by them to Richmond Hospital to attend to <lb/> their wounded.   A very unfortunate thing <sic>accurred</sic> in <sic>Guiness'</sic> Brewery last evening <lb/> we heard from a friend who is employed there as a clerk; two of his fellow<lb/> clerks and two officers who were on the premises doing night duty were <lb/> fired at and killed by a sentry because they had not electric torches in <lb/> their hands. That (carrying lights) was to be a sign that they were not <lb/>marauders.  <hi rend="underline">Tuesday</hi><lb/>  Although the rebels have surrendered unconditionally; at Chapelizod <lb/> and in other parts, sniping still continues; several hundred mounted <lb/> Infantry are in Dunboyne; presumably to surround the Garristown Camp (400 <lb/> Sinn Feiners) or to waylay a <sic>contigent</sic> from the South.  <hi rend="underline">Thursday.  4.5.16 </hi>  We were in town yesterday, G &amp; I. He has a pass through the city <lb/> and all women and children are now let in without let or hindrance.   There is not very much sign of the fight until one gets to Sackville
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_2361_img_1807_10"/>
            St; there the scene is just appalling; Henry St and Abbey St are pretty <lb/> bad too; I need not write about them, you can read all about the <lb/> desolation in the papers. We went up and down thro' the city; looking <lb/> up various people whose friends were anxious about them.   I ran up against Dr Douglas Hyde (Dr Hyde founded the Gaelic League <lb/> he was not a Sinn Feiner but many of his friends were. He never believed <lb/> they would actually rise), near Baggott Street Bridge. He told me he was <lb/> heartbroken; his friend T McDonagh (a clever literary man, a poet and <lb/> a Professor of the National University) had just been tried by Court <lb/> Martial and shot that morning and also P H. Pearse, Head of St Enda's <lb/> School, Count and Countess Plunkett (their son, Joseph Plunkett, a Sinn <lb/> Fein leader, was tried and shot on Friday), and many others have been <lb/> arrested .  J. Connolly is in hospital with a gunshot in his leg. I suppose they <lb/> will shoot him when he recovers. He is one for whom I feel no pity.   Occasional sniping going on even yesterday. We can now get the <lb/> Irish Times and the Evening Mail is also out. In it we read that three <lb/> out of the seven <seg type="del">signatures</seg> signatories  of the notice proclaiming the Irish Republic <lb/> have been tried by Court Martial and shot vis; T Mac Donagh, P H Pearse, <lb/> and T J Clarke, the last named was a long standing rebel; he was a <sic>Feinan</sic> <lb/> of the old days; he was sentenced to penal servitude and when he had served <lb/> his time he came back to Ireland and has kept a little shop in a back street <lb/> on the North side of Dublin selling tobacco, and seditious newspapers. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>