<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3648">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fellow & Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to Alfred Miller, 10 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) to Alfred Miller (1884-1942) concerning the nomination of Dr Thomas Gillman Moorehead (1879-1960) to the vacant professorship of the theory and practice of medicine in the Royal College of Surgeons (RCSI).

Alfred Miller served as both the registrar of the Royal College of Surgeons (1910-1938) and as secretary to the Conjoint Board of the College of Physicians and College of Surgeons. At the outbreak of the Rising Miller instructed James Duncan, the college porter, to lock the college doors in order to deter Michael Mallin&#39;s occupying rebel force in St. Stephen&#39;s Green. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-180</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3648</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0845">Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date>1916-07-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0696">Alfred Miller</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1615">Royal College of Surgeons, Stephen's Green, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3648_img_3044_1"  type="Letter"  url="b7144ac937da561867ba15f3604a1f78.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3648_img_3044_1"/>
             10th JULY 16.   Alfred Miller,Esq., <lb/>Registrar, <lb/>R.C.S.I.,Dublin.   Dear Sir,   I am <sic>dirested</sic> by the President and Fellows of the Royal <lb/>College of Physicians of Ireland to state that in compliance <lb/>with the terms of the Constitution of the Conjoint Examining <lb/>Boards they have nominated Dr.T.Gillman Moorhead for the <lb/>vacant Professorship of the Theory and Practice of Medicine <lb/>in the Schools of Surgery of the Royal College of Surgeons <lb/>in Ireland. Herewith I enclose Dr.Moorhead's application.   I remain, <lb/>Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>