<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3077">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Howard Kelly to White, 1 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Howard Kelly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Howard Kelly was Commander of the HMS Gloucester during WWI. He would subsequently enjoy an impressive career in the navy including acting as British Naval Mission to Greece. He also became Commander of the 1st Battle Squadron in the Atlantic Fleet in 1923 and commander of the 2nd Cruiser Squadron in 1925. 

He went on to be Admiralty representative to the League of Nations in 1927 and commander of the 1st Battle Squadron and second-in-command of the Mediterranean Fleet in 1929. His last appointment was intended to be Commander-in-Chief, China Station in 1931. 

Arethusa Leigh-White married Edward Leigh-White in 1904 and played a prominent part in life in the Bantry area throughout her lifetime. She would serve as director of the World Association of Girl Guides and Girl Scouts from 1938-1947. This letter is both personal nature but also details some aspects of life on-board during wartime.

This is a letter from the extensive Bantry Estate Collection, held in the Boole Library of University College Cork. The collection, which covers a period of 300 years, contains the formal records regarding the legal, financial and general administration of this large house and estate in County Cork.  </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>UCC Library Special Collections and Archives</repository>
                  <collection>The Bantry Estate Collection BL_EP_B_2546_38</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3077</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0830">Howard Kelly</persName>
              <date>1916-01-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0918">H.M.S. Gloucester</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Arethusa Leigh-White</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0238">Bantry House, Bantry, Co. Cork</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1952</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3077_img_2480_1"  type="Letter"  url="20273c2059e44b742a7da0e20b1433fb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3077_img_2480_2"  type="Letter"  url="c1735d9727f9bcd396e180809d7e230f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3077_img_2480_3"  type="Letter"  url="b9c1e7e72470804c65f8dd1ca05e3032.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3077_img_2480_4"  type="Letter"  url="732cc6cb05fc91ec4f18fa69a9fcc8af.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3077_img_2480_1"/>
             H.M.S. Gloucester   Jan 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1916   Dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Leigh-White   You <seg type="unclear">are</seg> still better known <lb/>to me by name, and from <lb/>long before George &amp; <seg type="unclear">Madge</seg> <lb/>had even met you, and <lb/>Eva White at Coomhoola is <lb/>a first cousin of mine, but <lb/>you had always happened to <lb/>be away <seg type="unclear">as many</seg> my visits to <lb/>Bantry. I am afraid I <lb/>haven't heard anything for the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3077_img_2480_2"/>
            <twins except to present their <lb/>wings separated. it was really <lb/>rather pathetic, one got the <lb/>mumps, and now-a-days in <lb/>war times any one leaving the <lb/>ship for hospital or elsewhere <lb/> leaves for good. After the sick <lb/>one had left I sent for the <lb/>other to tell him to write and <lb/>tell his mother I would get <lb/>the twins back some how and <lb/>her arrival in my cabin in <lb/>floods of tears, though I don't
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3077_img_2480_3"/>
            think they bother about each <lb/>other when they are together.   They are both very good boys <lb/>and quite bright and smart in <lb/>their minds, and after all the <lb/><seg type="unclear">colour</seg> of their minds is more <lb/>important than the <seg type="unclear">colour</seg>of their <lb/>hands and feet, especially in <lb/>war times. Owing to our <lb/>unfortunate depart in the ship <lb/>she will probably be seeing home <lb/>again for another fourteen days in <lb/>about a weeks time, which <lb/>I hope won't be too much for <lb/> their family  .
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3077_img_2480_4"/>
             I am hoping to spend a night <lb/> at   at the end of next <lb/>week.   Yours sincerely   <hi rend="underline">Howard Kelly.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>