<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4291">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Huggard to Edward Carson, 15 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Huggard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Huggard to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4291</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1508">William Huggard</persName>
              <date>1915-11-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0978">Tralee, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4291_img_3654_1"  type="Letter"  url="36f6be3180ae36f529cae8035e9db52b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4291_img_3654_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="863e329aaacb7c2633196a45cb44e4b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4291_img_3654_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="f42f9c386ac2d24eafde197d8e3a75ae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4291_img_3654_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="db825eb33bf0abde5e9da3fc107d0f2e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4291_img_3654_1"/>
            <seg type="head">NORWICH UNION FIRE INSURANCE SOCIETY LTD. <lb/>A. D. 1797.</seg>  <hi rend="superscript">TELEPHONE NO 95. <lb/>TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS "AGENTS TRALEE"</hi> <lb/>Estate Office, <lb/>Tralee.   LATE <lb/>HUSSEY, DENNY &amp; HUGGARD, <lb/>AGENTS. <lb/><hi rend="underline">NOW WILLIAM HUGGARD, F.S.I.</hi>   15th November 1915.   Dear Sir,   You will be interested to read the enclosed from the pen <lb/>of the R. C. Bishop of Limerick. The Loyalists of the South, think <lb/>it a great weakness on the part of the Government, at this time of <lb/>stress and need, to allow any men of Military age to leave the <lb/>Country.   May I express the hope that you may see your way to oppose <lb/>the Arming of the Nationalist Volunteers for <hi rend="underline">"HOME defence"</hi>, a course <lb/>which the Newspapers suggest is in contemplation. They are anxious <lb/>to be Armed and legalised merely as a preparation for the introduction <lb/>of Home Rule.   Your high Imperial and unselfish principles are greatly ap- <lb/>preciated by the Loyal Minority, and this/is my excuse for taking the <lb/>liberty of sending the/enclosed.   Yours faithfully,   W. Huggard.   The Right Hon Sir Edward Carson. K. C. M. P. <lb/>The House of Commons. <lb/>LONDON. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4291_img_3654_2"/>
            <!-- Clip from the Irish Times -->  Irish Times <lb/>13 NOV. 1915  <seg type="head">EMIGRA<hi rend="underline">NTS AND TH</hi>E WAR. <lb/>A REMARKABLE LETTER.</seg>  The Roman Catholic Bishop of Limerick has <lb/>sent the following letter to the Munster <lb/>News:—   SIR, — The treatment which the poor Irish <lb/>emigrant lads have received at Liverpool is <lb/>enough to make any Irishman's blood boil <lb/>with anger and indignation. What wrong <lb/>have they done to deserve insults and outrage <lb/>at the hands of a brutal English mob? They <lb/>do not want to be forced into the English <lb/>Army and sent to fight battles in some part <lb/>of the world. Is not that within their right? <lb/>They are supposed to be freemen, but they <lb/>are made to feel that they are prisoners, who <lb/>may be compelled to lay down their lives for a <lb/>cause that is not worth "three rows of pins" <lb/>to them. It is very probable that these poor <lb/>Connaught peasants know little or nothing of <lb/>the meaning of the war. Their blood is not <lb/>stirred by the memories of Kossovo, and they <lb/>have no burning desire to die for Serbia. <lb/>They would much prefer to be allowed to till <lb/>their own potato gardens in peace in Conne- <lb/>mara. Small nationalities, and the wrongs of <lb/>Belgium and Rheims Cathedral, and all the <lb/>other cosmopolitan considerations that rouse <lb/>the enthusiasm of the Irish Party, but do not <lb/>get enough of recruits in England, are far too <lb/>high-flying for uneducated peasants, and it <lb/>seems a cruel wrong to attack them because <lb/>they cannot rise to the level of the dis- <lb/>interested Imperialism of Mr. T. P. O' Connor <lb/>and the rest of the New Brigade.   But in all the shame and humiliation of this <lb/>disgraceful episode, what angers one most is <lb/>that there is no one, not even one of their own <lb/>countrymen, to stand up and defend them. <lb/>Their crime is that they are not ready to die <lb/>for England. Why should they? What have <lb/>they or their forebears ever got from England <lb/>that they should die for her? Mr. Redmond <lb/>will say a Home Rule Act on the Statute <lb/>Book. But any intelligent Irishman will say <lb/>a simulacrum of Home Rule, with an express <lb/>notice that it is never to come into operation. <lb/>This war may be just or unjust, but any fair- <lb/>minded man will admit that it is England's <lb/>war, not Ireland's. When it is over, if Eng- <lb/>land wins, she will hold a dominant power in <lb/>this world, and her manufactures and her <lb/>commerce will increase by leaps and bounds. <lb/>Win or lose, Ireland will go on, in her old <lb/>round of misgovernment, intensified by a <lb/>grinding poverty which will make life intoler- <lb/>able. Yet the poor fellows who do not see <lb/>the advantage of dying for such a cause are to <lb/>be insulted as "shirkers" and "cowards," <lb/>and the men whom they have raised to power <lb/>and influence have not one word to say on <lb/>their behalf. If there is to be conscription, <lb/>let it be enforced all round; but it seems to <lb/>be the very intensity of injustice to leave <lb/>English shirkers by the million go free, and <lb/>coerce the small remnant of the Irish race into <lb/>a war which they do not understand, and <lb/>which, whether it is right or wrong, has but a <lb/>secondary and indirect interest for them. —   I am, dear sir, your obedient servant, <lb/>EDWARD THOMAS, <lb/>Bishop of Limerick.   10th November, 1915. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4291_img_3654_3"/>
            <!-- Back of the Irish Times clip --> <seg type="head">BALKAN WAR <lb/><hi rend="underline">THEATRE.</hi> <lb/>BULGAR DEFEAT BY <lb/>TH<hi rend="underline">E FREN</hi>CH. <lb/>SERBIANS RETREAT- <lb/>ING IN GOOD ORDER.</head  Telegrams received in Athens confirm the re- <lb/>ported defeat of the Bulgarians by the <lb/>French near Kuprili, and the great losses <lb/>sustained by the enemy. The news is not <lb/>officially confirmed, and the Bulgarians <lb/>in their latest despatch make no mention <lb/>of this battle.   The Serbians report that they are retreating <lb/>in good order south and east of Kraljevo <lb/>and east of Ivanjica. Fierce combats took <lb/>place on the left bank of the Southern <lb/>Morava.   The Germans report that their pursuit of the <lb/>Serbians continues south of the line Kral- <lb/>jevo Trstenik.  <seg type="head">(PRESS ASSOCIATION WAR SPECIAL.) <lb/>ATHENS, THURSDAY.</seg>  A telegram from Salonika to the Patris <lb/>says the French have inflicted a sever defeat <lb/>on the Bulgarians near Kuprili (Veles).   The Bulgarians, who sustained immense <lb/>losses, demanded a short armistice for the <lb/>burying of the dead.   The fall of Kuprili is considered imminent. <lb/>The Serbian Legation here believes in the <lb/>possibility of this news, but there is no official <lb/>confirmation.  <seg type="head">SERBIAN REPORT. <lb/>(PRESS ASSOCIATION WAR SPECIAL.) <lb/>PARIS, Friday.</seg>  A serbian official <seg type="foreign">communique</seg> issued on <lb/>November 10th says:—   We occupied in good order the defensive <lb/>positions south and east of Kraljevo and east <lb/>of Ivanjica, and also positions on the eastern <lb/>front, on the left bank of Southern Morava, <lb/>where fierce combats took place.  <seg type="head">BULGARIAN <sic>DESPATCH</sic>. <lb/>(PRESS ASSOCIATION WAR SPECIAL.) <lb/>AMSTERDAM, Friday.</seg>  The Sofia official <seg type="foreign">communique</seg> says: —   Our troops on the 10th continued the pursuit <lb/>of the defeated Serbian Army on the left <lb/>bank of the Morava. Fresh booty is dis- <lb/>covered daily in the conquered towns.   In the Morava valley, along the railway, <lb/>we captured to-day four quick-;firing howitzers, <lb/>eight quick-firing field guns, with ammunition <lb/>carts; eight machine guns.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4291_img_3654_4"/>
            <seg type="head">IRISH VO<hi rend="underline">LUNTEE</hi>R FORCE <lb/>TO COME <hi rend="underline">UNDER</hi> NEW BILL.</seg> <lb/>The "Times" says — It is understood there is a <lb/>likelihood the passing into law of Lord Lincoln- <lb/>shire's Volunteer Bill. It gives power to the War <lb/>Office to accept the services of Volunteer corps in <lb/>England and Wales for home defence. The <lb/>Nationalists, however, took strong exception to the <lb/>omission of Ireland, and to the possible frustration of <lb/>Mr Redmond's dream, to which he gave expression <lb/>in a memorable speech, of the Nationalist and Ulster <lb/>Volunteers defending the coasts of Ireland side by <lb/>side, The Government have now acceded to their <lb/>wish that the Bill should apply to the United King-; <lb/>dom as a whole, and Lord Newton will move <lb/>amendments accordingly. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>