<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3378">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Carson to Herbert Asquith, 11 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Carson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928) was Liberal Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1908 to 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10679-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3378</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0928">Robert Carson</persName>
              <date>1916-03-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1384">7 Waring Street, Belfast, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0003">Herbert Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0665">10 Downing Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3378_img_2790_1"  type="Letter"  url="be5902b2ad47e7e2469c2b3cf026d8f9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3378_img_2790_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0dc00e317d9896d6551ee5ace0641c5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3378_img_2790_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">copy</hi>  <lb/> 7 Waring Street<lb/>Belfast  Sept 9<hi rend="superscript"><hirend=\'underline\">th</hirend=\'underline\"></hi> 1916 <!-- the date on the letter states 1914, is listed above as 1916 -->  Lord Stamfordham<lb/>Private Secretary to the King  Buckingham Palace. London   My Lord   Re The Home Rule Bill and the Betrayal of<lb/>Ulster by the government.  In the interests of His Majesty, The Crown, and the<lb/>British Empire I write you the following facts.  The <hi rend="underline">Home Rule Bill</hi> has not been submitted to the<lb/>Nation, <hi rend="underline">Asquith</hi> has <hi rend="underline">no mandate</hi> from the Parliamentary<lb/>voters of the <hi rend="underline">United</hi> Kingdom to place the<hi rend="underline">Home Rule Bill</hi><lb/>on the <hi rend="underline">Statue Book</hi>-  The Parliament act was obtained by <hi rend="underline">Asquith</hi> by false<lb/>representations, fraud &amp; force and under threat to create<lb/>500 new Lords all Radicals or Home Rulers. The House<lb/>of Lords was to be reconstructed, this has not been done.<lb/>Asquith holds office by a compact with the Nationalists<lb/>by bribery and corruption and payment of £400 a year to<lb/>members out of British Ratepayers pockets. All their<lb/>voting since being paid for their services is<hi rend="underline">illegal</hi> as the<lb/>members of Parliament were not re-elected-Asquith<lb/>dare not put his policy before the Electorate.  The Home Rule Bill has been admitted by Govern—<lb/>—ment to be a <hi rend="underline">bad Bill </hi>and unworkable. The Government<lb/>found it necessary to bring forward an amending Bill<lb/>and which has not yet been settled.  On the outbreak of <hi rend="underline">War Asquith called on the opposition</hi><lb/>to back up the Government and show a solid &amp; united front<lb/>to the Enemy, and <hi rend="underline">he gave an undertaking that all</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">controversial matters &amp; bills were to be hung up until after </hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">the War without prejudice to either party.</hi> <!-- Letter is dated 1914? above states it is to Herbert Asquith, Lord Stamfordham Private Secretary to the King in 1914 was Arthur Bigge the letter is about Asquith --> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3378_img_2790_2"/>
             Asquith now tries to place the condemned Home Rule Bill<lb/>on the <hi rend="underline">Statute Book to please his rebel Nationalists supporters</hi><lb/>and <hi rend="underline">break faith with the Nation,</hi> and by so doing <hi rend="underline">break up the<lb/><sic>the</sic> British Nation</hi> and <hi rend="underline">cause War in Ireland</hi>and which<lb/>will extend to England, if <hi rend="underline">His Majesty signs this Bill<lb/>without first having it submitted to the Electors of the still<lb/>United Kingdom</hi> it will break up the <hi rend="underline">British Empire</hi><lb/>and may cause dethronement- Asquith has all<lb/>along been a <hi rend="underline">traitor</hi> to <hi rend="underline">his King</hi> + <hi rend="underline">country,</hi> he + his cabinet<lb/>should have been taken to the <hi rend="underline">tower yard and shot.</hi>  Ulster people have not forgotten his <hi rend="underline">dastardly plot </hi>to<lb/>murder the Loyal Ulster Protestants in their beds. General<lb/><seg type="unclear">Gough</seg>was ordered to get into Ulster by forced marchers.<lb/>set the Province in a <hi rend="underline">blaze</hi> + make the <hi rend="underline">red blood flow</hi><lb/>and drive the people to the coast towns where <seg type="unclear">Churchill</seg> and<lb/>the battle-ships could destroy them + the towns + ruin <hi rend="underline">Ulster</hi>  In this way <hi rend="underline">Ulster Protestants Loyalty</hi>was to be rewarded-<lb/>the<hi rend="underline">German Emperor</hi>could not be plotting a more<lb/><hi rend="underline">diabolical outrage</hi> than this- And now Lord Kitchener calls<lb/>for volunteers from Ulster to fight for England + the Flag. Ulster<lb/>has responded to the call. Asquith would again betray Ulster.  The Irish Nationalist volunteers 300.000 strong, how many of<lb/>them have volunteered to fight for old England at this crisis. They<lb/>shout that <hi rend="underline">England's difficulty is Ireland opportunity </hi>I know<lb/>Ireland well for many years. always the Irish roman Catholics<lb/>have been rebels, and the sooner Lord Kitchener rounds them<lb/>up and sends them to the front the better it will be for the<lb/>United Kingdom. Should Asquith put this condemned<lb/><hi rend="underline">Home Rule Bill </hi>before <hi rend="underline">His Majesty</hi> let him <hi rend="underline">consider<lb/>well before signing it.</hi>  <lb/> I am my Lord<lb/>yours faithfully <lb/> Robert Carson     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>