<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4181">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 14 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/59</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4181</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-14</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4181_img_3554_1"  type="Letter"  url="7bbd1cabf5e456917395f964d3691d8e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4181_img_3554_2"  type="Letter"  url="3eca0585f7f651d22e75b7cd861aabe8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4181_img_3554_1"/>
             Gore is strong <lb/>on the future <lb/>rapprochement in <lb/>Ireland &amp; points <lb/>to the way in <lb/>which our men <lb/>got on with the <lb/>Dublin Fus<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> as <lb/>an example. I <lb/>should have thought <lb/>he had had one <lb/>lesson but <lb/>suppose he'll <lb/>want another   If it's after this <lb/>war I don't mind <lb/>but I don't want <lb/>a practical one <lb/>now.    14 Nov   My dear very remote pr   Rather a disgruntled b w .First of all no letters have come <lb/>for 3 days, nor what <hi rend="underline">of course</hi> I mind much more any papers. <lb/>Next you will hardly believe it but I hear that Hickan </seg> <lb/>after an extra good lunch got round Gen N &amp; has persuaded <lb/>him to give Chich more leave &amp; to let him have a chance <lb/>of coming out here later. It really is too disgraceful, &amp; it almost <lb/>makes me a socialist for undoubtedly Lord <seg type="unclear">Townuddy </seg>&amp; Lady <lb/><seg type="unclear">Tweebledo</seg> are responsible but I find it hardly credible. Please let <lb/>Sir G &amp; Gen P know. Won't they be pleased.   Next I hear that the Comports Committee sat &amp; talked <lb/>but have not decided much except that they are short of funds. <lb/>Apparently  2000 has been promised for the Gunners who are <lb/>not Ulster men &amp; who are not out here yet, a  450 for the others, <lb/>&amp;there seems to be no plan. I dont' fancy Mrs   likes being <lb/>bossed by Lady C but surely the Duchess can look after both &amp; <lb/>make all play up. It seems to me that this is the least <lb/>we can ask of our Aristocracy now, <seg type="del"> </seg> instead of pulling strings for <lb/>their <seg type="unclear">proteges.    I am getting not only reconciled but quite eagerly <lb/>looking forward now to the quiet life which will be <lb/>inevitable after the war. I heard from Linsay on the telephone <lb/>that a letter had come out 4 months ago &amp; that he had returned <lb/>to his regiment as junior Captain. He thinks that at the <lb/>present rate he will work up to his old place before the war. <lb/>Certainly I did not understand this from his letter, &amp; it alters his <lb/>case entirely, but I don't intend to follow his example &amp; go back
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4181_img_3554_2"/>
            under boys 15 years junior to myself, which is what would <lb/>happen in the Gunners! I hope that nothing will prevent one <lb/>from regaining one's independence before many months but I don't <lb/>want the war to stop till Germany is beat. There are a lot of <lb/>unpleasant rumours in the air about this, &amp; one political <lb/>personage says the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>will one day make peace without acquaint <lb/>ing any one. Certainly <seg type="unclear">Squiffy's</seg>assertions that he will never <lb/>do so till Germany is squashed make this seem quite possible. I <lb/>should not like to be the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> in that case <seg type="del">with</seg> especially when <lb/>The Ulster Div returned!   One also hears the senior Gents discussing quite openly that <lb/>the New Armies are not 17 out here &amp; showing how those which have <lb/>done well have hardly been noticed whilst other troops who have done <lb/>less well have been cracked up to the skies. Eg 1 Div the Canadians <lb/>I think are described as having captured a first line of trenches with <lb/>great gallantry, when as a matter of fact these trenches had been unoccu- <lb/>pied for weeks. I believe they did quite well but why make them laughed <lb/>at out here &amp; arouse bitterness by such complaints. Our Friend   <lb/>when GSO 2 earlier came breathless to the 2 Army &amp; announced that <lb/>one of our Divs was in full disorganised retreat. There was naturally <lb/>a bit of a stir, &amp; up to the present   have not been able to <lb/>find out what he saw whether a   party or some men chasing <lb/>a rat. The GOC to whom he reported, Smith Darwin, is now at <lb/>home &amp; duly a Div'Com<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>&amp; wanting a corps ! However now <lb/>I have left off steam, &amp; I hope not made you quite ill I feel <lb/>better tho' I wish Winston Churchill were not coming out here <lb/>to join his regiment (? I will bet any one some money that he <lb/>won't be in his regiment one month; probably he will be made GSO 1 <lb/>for a fortnight before becoming a General. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>