<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5682">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 7 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Marie Martin (1892–1975) joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment (VAD) upon the outbreak of World War 1. During her time as a VAD in Malta, and at the Battle of the Somme in France, she regularly wrote to her mother Mary Martin (1866-1955) in Dublin. In her letters, she tended to describe her day to day duties as a VAD, her patients and trips she would take on her days off.  
In this letter, Marie begins by describing her ailments to her mother.  She is suffering from diarrhoea and her face is swollen from insect bites.  She discusses the number of patients she is caring for and some of her day to day duties as a VAD in Malta.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Malta Letters</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5682</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1540">Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5682_img_783_1"  type="Letter"  url="5e58ceedf1d72204dec952f1fe400f4b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5682_img_783_2"  type="Letter"  url="4b8e1f1be896d359d0e46e153e7ce35e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5682_img_783_3"  type="Letter"  url="31a266297d4dbb8238717823dcffc867.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5682_img_783_4"  type="Letter"  url="bdfc23c07aa9f1cbaa9004fb39b49487.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5682_img_783_5"  type="Letter"  url="2e611b8f65f953e7db15a95f27aaba85.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5682_img_783_1"/>
             7th Nov 1915   My own dearest Mother,<    I am very sorry for leaving you so <lb/>long without writing but really I have <lb/>not had time till to-day when matron <lb/>gave me a day off as she did not <lb/>think I looked up to the mark, for <lb/>the last couple of days I have had a <lb/>touch of diarrhoea which rather disturbed <lb/>my nights rest &amp; instead of the work getting <lb/>easier it is getting harder. I have been changed <lb/>up to upper E Block &amp; we got in a new <lb/>convoy the other day with a very bad lot <lb/>of dysentery cases but I am glad to say the <lb/>days rest has done me a lot of good &amp; I <lb/>am feeling quite myself again &amp; in the <lb/>best of form, it is no wonder the Matron <lb/>said I was not looking well, my face <lb/>is like a bit of putty pulled in to a very <lb/>funny shape as the mosquitos and sandflies <lb/>have my face in a terrible state all my <lb/>eyes swollen up with them, it is very <lb/>funny how they go for me, the men <lb/>have a great joke about it &amp; say they
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5682_img_783_2"/>
            the mosquitos know whats good" I suppose you <lb/>got my <seg type="unclear">Cath</seg> about the camera, they say it <lb/>is much better to buy one out here as one <lb/>has to declare everything in parcels &amp; would <lb/>most probably take camera out   I shall try &amp; write you a proper description <lb/>of this sometime when I can get a man <lb/>to bring it home &amp; post it in England, as <lb/>it is rather like the G. Prisoners here <lb/>we have to be very careful what we <lb/>say or the letters do not go, I shall <lb/>explain all this later .   I am really not lonely as we have no <lb/>time to be, you might tell Aunt Lily the <lb/>work is much harder than you can <lb/>imagine &amp; to be sure not to come out <lb/>without <seg type="unclear"> camp kit wear</seg> if you are not <lb/>under canvas one very often has to use <lb/>the beds &amp; wash basins. There is a very <lb/>strong rumour that shortly we are all <lb/>going to be sent on to Servia, I really <lb/>do not think it can be harder than <lb/>here &amp; the sanitary arrangements could <lb/>not be much worse, it would mostly <lb/>be surgical work out there . 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5682_img_783_3"/>
             However we must only wait &amp; see perhaps if you <lb/>would rather I did not go I could remain here <lb/>and go to another hospital if they are keeping <lb/>any open but what they say is that they <lb/>will not be using this much if they are <lb/>giving up Gallipoli for the present . <lb/> Letters take so long going &amp; coming one <lb/>has to write about things long before <lb/>we really know, the post arrived to-day <lb/>but got nothing but a letter from <lb/>Nana. Tell her I was delight to get <lb/>it &amp; hope Andrew is better, give them <lb/>all my fondest love &amp; big kisses . <lb/>I cannot tell you how relieved I was <lb/>to hear the good news of Charlie, I <lb/>hope he will continue to let us know <lb/>how things are going with him I do <lb/>not think they are doing much out <lb/>there we hear no war news except <lb/> now &amp; again a bad rumour of a <lb/>Transport being sunk — It is quite <lb/>exciting here some times, the practicing <lb/>of the guns make quite a good noise <lb/>we thought we were being invaded
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5682_img_783_4"/>
            when we 1st came.    I would like so much to be able to <lb/>do something for the men at Xmas in <lb/>my flock! but of course the difficulty <lb/>is to know what to get them sent <lb/>out, so I was think perhaps if Violet <lb/>made a small collection round our <lb/>relations &amp; friends &amp; collected enough <lb/>of pounds I could give them a <lb/>little treat by give them cakes &amp; <lb/> cigarettes the poor men have a very <lb/>hard time of it here. That is all <lb/>I can say — I am sure they would <lb/> not mind giving about 5/- each, the <lb/>other V,A.D is doing the same for <lb/>our 140 beds as we try &amp; give <lb/>them as jolly a day as possible .<lb/>What about your photo, I am <seg type="unclear">looking</seg> <lb/> for it, Everyone of the Girls said you <lb/>looked so sweet at the train &amp; they were <lb/> <sic>no</sic> surprised at me feeling leaving you <lb/> so much.    Did the Oxfordshire go to Dublin <lb/>since, I wonder if you are getting my
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5682_img_783_5"/>
            —letters alright, I never got the things <lb/>from the J A N Stores it was nearly <lb/> a £1 worth — but perhaps they will <lb/>turn up, the post is very bad we <lb/>long from Sunday to Sunday because <lb/>that is the day we get the post out <lb/>here. Last night a convoy of <seg type="unclear">Pam</seg> Nurses <lb/> arrived just for the week and their <lb/>uniform is too smart for words &amp; then they <lb/>have stars just the same as officers on <lb/>their shoulders with a sand brown leather <lb/>belt &amp; a pale blue uniform with white <lb/>aprons &amp; square bibs    I have a very nice lot of men but was <lb/>very sorry having lower E. I was just <lb/>getting in to their ways &amp; to know the <lb/>patients, however all these things are in <lb/>the days work.   I hope this will find your cold alright <lb/>&amp; that Andrew is up and well <lb/>With every good wish love &amp; blessing <lb/>to you dearest Mother  Your ever loving daughter   Marie 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>