<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2730">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Tate to his mother, Millicent Tate (née Farren), 14 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Tate</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Tate to his mother in which he refers to a new sailing boat that has arrived to the port which they are using for sailing in the evenings. He also talks about a new ambulance, the cavalry, and technical work for the bridge. He also asks for books and copies of Blackwood Magazine to be sent to him.

James&#39;s father, Alec C Tate, also served with British army in India before he married Millicent Farren and started a family in Whiteabbey Co. Antrim. Their sons, James and William continued the military tradition and enlisted with the British army with James serving as a Second Lieutenant with the Indian Expeditionary Force. James spent the majority of the war in India during which time the Indian Expeditionary Force was dispatched to Mesopotamia. 

This letter is part of a collection that he wrote to his parents detailing his movements and his day to day experience.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Tate Papers, D2859/2/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2730</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0347">James Tate</persName>
              <date>1916-08-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1952">No.3 Bridging Train, Indian Expeditionary Force</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Millicent Tate</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1128">2 Glenlua, Ballycastle, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2730_img_2150_1"  type="Letter"  url="32eae473fd43a5e131f4da1c62ba0ca3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2730_img_2150_2"  type="Letter"  url="d815d4dedb0d883becae7112f3b059e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2730_img_2150_3"  type="Envelope"  url="9b314f90fe0650da308c2f917c902224.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2730_img_2150_4"  type="Letter"  url="866784e4fa1df3c17cfd6f329a97a2a2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2730_img_2150_1"/>
             N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 3. Bridging Train. I.E.F.D.   14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> August. 1916.   My dear Mother   I was very glad indeed to get your last letter with<lb/> the news that Daddy was getting on so well &amp; I hope<lb/> he will continue to do so. I hope the rest of the family<lb/> <seg type="del">are</seg>  is  also doing well. There is nothing much doing<lb/> here and I am still very well. The wind has kept<lb/> up well and it is getting cooler &amp; cooler each day<lb/> The nights are quite cold and I am just going<lb/> to start a blanket. A new sailing boat has arrived<lb/> for the post in which we go out for sails in the<lb/> evening. But as the wind is always straight down<lb/> stream we can only go straight ac<seg type="del">c</seg>ross <lb/> home; we usually go straight ac<seg type="del">c</seg>ross. No Iron<lb/> has come for the bridge so we are no nearer<lb/> getting away. We are at present enlarging the camp<lb/> — a very slow &amp; rotten job. There are going to be<lb/> a lot of changes here. The gunners are being<lb/> changed. The cavalry hopes to go on leave — they<lb/> have been out here well over a year and the<lb/> ambulance has changed so we will soon<lb/> be the oldest inhabitants if the Field Park<lb/> does not hurry up the bridge stuff. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2730_img_2150_2"/>
             Please tell the cat that we have made a new<lb/> arrangement by which Fox orders tins etc.&amp;<lb/> ask her to send rather smaller parcels than<lb/> I asked her to last letter — Books <seg type="del">chiefly</seg><lb/> Blackwoods, <sic>Magizine</sic> &amp; anything she can think of<lb/> &amp; also about six tins of sorts a month.   I am afraid she will not know whether she is<lb/> standing on her head or her heels but still<lb/> things have changed in the last week &amp; we<lb/> will soon be messing on our own.  I hope <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> is very well &amp; a very good<lb/> Boy and I hope Baby got my letter<lb/>  with love to you all from your<lb/> loving son   <hi rend="underline">Jim</hi> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2730_img_2150_3"/>
             Mrs. A.C. Tate<lb/> <seg type="del">Slieve - na <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg>  2 Glenlucin <lb/> <seg type="del">Whiteabbey</seg>  Ballycastle <lb/> Co Antrim<lb/> IRELAND 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2730_img_2150_4"/>
            <!-- Back of envelope -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>