<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4003">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne to Alice Katherine Wynne, 9 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Wyndham Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to his mother after he received several letters of hers. He write about conditions at war, and his recent illness. Writes of a mission in an advance party for his Battery. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin </repository>
                  <collection>TCD MS 10247/1/808</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4003</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1182">Charles Wyndham Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-02-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_1"  type="Letter"  url="eb80ffdd03d9c7300abb403df217f86e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_2"  type="Letter"  url="16899d58a7c215a68adde9ad0ccb8521.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_3"  type="Letter"  url="841c66d4182e0e840acd8331d8c48eec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_4"  type="Letter"  url="c7048591f7b359776ce41e46e4b2f8ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_5"  type="Letter"  url="301dd503489e01a48f7c1282ddfdfb49.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_6"  type="Letter"  url="99cf46e1992dd9e7d020ea084f40efda.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_7"  type="Letter"  url="9d44120a2280229b491a691429e2fa45.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4003_img_339_8"  type="Letter"  url="ad91d096758d4f762098be2e8c5640bd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_1"/>
             9.x.16   Dear Mother,   I have had another stroke of rotten <lb/>luck, and am cursing hard, however that <lb/>doesn't do much good so I try to make <lb/>the best of civilisation while it lasts.   What joy when the battery brought along a <lb/>grand budget of letters. I almost stuck <lb/> them in my pocket to prolong the anticipation.   I got yours of 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, &amp; 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> with <lb/>Win's enclosure and Em's of the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> very <lb/>many thanks to all . You hardly know <lb/>the joy of letters, Mother, its simply grand.   Well I must say the way they've treated us <lb/>here has disgusted me and thoroughly <lb/>enraged the Captain! I suppose we'll soon <lb/>get accustomed to their ways. As you <lb/> know I went forward with the advance <lb/> party —my duties being presumably to get <lb/>ready the battery pos<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. find out all there was <lb/> to know and generally make things smooth <lb/>for the battery to come in. I think <seg type="del">we</seg> <lb/>my last letter brought me up to where we <lb/>got to the battery pos<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. — we got there on <lb/>Sunday and when I got there I found  all <lb/>the officers of a battery section just by our pos<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> <lb/> were going out for the afternoon and I had
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_2"/>
             to take charge — never having seen or heard <lb/>of the battery before or knowing the country <lb/>at all! In the afternoon orders came through <lb/>to open fire on a certain tramway but <lb/>just as we started the mist came down <lb/>so that the fall of the rounds couldn't be <lb/>observed - wasn't it rotten luck - we <lb/> only fired five. Sunday and Monday <lb/>we were working hard on our pos<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. and <lb/> really got it quite nice. On Sunday afternoon <lb/>the other battery — with whom by the way <lb/>I was missing got orders to move that <lb/> night — awful commotion — and of course, <lb/> heavy rain — between twelve &amp; 1 o'cl I was <lb/>called out of bed and had to shove something <lb/>over my pyjamas while I went down &amp; <lb/> took over some ammunition which owing <lb/>to some muddle they couldn't take!   Next morning we got orders to go and <lb/>cover the tracks of another battery that had <lb/>moved out that night — it was raining <lb/>steadily, and a beastly job —but we made <lb/> a regular work of art of it.   Next day we again started on our own <lb/>posn. where in the afternoon I got information <lb/> that the battery was really going to another <lb/>pos<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. altogether right the other side of the <lb/> ridge!! We had to wait that night to load
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_3"/>
            up the shells I had taken over from the <lb/>battery going out. — A heavy job &amp; there were <lb/>45. I went up with my kit on the <lb/> lorry, leaving the men behind. In the <lb/>morning I heard that my party were to <lb/>be handed over to the R.E. for fatigues <lb/>I had to go down with an R.E. officer to <lb/>blow up one of the shells in which the fuse <lb/> had stuck, &amp; was ordered to get the men <lb/>up at the group headquarters by 1.0 o'cl. <lb/>It shows how safe R.E. shells really are tO <lb/>handle when I tell you that we absolutely <lb/> blew the shell to bits  (with a slab of gun cotton)  without exploding it <lb/>certainly explosions must be a very interesting <lb/>study. Well when we had finished off <lb/>the shell we started to walk back — I had a <lb/>telephone &amp; waterproof etc. — on the way a <lb/>wasp got caught behind my glasses and the <lb/>telephone went about twenty yards in one direction and <lb/>the mac in another and my cap in another and with a roar <lb/>I landed in a most undignified pos<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. in the mud <lb/>—fortunately the wasp only got me in the <lb/>eyelid which wasn't very bad — <lb/> anyway, when we got up I found that <lb/>that evening we had to go back again to <lb/>new billets quite near the old place. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_4"/>
             I reported to the R.E. officer and we <lb/>went down — he showed me the men's <lb/>billets <seg type="del">an</seg>— quite nice dugouts and <lb/>then we went through what seemed <lb/>miles of muddy trench to the O.P. <lb/>(observation post) on which they were <lb/>to work. I should be a fine place when <lb/> finished concrete and a big drainage <lb/>shaft underneath - but <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>he said it <lb/> would take three weeks.   That night I brought <sic>they</sic>men down per <lb/>lorry and settled them in and myself went <lb/>back to headquarters to join the battery. <lb/>I had seen the Captain and three other <lb/>officers there that day at lunch. <lb/>Anyway that shows<seg type="del">ho/del>how they treat you: <lb/>here's the advance party scavenges three <lb/> battery posns. none of them for the battery <lb/> and in the end the R.E. pinch <seg type="del">the</seg>all 13 best <lb/>men for fatigues —The Captain was <lb/>thoroughly disgusted when <seg type="del">and</seg>he heard - one <lb/>consolation is that I rather think the O.P. <lb/>in question is to be for our battery — that <lb/> is if we're still here when it's finished <lb/> though I don't expect we'll be here long   but it's a wonder if that's their way, they don't leave a rear guard to <lb/>lead the battery to its position while the advance party brings <lb/> up the rear.  <lb/>Next day Friday I met the Captain and
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_5"/>
            some others of the battery and went to <lb/>the new posn. <seg type="del">and</seg>The position is splendid <lb/>and we are actually billeted a house which <lb/> is actually in fairly decent repair!! the <lb/>village there is a pretty good wreck but <lb/> nothing like <sic>they</sic>other where I was, as <lb/>there are plenty of walls and even a good <lb/>many roofs! There is a topping workshop <lb/>in the billets with an engine and all sorts <lb/>of things if only I have any time and we stop <lb/>here I ought to get some fun out of it.   We returned to hqrs for lunch and then <lb/>motored to another place where a very nice <lb/> A.S.C. major gave us tea, then we went <lb/>back to the battery — that night we got two <lb/>of the guns in but chiefly owing to the A.S.C. <lb/>who would get the lorries stuck in the ditch <lb/>we were at it till about three a.m. —next <lb/>morning I had to be up at 7.0 to get out some <lb/>telephone lines and then the Captain came along. <lb/>I hadn't had any supper the night before and <lb/> I hadn't time for breakfast, but I managed to <lb/>pinch a couple of dog biscuits to eat in the <lb/>motor — you see I haven't had many <lb/>minutes to spare since I came over. It's <lb/> a heavenly change after Lough Swilly.
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_6"/>
             We motored up to headquarters and then <lb/>went for a long tramp through trenches, <lb/>fortunately clean - to have a look at O.P.'s <lb/>and the sector we have to operate over <lb/>we were on a ridge from which there <lb/> is a splendid view. — We came back <lb/> for lunch — of which I partook Greedily — <lb/> and then started out to chase the kegs of the <lb/>timbers which had been removed during <lb/>the inspection of the guns and the timbers sent <lb/>back locked — we were sent from place <lb/>to place till I should think we had covered <lb/>thirty miles. I think I know a large part of <lb/> this country well already, and one has <lb/>to keep one's eyes open when one has to find the <lb/>way by night after<seg type="del">have</seg>going - say once by day. <lb/>When we returned I found the Corporal I <lb/> had started putting up the telephone hadn't finished <lb/> it and I started on that ; I was able to get <lb/>a couple of topping fresh eggs and some tea and bread and when I had communication <lb/>established on the telephone I turned in as I was <lb/>dead sleepy and was on duty that night in the <lb/>battery. They got the guns in very promptly that <lb/> night and after a little over an hour at <lb/>about ten I was called up. I had to keep <lb/>walking pretty well all the night as the
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_7"/>
            minute I sat down I found myself <lb/>dropping off to sleep. In the morning <lb/>about 9.0 the Capt came round and <lb/>we started talking about various things <lb/>then a very queer thing happened — I got a <lb/> slight giddiness and walked away to <lb/>stretch myself a bit, and the next thing <lb/>I found myself on a stretcher — I thought <lb/> I was somewhere in England — it was a <lb/>good time before I began to piece things <lb/> together and remembered what had happened. <lb/> <seg type="del">All</seg> I don't know how long I was unconscious <lb/>or what happened — but in short <lb/>they let me into the clutches of the R.A.M.C. <lb/> and I was too sleepy and tired &amp; stupid to <lb/> protest. Isn't it sickening — and another <lb/>officer was just coming across to relieve me <lb/>and in five minutes I should have been at <lb/>breakfast and been alright. Th brought me <lb/>along in a Red + van and now I'm in <lb/> hospital — isn't it abominable — I was grand <lb/>this morning but they won't let me back to <lb/> the battery - I don't know why the Capt. <lb/>ever let me into their clutches — it's disgusting <lb/>rotten luck — You can't imagine how sick <lb/> I am — it's so silly &amp; meaningless — they'll
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_4003_img_339_8"/>
            probably keep me here for days now — I thought <lb/>I was pretty well through with Lough Swilly <lb/> ladies — I can't think what happened to <lb/> me — I think I must have fallen asleep where <lb/> I stood and when they saw me fall they <lb/>immediately got the wind up — it does make <lb/>me angry. Anyway things are very <lb/>comfortable here, so I suppose I'll have to <lb/>make the best of it — maybe they'll let me <lb/>back tomorrow. But they really are hopeless.   Well this is a rather lengthy <lb/>epistle — I hope you don't mind — we <lb/> have jolly good grub here and are <lb/>very comfortable if bored. I don't <lb/>know exactly where we are as I was <lb/>asleep all the time <seg type="del">we</seg>I was moving <lb/>yesterday. Anyway I'm right as rain <lb/>and should surely be back tomorrow. <lb/>I am of course dressed — there is a concert tonight.   Goodbye <lb/>Your very lv.   Charles W.Wynne 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>