<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5450">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kuno Meyer to Roger Casement, 15 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kuno Meyer</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from Kuna Meyer (1858-1919) to Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). Meyer was a German philologist and scholar who had founded the School of Irish Learning to promote the Irish language and was a close friend of Casement. The letter was written to Casement while he was in Germany. Casement spent eighteen months in Germany, arriving first as an envoy of Irish-American leaders, attempting to encourage Germany to support Irish separatist aspirations by providing arms. He succeeded in securing limited German support but his attempt to form a brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps to fight against Britain was largely unsuccessful. Believing the German support was insufficient, Casement travelled to Ireland to prevent the planned rebellion but was arrested after in Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. He was hanged in London in August 1916.
Meyer, whose pro-German stance was unpopular in the US (from where he writes), refers to American public interest in World War I and is critical of both the British secret service and the English people, whose he describes as &#39;vicious cowards&#39;. He finishes by informing Casement of his marriage to a women of Scots-Irish descent and his plans to continue lecturing after an accident.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List A15; Ms. 10,073/10iii</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5450</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1158">Kuno Meyer</persName>
              <date>1916-01-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0883">Arrowhead Hot Springs Hotel, California, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0160">Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5450_img_481_1"  type="Letter"  url="d3ecdec5154b9bb02e6de886b9c40696.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5450_img_481_2"  type="Letter"  url="2b105be27d27386ac15df3104b4d098d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5450_img_481_3"  type="Letter"  url="577504732a305f333b112daa31ad892b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5450_img_481_1"/>
             R. 19.1.16 <lb/>This is Irish of <lb/>"My <hi rend="underline">sweet friend"</hi>   Arrowhead Hot Springs Hotel <lb/>H. M., NICKERSON, MANAGER <lb/>ARROWHEAD SPRINGS, CALIFORNIA   15/1.16  <hi rend="underline"><seg type="foreign">Mo chara dhílis,</</seg>hi>  Our correspondence has <lb/>become very irregular, but I believe that all our <lb/>letters have got through. Meanwhile I hear of you <lb/>both from Germany through my brother &amp; Schiemann &amp; <lb/>on this side from several of <seg type="unclear">yr</seg> correspondents. <lb/>Your various articles in the Cont. Times &amp; c. have<lb/> <lb/>been widely reprinted here &amp; have had much effect <lb/>on people who still use their own judgement. On <lb/>the whole however the interest in the war has <lb/>greatly decreased here. I also notice that the vehement <lb/>partisanship of a year ago has abated much. The <lb/>belief that England is losing her game is spreading <lb/>in ever wider circles. I have had some interesting <lb/>correspondence with Roosevelt, who writes that the <lb/>thought of the loss of so many of his former <lb/>German friends is a genuine grief to him.   The British secret service is as <lb/>active &amp; futile as ever. You cannot imagine what <lb/>silly things they do &amp; make the American govt do. <lb/>Some time ago they came to the conclusion that <lb/>Germany was looking for a submarine base some- <lb/>where on the coast of Maine. So they spread a <lb/>network of secret service men all over that part <lb/>of the country. Among others, my friend Kommer, <lb/>whose delightful <sic>exposal</sic> of the "Morning Posts" <lb/>daily despatches from Budapest you will have <lb/>read, was for 3 days under surveillance when
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5450_img_481_2"/>
            he stayed at a hotel in <seg type="unclear">Monhegan</seg> <lb/>Island. It makes a most amusing story which <lb/>he must write some day.   I often hear from Ireland, but you will be <lb/>as well posted as I, or better. I still correspond <lb/>with many old English friends, who all give the <lb/>most <sic>woful</sic> accounts of conditions there. The <lb/>ignorance about the resources of Germany and the <lb/>conditions prevailing there is as great as ever, and <lb/>the silliest lies are still believed. But I know <lb/>their minds &amp; temper too well to be astonished <lb/>at anything. Looking back on my English life I can <lb/>hardly recall <sic>mor</sic> than a dozen really intelligent <lb/>&amp; well informed men, whose character was above <lb/>reproach. Moral cowardice in public &amp; private <lb/>life was always the curse of England, &amp; you know <lb/>how vicious cowards can be. Lying has become an <lb/>art with them &amp; he who can best handle <seg type="unclear">cant</seg> is <lb/>always sure of a following. It was so in Munich, <lb/>city life, &amp; you know better than I that it was <lb/>so in politics. Add to this, as friend Yeats <lb/>that the conversation of an Englishman is <lb/>one continuous swagger, and you have all the <lb/>elements of their present doings. Monroe's <lb/>report on the evacuation of Gallipoli with "one <lb/>man wounded" was a delightful example the other <lb/>day. To me the whole bitter fight between Germany <lb/>&amp; England is rather ethical than physical, and <lb/>that from the outset never made me doubt for <lb/>one moment what the issue would be. Your
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5450_img_481_3"/>
            <lb/>characterisation of <seg type="unclear">Grey</seg> interested me <lb/>greatly. I have known dozens of men like him.  <!-- There's a pencil marking that seems to mark out part of the paragraph below from 'circles' to end of paragraph. -->  My own activities here came to a temporary <lb/>standstill through my accident. But now that I <lb/>have recovered I shall resume them. I dare say you <lb/>heard of my marriage. My wife is of Scots-Irish <lb/>origin &amp; was a good pro-German even before I <lb/>made her acquaintance. The only thing I have <lb/>done lately is writing for the press. I hope to <lb/>continue my lectures among Anglo-American <lb/>circles whom I can easily meet on their own <lb/>ground through my superior knowledge of <lb/>England &amp; the English language. As for the Irish, <lb/>they need no conversion, as you know. It was <lb/>amusing to see how the Aberdeens were given <lb/>the cold shoulder <hi rend="underline">here wherever they went, and</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Lady Gregory has not fared much better.</hi>   I have had some delightful visits from <lb/>old English friends, Sir Walter Raleigh and <lb/>Prof. W.. H. Young, one of the foremost mathe- <lb/>maticians of England, among the number.   Write again. My best address is always <lb/>c/o L. Guenzel, 332, So. Michigan Ave. Chicago.  <seg type="foreign">Mise do chara</seg>   Kuno Meyer 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>