<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1648">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 15 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin (1866-1955) in Dublin. Marie was a born in Dublin and trained as a nurse at the out break of World War I. Two of Marie&#39;s brothers joined the British Army at this time, one of whom was killed in action. Marie served as a nurse in Malta, Leeds and France, and later set up the Medical Missionaries of Mary.
Marie states that she has not received much mail lately and that is has been a long time since she has hear from her mother. She discusses her first night on the night shift, stating that it will be difficult. She tells of a meeting she had with a private Martin, a soldier who picked up her brother Charlie&#39;s (1895-1915) disc the day before he was killed in action, going on to describe her brothers death. The letter discusses her brother Tommie (1891-?) who is also in the war. Marie tells her mother not to be surprised if they are home in 3 weeks, going on later to account 3 Sisters being sent home for taking a patient out for a drive. She also discusses family members including her aunt Katleen (1874-?) who sent her a lamp.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF134</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1648</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1916-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1648_img_1109_1"  type="Letter"  url="5eb48cd32aca075f3b08c11c3e51ef38.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1648_img_1109_2"  type="Letter"  url="942ed2db0c17258066f9d6f1f25ba587.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1648_img_1109_3"  type="Letter"  url="c508e80574f8da05ceb8aca25ff03404.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1648_img_1109_4"  type="Letter"  url="00053c4af7ea2104ad4437a2d77f010d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1648_img_1109_5"  type="Letter"  url="faafafdc01952f453dafaa0dd26ee140.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1648_img_1109_6"  type="Letter"  url="60be6d8f6078a47327452324a2b69266.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1648_img_1109_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">B1F/1134</seg>   15-3-16    My very dearest Mother <lb/>It is just ages since we have<lb/>had a mail. I have not heard from any<lb/>of you for 3 weeks of course I know it<lb/>is not your fault. it is just the Mail<lb/>has been delayed, we are not looking <lb forward="" to="" the="" next="" very="" much="" it="" one="">forward to the <seg type="unclear">pack</seg> one very much it<lb/>ought to be a very large one— Many<lb/>thanks for cable. I went off that day<lb/>to see Pte Martin but missed him as<lb/>he was not on pass &amp; as I was not<lb/>able to go on Saturday I went on<lb/>Sunday &amp; had a long chat with him<lb/>he seems a very nice man &amp; has<lb/>promised to write to you himself —<lb/>I shall tell you exactly what he told<lb/>me. I hope you were able to make<lb/>something of   — He started off<lb/>by telling me how he picked up Charlie's<lb/>Disc on Dec 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>&amp; as he was not able<lb/>to just near Charlie himself that day as<lb/>they were advancing he handed it to<lb/>Lt. Mahoney. Pte Martin is in A. Company <lb/> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1648_img_1109_2"/>
             &amp; was on the left of C, Charlie's Company.<lb/>he saw Charlie who was in great form<lb/>on the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, later on in the day he saw<lb/>him hit as all the men kept shouting<lb/>keep down Captain Martin or you get hit<lb/>&amp; they saw him hit in the leg. Charlie<lb/>immediately sat down under cover but<lb/>could not get away as the ground was<lb/>impossible for him to walk with wound.<lb/>Very shortly &amp; through glasses, they saw the<lb/>Bulgarians surround where Charlie was<lb/>lying &amp; capture the whole trench with<lb/>most of C Company in it. Mahony<lb/>(of Cork) &amp; White were also <sic>capture</sic>. the<lb/>next thing they saw was was them being<lb/>marched <seg type="unclear">Lcyc</seg> Bulgarians, he said they<lb/>could not actually distinguish any one<lb/>but he is quite sure he has not been<lb/>killed. If Charlie has <sic>be</sic> <sic>capture</sic><lb/>without his disc, it accounts for the<lb/>long delay over his name.— I do hope<lb/>we shall hear something very soon.<lb/>I had a card from Tommy dated March<lb/>the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> from Alexandria, he did not seem 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1648_img_1109_3"/>
             to know what is going to happen to him or<lb/>where they are moving on to. They<lb/>say here that his division have been<lb/>removed from Salonika but like every<lb/>thing else it is only a rumour.  One thing I am going to tell you now<lb/>is not a rumour but very much the<lb/>truth. I am on night duty for the<lb/>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> time to-day in fact I am sitting<lb/>in the bunk now 15-30 writing this.<lb/>There are 64 patients but very glad to<lb/>say none are bad so it is very light.<lb/>I am sure the nights will be very long<lb/>with nothing to do. I went to bed<lb/>this afternoon but of course could not get<lb/>to sleep but I suppose after I have<lb/>been on for a couple of nights &amp;<lb/>begin to get tired I shall sleep like<lb/>an Elephant.  <lb/>Don't be a bit surprised if you see<lb/>us home in about 3 weeks time. this<lb/>place is going to close shortly. I<lb/>should not be a bit surprised if they<lb/>send most of us home. The first lot of 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1648_img_1109_4"/>
            V.A.D.s did go home sometime this week. <lb/>Have you heard anything about the <lb/> name Malta has got &amp; especially the <lb/> V.A.D. we hear it is something trouble. <lb/> I have been out here over 4 months &amp; I <lb/> do not think I have ever seen any <lb/> thing very rough but evidently <lb/>some have been making utter fools <lb/> of themselves &amp; we have to suffer <lb/>for it &amp; <seg type="unclear">be</seg> . Two poor unfortunate <lb/> sisters are being sent home because <lb/> they took a patient out for a drive <lb/> the other day. I only know I have had <lb/> the quietest &amp; most harmless life out <lb/> here sooner than give people the <lb/>slightest chance for gossip although I <lb/> have <sic>be</sic> asked many a time to go <lb/>out riding which I would have loved <lb/>with quite a nice man Captain Pickering <lb/> but always refused as it meant <lb/> breaking a rule &amp; was not worth <lb/>my while to do so. I think it would <lb/> nearly be impossible with such a <lb/>number of Sisters &amp; <seg type="unclear">Malta</seg> such a
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1648_img_1109_5"/>
             a <seg type="unclear">sinah</seg> not to find a few who<lb/>do not know how to behave themselves<lb/>but why we all should suffer nobody<lb/>knows.  I would have written a few days<lb/>ago only I was waiting for the<lb/>Mail &amp; have been rather upset as<lb/>Miss Paul has suddenly got very ill<lb/>so I turned out on the Balcony,<lb/>for a night, poor thing. I really do not<lb/>know what is rough with her. I hope<lb/>she is getting nothing serious.  <lb/>I do not think I will like night<lb/>duty much it is very lonely except<lb/>for an occassional visit from a<lb/>N.U. &amp; Sisters however I am very lucky<lb/>as sister <seg type="unclear">Trower</seg> is the night sister<lb/>superintendant.  <lb/>Have you had any late news of<lb/>Gerald &amp; did he ask in on<lb/>his way back, I have been expect-<lb/>ing a letter but of course just like<lb/>yours it is still on its way.<lb/>Tell A. Kathleen the next time 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1648_img_1109_6"/>
             you see her how useful her torch<lb/>is to me now on night duty &amp;<lb/>everyone admires it so.  I hope you are keeping well &amp; all<lb/>at home. I saw A Lily on Sunday<lb/>who is in the best of form<lb/>&amp; gave me an excellent lunch of<lb/>Roast Chicken. fried Pots &amp; peas certainly<lb/>they were done well at <seg type="unclear">Floriana</seg><lb/>any one that grumbles at the food<lb/>there ought to be shot. I heard today<lb/>that Floriana is going to be closed.<lb/>I wonder what will happen to A. Lily if<lb/>that is the case.  <lb/>I must go and do a round now so<lb/>good-night, we will be having our<lb/>dinner in half an hour.  <lb/>Very best of love and kisses to you &amp; all<lb/> Your most loving and grateful daughter   Marie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>