<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4360">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Clements to Edward Carson, 18 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Clements</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles Clements, 5th Earl of Leitrim (1879-1952) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Clements commanded the Ulster Volunteer Force in County Donegal, and arranged to run guns into the county in his yacht, SS Ganiamore, in 1913. During the First World War, Clements was commissioned a major in the 11th Service Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4360</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0875">Charles Clements</persName>
              <date>1916-07-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1749">21 Egerton Gardens, S.W., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1952</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4360_img_3716_1"  type="Letter"  url="be559bf836be71345b07950c08d7a5af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4360_img_3716_2"  type="Letter"  url="be47241bd5b628932da2245f2834e4a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4360_img_3716_3"  type="Letter"  url="9a3c8979fac3cb0db8b5822ae4c6877d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4360_img_3716_1"/>
             21 Egerton Gardens <lb/>S.W   July 18th. 16.   Dir Sir Edward   I wish to forward to you a resolution, <lb/>passed by the Donegal Unionists. You will observe that <lb/>they do not commit themselves to saying that there has <lb/>been a misconception, which if I may say so, is an unspoken <lb/>expression of their loyalty and confidence in you, this is <lb/>clearly set out in a letter to me.   It is my opinion, that, what published <lb/>evidence there was of misconception, was insufficient before <lb/>the <hi rend="underline">Prime Minister spoke in the House on the 10th</=hi>. inst. <lb/>In considering his statement then, together with the state- <lb/>ments of <hi rend="underline">Lord Selborne and Lord Lansdowne</hi> on the subject <lb/>of the intention and position of the Cabinet, it is clear to <lb/>me now, that the grounds on which Ulster approved of <sic>nego- <lb/>ciations</sic> being continued, have proved to be misconceived.   What is a Unionist member of the Three Counties
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4360_img_3716_2"/>
            to do under such circumstances? Had the Unionist Members <lb/>of the Cabinet agreed before the 12th June, that there must <lb/>be Home Rule during the War, owing to Imperial necessity, <lb/>his duty would have been, to obtain the best terms for <lb/>Ulster; but as it can be shown, that the publication of <lb/>the terms of Settlement, (by whom I don't know), before the <lb/>Cabinet had considered them, forced the hands of the Unionist <lb/>Leaders, into unwilling agreement, then his duty must be to <lb/>act and vote against such proposals. I do not think there <lb/>is anyone who will dislike such a course more than I shall.   Is it really too late to take a course, which will place the responsibility upon the Six Counties? <lb/>You told me that in the event of the <sic>negociations</sic> being <lb/>discontinued, you would not be sure of ever having the offer <lb/>of Six Counties made again. In spite of that, under the <lb/>present circumstances, I feel very strongly that the Six <seg type="del">Counti</seg> <lb/>Counties should have an opportunity of deciding, whether <lb/>they have acted in accordance with the Covenant and the <lb/>Pledge; as if they find they have not so acted, I believe
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4360_img_3716_3"/>
            they would prefer to take the risk, of the loss of the Six C <lb/>Counties after the War.   If after discussion with the Six <lb/>Counties only, you found the feeling to be, what I believe <lb/>it is, against continuing the negotiations- personally I <lb/>can only see, that great good would come from breaking them <lb/>off. - To Ulsters peace of mind.- To the Empire.- And to <lb/>yourself.   As regards the Nationalists, if you break off <lb/>negotiations for a plan, which they all hate, will the <lb/>disaffection be any greater than it is now? <lb/>But it does not matter in the least what they say, just so <lb/>long as your great work is finished in the same splendid way <lb/>it has always been carried on?   It remains with you to decide. <lb/>All I hope is that you will not decide against going to <lb/>Ulster, because it is too late.   Yours sincerely   Clements 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>