<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4260">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to family, 11 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his family. Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/96</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4260</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4260_img_3626_1"  type="Letter"  url="4b28d2eb77f4257085fd4aa5708ee0bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4260_img_3626_2"  type="Letter"  url="8186bef619dcc2a73cb1a2ffbdd1ae02.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4260_img_3626_3"  type="Letter"  url="5be78bec42eca5c6c650d38c9423dc1f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4260_img_3626_1"/>
             <seg type="del">Mater</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Mat</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Edmund</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Rex</seg>   <hi rend="underline">Please Return To Lil</hi>   Dec.11   My dear folks   I am beginning this letter during an easy 10 mins <lb/>but do not know when &amp; where I shall finish. I have had 3 <lb/>separate interruptions since I began!   I took a walk today long our river towpath. The river <lb/>is the size of the Thames at Oxford but deeper &amp; faster. All the <lb/>same the French use it for barges &amp; I overtook an enormous <lb/>one towed bt 6<seg type="del">7</seg> horses. The railway lines alongside so appar- <lb/>ently there is room for both in this country.   We are all settling down into our new quarters &amp; doing <lb/>enquiring works on a large scale quite oblivious of the fact <lb/>that we may be called up to the trenches at a moments' notice <lb/>However other troops will get the benefit, if we don't, &amp; if everyone <lb/>acted on these principles the country would be that more comfortable <lb/>&amp; certainly the trenches would in certain cases be better./p>  One is occasionally on a strenuous bout of duty, as when <lb/>any intraining is on, &amp; I expect to be up Sunday night at <lb/>the station, but I find that being without an occasional night's <lb/>rest does not hurt one if one is in the open air —a great <lb/>score for <seg type="unclear">Martin's</seg> open air faith —. At other times I may <lb/>find myself confined from 8.15 AM till 12 MN in the office &amp; <lb/>dictating fairly hard the whole time except meals, but again one <lb/>has begun to grow accustomed to long hours by now, &amp; if only one's
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4260_img_3626_2"/>
            work is good&amp; meets with <lb/>occasional appreciation.  one does not mind  This is not very often the case from the Gen— <lb/>eral, but it is not his way, &amp; in any case one does not work for <lb/>praise, though it would occasionally grease the wheels.   I must try to send you a picture postcard of our <seg type="foreign">chateau</seg> <lb/>a most imposing looking building, &amp; which is really old this <lb/>new modern portion being at least 200 years old. It is rather gloomy <lb/>inside except on a sunny day, and the arrangements were not meant <lb/>for beauty, i.e. 2 very fine staircases go up the towers where <lb/>they are quite lost from a picturesque point of view. I never <lb/>realised before that halls and staircases are really a beautiful part <lb/>of a house, or can be made so   Tomorrow I am to dine with General Remington of <lb/>the Indian Cavalry Corps, who as a fervent Ulster man wishes <lb/>to see me, and will I fear be disappointed!   If all the Home.Service Territorials are now brought into <lb/>the army it will certainly mean a big increase out here, <lb/>&amp; every one seems to be agreed that it is here that the <lb/decision will have to be made. I shall make no prophecies <lb/>as to date as tho' I know nothing officially, I am going to be very <lb/>careful indeed in what I write not because I would not trust you all but <lb/>to set an example which is badly needed. Would you believe it, I <lb/>actually heard a senior officer relating full details of our Naval Intell- <lb/>igence system in Germany giving details which would certainly inculpate <lb/>those concerned if passed to that Country. This had been told him by a
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4260_img_3626_3"/>
            Naval Intelligence Officer, <lb/>who is endangering the lives of our people certainly deserves to <lb/>be shot himself. It is the English way &amp; in certain places <lb/>the French are equally careless apparently. They are like a lot of old <lb/>women gossipers   Talking of gossip they say that Winston Churchill has applied to <lb/>be made a Brigadier General! I thought he would have the propriety to <lb/>remain out here for 2 months as he is without demanding promotion, <lb/>but there may be special reasons for his wishing to hurry before <lb/>his pals in high places are removed   Tomorrow (Sunday) I am doing a railway reconnaissance <lb/>so shall probably miss church unless there is an evening service. <lb/>Unluckily the padré who has 9 services and 7 sermons in the <lb/>day is usually so tired in the evening that he lacks <lb/>concentration at the 2 late services. Poor man he like everyone <lb/>else has war work to do.   No mail has arrived today &amp; I always feel dried up <lb/>without it.   My best love to all, and again my hearty thanks <lb/>to Martin for his hospitality to Lily &amp; his kindness to her <lb/>which she appreciated to the full, &amp; I a little less.   Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>