<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2637">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Molly  Duffin to Maria Duffin, 4 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Molly Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

This chatty letter from Molly to her mother Maria is mainly &#34;ward gossip&#34; and thanks for Christmas presents</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/A/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2637</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0149">Molly Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0827">1st Southern Gen. Hospital, Dudley Road, Birmingham, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2637_img_2063_1"  type="Letter"  url="42c9ea22333b202180bd87a02ae90e6a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2637_img_2063_2"  type="Letter"  url="56bde3b465eb3aaccc3df9d50a2cdfd5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2637_img_2063_3"  type="Letter"  url="0dddf74cb10c092a34a44ec12fb57917.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2637_img_2063_1"/>
             1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Southern Gen. Hospital.<lb/>Dudley Road   Jan. 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> /16     Dearest Mamma,   I tried to get into bed early to-night to<lb/>write some letters, but there is always a scuffle for<lb/>baths before settling in, and the Sisters on the next<lb/>corridor <hi rend="underline">will</hi> come and use our bathroom although they<lb/>have one of their own and they have no consciences about<lb/>keeping you waiting for hours! Of course there are<lb/>exceptions, but I think the whole race of Sisters are very<lb/>disagreeable, and almost more so when they are off—duty!  I am still in the same ward with my nice Sister<lb/>in charge, but the Nursing Sister is a horrid little<lb/>thing and I am hoping she will be moved out first;<lb/>she has never been in a military hospital before and<lb/>I am sure she doesn't understand how to deal with<lb/>these wounds that are nearly all septic and <seg type="del">with</seg> very<lb i="" am="" sure="" she="" doesn="">often with contaminated fractures underneath. She handles<lb/>them so roughly, the men all dread her coming near<lb/> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2637_img_2063_2"/>
             them and the other day when one of them was coming<lb/>out of chloroform he shouted out such rude things<lb/>about her, it was quite embarrassing. She is always<lb/>grumbling about how she is treated here, so I hope<lb/>she will soon return to wherever she came from!  We had another whist drive in my ward on New<lb/>Year's Day with a supper afterwards, when Sister<lb/>Williams was presented with a beautiful manicure set<lb/>from the patients and the VAD's with nice little books.<lb/>Mine is a little leather one of Moore's Melodies — Wasn't<lb/>it nice of them? Unfortunately in the middle of the<lb/>whist drive, one of the men's legs began to haemorrhage<lb/>and we had to rush off for the doctor etc. which<lb/>rather broke up the evening; however, he was able to<lb/>stop it alright. That is the only thing I am<lb/>afraid of, as of course a minute or two wasted may<lb/>just make all the difference and I never much like<lb/>being left alone on duty in a surgical ward.  Sister Hodgkinson departed <hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi> of an hour before her<lb/>time this afternoon as she said she wanted to catch a<lb/>train and left me in charge of the ward. The Matron<lb/>came round on an inspection, but fortunately came in<lb/>just before Sister left, as of curse it is quite against 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2637_img_2063_3"/>
             D2109/10/1/A  3  <lb/>the rules. I like the Mr. E. T Irwin book<lb/>you gave me very much. Did you read it, I wonder?<lb/>It is very original and rather the same style as<lb/>Come out to Play There don't seem to be many<lb/>new novels this year. I am going to the theatre<lb/>with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Chance, R White's sister, next week. I think<lb/>to see The Mikado as the D'Oyley Carte Company is<lb/>here. Please thank Helen for exchanging<lb/>the silk blouse which arrived this evening and fits<lb/>very well. It is nice to have a new one, as the<lb/>others were shabby, also the new gloves, which I am<lb/>so pleased to have. I nearly bought a new pair the<lb/>other day, but luckily put it off!  Ever your loving<lb/>Molly 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>