<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2805">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Edward Cahill SJ to Fr Thomas V Nolan SJ, 11 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Cahill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr Edward Cahill SJ (1868-1941) to Fr Thomas V Nolan SJ (1867-1941), 11 December 1915, in which Fr Cahill outlines the invitation that he gave the Irish Volunteers to drill at Mungret College. Cahill explains that he is trying to establish a cadet corps among the pupils of Mungret College (like Fr William Hackett&#39;s corps at Sacred Heart College, Crescent, Limerick). Cahill invited both the Irish Volunteers and National Volunteers to drill at Mungret and informs Fr Cahill that Fr Corboy SJ is misinforming him about the Irish Volunteers, as his cousin is the principal man in the National Volunteers.

Fr Edward Cahill SJ (1868–1941) was born at Callow, Ballingrane, Co. Limerick. He joined the Society of Jesus (10 November 1890) and was ordained priest in 1897. From then until 1923 he was at Mungret College, Limerick as master, prefect of studies, and rector, and as superior of the apostolic school attached to the secondary school. In 1936, Cahill sent Éamon de Valera, with whom he was very friendly, submissions outlining catholic principles on which he believed the new constitution
being drawn up by the head of government ought to be based. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/SC/MUNG/204</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2805</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0273">Edward Cahill</persName>
              <date>1916-12-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1738">Mungret College, Limerick</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1897">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2805_img_2222_1"  type="Letter"  url="70a6ccb0c8ba4f472d87b114f3fbfc73.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2805_img_2222_2"  type="Letter"  url="2fbafd2c286bceba280d9ff5ba91a6d7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2805_img_2222_3"  type="Letter"  url="3f4593f8c9783308aad75f4ccae01072.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2805_img_2222_4"  type="Letter"  url="1c75c90719843d40f6615299601a7ae6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2805_img_2222_1"/>
              <!-- embossed heading --> Mungret College<lb/>Limerick<lb/><lb/> Dec 11 1915      Very Rev and dear Fr Provincial <lb/>P C    Your letter dated December 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> reached me<lb/>only this afternoon when I was going to class. Its contents surprised me very much;<lb/>and I hasten to reply. The whole matter has been <seg type="del">most</seg> misrepresented to you; and<lb/>I fear rather grossly so. When you speak of the Sinn Fein Volunteers you mean I<lb/>presume the Irish Volunteers. Sinn Fein is a misnomer put on them by the Politicians<lb/>in Limerick at the least the name is most misleading. Their executive committee includes<lb/> besides at least one priest  some of the <seg type="del"> very </seg>  very  first citizens in position and ability such as U. O Callaghan (city<lb/>Tannery)   O Toole ( city Treasurer etc      The history of their <seg type="del">  </seg> invitation to Mungret is this: - I have been most anxious<lb/>for the past two years to get up some kind of a Cadet Corps amongst the<lb/>boys with a view to teach drill which several patents ask for. Last year<lb/>I <seg type="del">established</seg> paid an instructor £20 for 1/2 hour <seg type="del">1/2</seg>drill every day with the boys <seg type="del">  </seg><lb/>of the different divisions; but the whole thing proved a dismal failure. This year<lb/>several of community <seg type="del">  </seg> suggested to form a Cadet Corps which the boys would <!-- possibly could --><lb/>enter <hi rend="underline">voluntarily</hi> and <seg type="del">  </seg> manage themselves  under the supervision of a scholastic  <seg type="del">someth</seg> something like Fr Hackett<lb/>Corps in Limerick which seems to be a great success.  I had talked this over with <seg type="del">sev</seg> several and had resolved to do it; and  in order <seg type="del">  </seg><lb/>to encourage the boys to take an interest in it I told Fr Corboy (who was very keen on<lb/> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2805_img_2222_2"/>
            <!-- embossed heading --> Mungret College<lb/>Limerick<lb/>it that I had asked ) Hackett to bring out his corps here some Sunday. Fr Corboy<lb/>however objected (as Fr Hacketts boys were too <hi rend="underline">small</hi> to make any impression on our<lb/>lads) and suggested to ask out the <hi rend="superscript">Limerick</hi>Volunteers — his cousin Mr Corboy is the principal<lb/>man in the National Volunteers &amp; he offered to arrange the matter with him. I discussed the<lb/>matter with <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the other consultors and finally determined with <hi rend="underline">the approval of all</hi><lb/>(except Fr Corboy whom I did not consult any further on the matter as I found it too <seg type="del">difficult</seg><lb/>difficult to so so) to ask out <hi rend="underline">Each sections of the Volunteers</hi> to come here on the same<lb/>day and give a display to the boys &amp; the consultors ( vr F Byrne F. Casey and<lb/>F. Tomkin) were of opinion that we could not ask one section without <seg type="del">the</seg> asking<lb/>the other as otherwise our action would mark the identification of the college<lb/>with that party: but that <seg type="del">n</seg> no one <seg type="del">n</seg> could or de facto would object<lb/>to our asking both; <seg type="del">e</seg> —especially <seg type="del">th</seg> as in Limerick there is no real opposition<lb/>Both  have  marched in the same procession  more than once: salute each other  and seem likely to form the same body<lb/><seg type="del">in</seg>very soon.<lb/><seg type="del">In</seg>I  accordingly  interviewed the <seg type="del">lead</seg>leaders of both <seg type="del">  </seg>Volunteer Sections more<lb/>than two weeks ago as to the possibility of both coming <hi rend="underline">here together</hi>  next Sunday  <seg type="del">They both the Irish V</seg><lb/>They  both  promised to lay matter before their committees and let <seg type="del">m</seg>me know. <seg type="del">The   </seg> the<lb/>National Volunteers however <seg type="del">e</seg> implying that they would much prefer <seg type="del">to</seg> that<lb/>the Irish Volunteers would  come at  <seg type="del">have</seg> a different <seg type="del">  </seg> time. The next <hi rend="superscript">I</hi>I heard was a<lb/>letter from Mr Corboy last <seg type="del">Su</seg> Sunday morning that the Nat Volunteers<lb/>were coming that very day. They came <seg type="del">ab about</seg> after midday <seg type="del">  </seg> drilled <seg type="del">  </seg><lb/>in playground: and the boys enjoyed it. I told them publicly why I had<lb/>asked them. A <seg type="del">very full</seg> report of the proceedings were published a day or two<lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2805_img_2222_3"/>
            later in the <hi rend="underline">Freeman </hi> in  the <hi rend="underline">Limerick papers</hi> and evidently  political  capital was <seg type="del">being</seg> being  made<lb/> of it <hi rend="underline">to identify</hi> us with that party. Last Wednesday the <hi rend="underline">Irish Volun-<lb/> teers</hi> wrote enquiring is next Sunday <seg type="del">I</seg> would suit us for their visit. I<lb/> again talked the <seg type="del">m</seg>matter over with Fr Minister Fr Casey Fr Tomkin. I found<lb/> it useless to discuss such matters with Fr Corboy as he does not <seg type="del">understand</seg> yet<lb/> understand the house; and I find his <seg type="del">vie</seg> views <seg type="del">to</seg> very one sided and his accounts<lb/> of facts <hi rend="underline">very unreliable.</hi> They were <seg type="del">unam</seg> <hi rend="underline">unanimously</hi> of opinion<lb/> that it was <hi rend="underline">now</hi> quite essential to have the Irish Volunteers who are the<lb/> more <seg type="del">m</seg> numerous in Limerick of the two and have apparently the sympathy of<lb/> the <hi rend="underline">Bishop</hi> <hi rend="underline">the priests</hi> and <seg type="del">of</seg>  of  most except <seg type="del">the</seg> the Unionists &amp; <seg type="del">proff</seg>professional<lb/> politicians and are as a body the <seg type="del">best</seg> best men and best Catholics in Limerick.<lb/> I accordingly <seg type="del">wr</seg> wrote accepting <seg type="del">their</seg> their visit on Sunday. Since then I have<lb/>  written again and have  interviewed the leader arranging details <seg type="del">&amp; have written</seg> I <seg type="del">have al</seg> also spoke to  all  the<lb/> boys <seg type="del"> </seg>at <seg type="del"> </seg>my <seg type="del"> </seg> religious knowledge classes telling them of the  coming  visit of the Volunteers &amp;<lb/> of its object &amp;   that they may see good drill &amp; that <seg type="del">we</seg> our corps would  not  <seg type="del">be</seg><lb/> be affiliated with or identified with any party. F Corboy interviewed me<lb/> about the matter a few days ago saying that the boys were opposed <seg type="del">it</seg> to them<lb/> <seg type="del">    </seg> I made enquiries about that and found it to<lb/> be <hi rend="underline">quite without</hi> foundation. <seg type="del">They</seg> The boy, outside a &amp; very <seg type="del">few</seg> few know little<lb/> or nothing about politics and practically all the boys in the house are very Irish<lb/> in their sympathies and will  neither boys or parents  <seg type="del">to not no not</seg> I know <seg type="del">It I think</seg> for certain have any<lb/> opinion hostile to the Irish Volunteers. This is also the opinion of all the other<lb/> Consultors. I read your letter <seg type="del">today</seg> and <seg type="del">t</seg> talked the matter over with the<lb/> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2805_img_2222_4"/>
            the same three consultors <seg type="del">th</seg> separately this evening. <hi rend="underline">All Three</hi> were strongly of<lb/> opinion that your order was given under a <seg type="del">mis</seg> misapprehension and as a<lb/> <seg type="del"> </seg>result of false or misleading information and that <seg type="del">it    </seg> the<lb/> carrying  out  of it litterally would inevitably have the very effect which you<lb/> wish to avoid. &amp; <seg type="unclear">feel</seg> that it would not have been <seg type="del">givn</seg> given<lb/> if <seg type="del">you</seg> you knew the facts as we know them here. I myself am<lb/> of the same opinion. Besides it would be quite impossible <seg type="del">t</seg> now to<lb/> cancel arrangements without causing a <seg type="del">sent</seg> <hi rend="underline">sensation</hi> and a scandal<lb/>  both in college and outside  and giving  vey very  grave  offence to many of the best people in Limerick<lb/> and  such action  would be likely to have serious effects for the college, Hence<lb/> although I see the matter <seg type="del">my</seg>  may  be <seg type="del">ser</seg>serious for myself I have no alternative<lb/> but to let things go on. It is quite certain that <seg type="del">t</seg> as far as boys and<lb/> outsiders are concerned the whole <seg type="del">thing</seg>  visit  will be forgotten in a week <seg type="unclear">whereas<lb/> <seg type="del">a</seg> to <seg type="del">co</seg> cancel <seg type="del">the</seg> such an invitation now would <seg type="del">inflict    </seg> rouse feelings<lb/> that probably never <seg type="del">wo</seg> would be forgotten.<lb/> And now that I have laid the whole matter before you as fully as I can<lb/> in a <seg type="del"> </seg> hurried letter I think I have the right to ask that you investigate<lb/> the matter and learn if <seg type="del"> </seg>what I say is accurate and prevent if possible<lb/> such unfair and misleading information <seg type="del">be</seg>being sent in future.<lb/>  Asking a  you   prayers I remain<lb/>     and respectfully<lb/>  Ed Cahill SJ<lb/> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>