<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2823">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter written by Eileen Doris Meyer to family members during Easter Week 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eileen Doris Meyer</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Eileen Doris Meyer (1896 - 1976 ) was returning to Dublin from Derry when she was caught up the events of the Easter Rising with her family. Her letters function as a diary, detailing her time living in Rathmines avoiding the conflict. Meyer&#39;s account describes the excitement, confusion and weariness of living in a city in conflict.  
 

Meyer&#39;s brother, Alan Meyer (1899 - 1918), who is mentioned throughout the letter, became a 2nd Lieutenant with the Royal Garrison Artillery some time after the letter was written. Meyer was killed in action 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Private Collection </repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2823</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1468">Eileen Doris Meyer</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Emma Meyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1985">Gleaneen, Rostrevor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_1"  type="Letter"  url="820207551ae90daf77e338df3b9dc7b1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_2"  type="Letter"  url="5b11bd5eeb7cc69ffe42dd1435fe967b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_3"  type="Letter"  url="c34061b591628d2d67b76896c93abfd9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_4"  type="Letter"  url="fce2b3d94c887f357153b582000bb04b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_5"  type="Letter"  url="ce2f77bddc0cd6dc7c36768ce7c3aa69.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_6"  type="Letter"  url="455d344b2b6596333416a4a624517858.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_7"  type="Letter"  url="ae7946f41f06848d8f5567ed70998500.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_8"  type="Letter"  url="ffa6eed0642bda4b7ad8b81fca8482b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_9"  type="Letter"  url="6a89425361ee30546322e8c987f9ad25.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_10"  type="Letter"  url="7471088321d30288f0e6d99fb2a206a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_11"  type="Letter"  url="3d2d505468f98086d2a9134871944f6b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_12"  type="Letter"  url="c633ecea4f9f42a361642ee4adc5737d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_13"  type="Letter"  url="419cb5a72fc658e504a9db745e0efdc0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_14"  type="Letter"  url="a964ed6d3284084a477f2ecf1a77659e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_15"  type="Letter"  url="6f41d72ffd889c6db78227d07a79d0fe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_16"  type="Letter"  url="ddc45880f396317336e29b8a3d75d4a7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_17"  type="Letter"  url="ad69421248023555d26d471d6b95c950.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_18"  type="Letter"  url="50b9ed0fa9acb60fc61dc395920de85e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2823_img_2239_19"  type="Envelope"  url="45f8cc1c70fbc6256e07ab7f30e5bb34.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Monday</hi> Left Derry at 3.30 and arrived at Porta-<lb/> down at 5.30. There was no mail train it being<lb/> a bank holiday so we had to wait till 6.30 for<lb/> a train. While we  Miss Austin &amp; I  were having tea in the refresh-<lb/> ment room a chap called Pollock, a man<lb/> I had known in the Bank of Ireland came<lb/> to us &amp; said that there was some talk that<lb/> we couldn't get through to Dublin as a<lb/> bridge had been blown up at Donabate.<lb/> This sounded quite exciting &amp; I went to send<lb/> a telegram to inform them at home of the<lb/> fact, but was told that they couldn't get<lb/> through to Dublin at present; in the end<lb/> they took it &amp; said they might get it through<lb/> by about 10 in the evening. When the train<lb/> came in it was very crowded &amp; we all got<lb/> into a first class carriage. We were up to<lb/> time as far as Drogheda, and the Guard <lb/> went along the platform shouting 'first<lb/> stop Dublin' so we thought it must all<lb/> have been a mistake, but we stopped<lb/> next at Skerries for about half an <lb/> hour &amp; then went on stopping so long<lb/> &amp; so often that it was half ten by the<lb/> time we got to Amiens St. Then the ex-<lb/> citement began. Miss Austin had a lot<lb/> of luggage &amp; there wasn't a cab or <lb/> a car or a taxi in the station. Pollock went to<lb/> telephone for a taxi, telephone wasn't<lb/> working &amp; a porter kindly informed him<lb/> that no taxi man would risk his life <lb/> to come out. There were an awful lot<lb/> of soldiers about &amp; they told us that they<lb/> had come up from the Curragh &amp; were<lb/> guarding the station, that many other<lb/> stations &amp; the post office were in the <lb/> hands of Sinn Feiners. They said
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_2"/>
            there had been two engagements in the streets, that the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Lancers &amp; 10t<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> Dublins had been engaged in. All this was very thrilling if you could have stayed where you were but as we had to get <lb/> right through the city it was a bit too thrilling.<lb/> Anyway we put the luggage in the left luggage<lb/> office which was packed &amp; I heard a porter tell <lb/> a man that the waiting room was open but<lb/> was already full. Miss Austin thought we <lb/> ought to have an escort of soldiers but they<lb/> assured us we would be much worse off <lb/> with soldiers as they shot them but wouldn't <lb/> shoot us if we didn't annoy them! Well <lb/> we started off to walk as there were no<lb/> trams &amp; barring the fact that we had to <lb/> go by the Quays because Earl St was barr-<lb/> acaded at the top. Earl St itself was all<lb/> broken glass etc., the town was absolutely<lb/> quiet &amp; we arrived home without a single <lb/> solitary adventure - rather to our disapp-<lb/> ointment as we had been expecting so<lb/> much. But the family nearly fainted <lb/> with surprise when they saw us (they had<lb/> all gone to bed by the time I arrived)<lb/> Alan had gone down to Amiens St to wait<lb/> the 7 &amp; had to dodge bullets all the way <lb/> down &amp; when he got there was told there<lb/> was no mail, he waited till 9 &amp; then the<lb/> military came &amp; took possession &amp; turned<lb/> him out saying there would be no more<lb/> trains that night. He was away from 6 <lb/> till 10 &amp; mother says his hair is greyer<lb/> since &amp; Aunty says if hers hadn't been<lb/> white already it would be after that. They<lb/> were amazed that we had got home as<lb/> easily. We heard afterwards that a man
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_3"/>
            &amp;his wife &amp; child had gone through Stephens<lb/> green (the <seg type="foreign">sinn Feiners</seg>, had possession of it) half<lb/> an hour before us &amp;&amp; had all been shot, not <lb/> killed but they each of them had a bullet in<lb/> them. They started about 12 on Monday by<lb/> taking possession of the post office — the g.p.o.<lb/> the Castle, the City Hall, all railway stations<lb/> barring Amiens St. the magazine in the park<lb/> Stephens green &amp;&amp; Jacobs. also Hatch St<lb/> which they <sic>baracadeed</sic> at one end with <lb/> gilbeys barrels &amp;&amp; <sic>th</sic> other with motor cars<lb/> from the garage at the end. Some of <lb/> them got into Davy's the public house at <lb/> Portobello Bridge &amp; they shot every soldier<lb/> who crossed the Bridge. Only for Noel Scott<lb/> Alan would probably have been shot too.<lb/> Noel was home on leave on Sunday &amp; as he <lb/> was going out for a walk with him alan<lb/> changed into <seg type="unclear">muffle</seg> so when he was going<lb/> into hospital on Sunday evening he still <lb/> had it on. When he was coming back on<lb/> Monday morning first about 12 they were <lb/> shooting the soldiers from Davys, he <lb/> saw one shot &amp; only for Noel he would <lb/> have been in uniform himself. He <lb/> wanted to get into it then &amp; go &amp; report at <lb/> Portabello &amp; v volunteer for "active service"<lb/> but Father would not let him &amp; mother<lb/> locked up his uniform.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_4"/>
            4<lb/> <hi rend="underline">Thursday.</hi> This morning everyone rallied forth to <lb/> barriers wondering whether the military had<lb/> dished the S.F altogether or not. There was a <lb/> fearful crowd in Rathmines everyone was in <lb/> groups talking when alan &amp;&amp; I got as far as <lb/> Portobello Bridge we met Tom Lawlor who <lb/> <seg type="del">ass</seg> implored us not to go any further as when <lb/> he got as far as the green the bullets were<lb/> flying &amp; he had to run for his life (they had<lb/> got them out of Davys, Harcourt St. station &amp; <lb/> Hatch St, by this time) we said we'd go on<lb/> at any rate &amp;all the bullets so we went on. <lb/> The Rathmines <seg type="unclear">section</seg> of the Bank of Ireland<lb/> male &amp; female was grouped in Harcourt <lb/> St &amp; everyone else was standing about<lb/> talking. Joe Walker was on his door step<lb/> conversing with a large crowd &amp; warned<lb/> us not to go further than the Ivanhoe <lb/> Hotel. I met some of the men from the<lb/> office coming back. They said there were <lb/> shots in the green &amp; they were not going to <lb/> risk their skins when not risking it one as <lb/> a holiday we went as far as the corner of the <lb/> green where there was a large crowd standing <lb/> some people who were fond of work were<lb/> going on, of course the shots were really only <lb/> up in the air they were not trying to shoot<lb/> civilians, if you were shot it was an <lb/> accident unless you were a soldier, but <lb/> a good many accidents happened. The <lb/> people who did go on (it was no use going<lb/> down Camden St for they potted at you<lb/> there from Jacobs) &amp; arrive at the offices<lb/> &amp; banks were sent home again as there<lb/> was no business being done. I came
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_5"/>
            and took about an hour to get home,as you<lb/> met so many people &amp; had to stop and discuss<lb/> the situation with them all. Then I came out<lb/> again with Father, and anything like the<lb/> crowd in Rathmines standing around doing<lb/> nothing! We went on to Gainforts then, Lil<lb/> &amp; Nesa had gone down to Marabrough <lb/> the day before &amp; hadn't arrived home. Uncle<lb/> Willie had managed to get down town<lb/> in the morning, &amp; there wasn't even a counter<lb/> left whole in <seg type="unclear">Leivers</seg> much less any of <lb/> the stock &amp; even the books were gone.<lb/> Nearly all the shops in Sackville St. had<lb/> been looted the same way.   In the afternoon it poured &amp; no one went<lb/> out except Alan who went right down<lb/> town into the thick of it, just to see the <lb/> fun. In the evening it cleared up<lb/> &amp; Rathmines was quite gay, all the<lb/> shops were open &amp; the Picture Houses<lb/> &amp; everyone was about, you'd never<lb/> think there was war in the city.   <hi rend="underline">Wednesday</hi>. People started off for <lb/> business again &amp; the same thing happened.<lb/> Most of them turned back again &amp;<lb/> stood round Rathmines discussing <lb/> the situation. Martial law was<lb/> declared &amp; all the shops were shut, you<lb/> had to get in the side doors to buy <lb/> anything. Mother got tired standing<lb/> so long so Father &amp; I started off for<lb/> <seg type="unclear">Findlaters</seg> &amp; bought up all the tea &amp;<lb/> sugar etc we could get, &amp; carried them
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_6"/>
            <lb/>home, imagine Father carrying home parcels of <lb/>groceries! We went round to Gainforts <lb/> again in the afternoon. Lil &amp; Nesa had got <lb/> home that morning. They had got into King &amp; #x2014; <lb/> bridge the evening before, and of course <lb/>could get no conveyance, and as they could <lb/> not possibly walk to Ranelagh, they went <lb/>for the night to Herbert Smiths, where they <lb/> went up to their bedroom &amp; while trying to <lb/> light the gas a <sic>bullit</sic> came through <lb/>the window. Lil declares she couldn't <lb/>see for half an hour she got such a <lb/> shock. Things were very bad round there <lb/> that night &amp; it seems that they flicked <lb/>the light about so much the military <lb/>thought they were signalling to the <lb/> Sinn Feiners &amp; fired, anyway they had <lb/> a very narrow escape. The next morn #x2014; <lb/>ing they had to walk all the way home, <lb/> &amp; had the greatest difficulty to pass <lb/> some of the sentries. We had some <lb/>difficulty in getting back from Gain — <lb/> sfort ourselves as they were searching <lb/>Oakley Rd, fortunately there was a nice <lb/>Dublin Fusilier officer at the end of the <lb/> road &amp; he let us pass. You couldn't get <lb/>further up Rathmines Rd than Richmond <lb/> Hill either. The only house we could <lb/>visit with any certainty of getting back <lb/>was the Cronhelms - &amp; and Dorothy had <lb/> measles. It really is very thrilling to <lb/> go out &amp; not know whether you can <lb/>get back or not. Of course Mother &amp; <lb/>Aunty are in a fit every morning Alan goes <lb/> down town, as the <sic>bullits</sic> are flying there.
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_7"/>
            7  <hi rend="underline">Thursday</hi>. No one attempted to go into business <lb/> today but went chasing food instead. The <lb/> queues outside Findlaters &amp; Williams were <lb/> tremendous. Magees were Sinn Feiners &amp; <lb/> had all departed on Monday. Mother got <lb/> rabbits in M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cabes, they'd absolutely no fish, <lb/> &amp; got a steak &amp; also a joint for Sunday in <lb/> Keoghs, he charged mother 1/6 lb but own <lb/> customers 2/- , &amp; if he gave them any at all. We <lb/> were in despair about groceries till Annie <lb/> Starkie told us Cooks were open if you <lb/> knocked at the side door. I had to go back <lb/> to Rathmines so Mother went round by <lb/>Charleville Rd. with a 1/4 stone packet of <lb/> oat meal under each arm &amp; Cooks <lb/> little boy beside her with a basket full <lb/> of the rest of the things. There were <lb/>sentries all over Rathmines &amp; just at <lb/> the corner of Wynnfield Rd, where they were <lb/> particularly guarding the Post office &amp; <lb/> the telephone, if you passed with your <lb/> hands in your pockets you heard a <lb/> peremptory "take your hands out of <lb/> your pockets". He wasn't a very good <lb/> tempered sentry either &amp; was getting <lb/> annoyed at everyone's broad grin as <lb/> they displayed both hands.    There was a proclamation posted all <lb/> over the place this morning announcing <lb/> that everyone was to be in their houses <lb/> between the hours of 7.30 pm. &amp; 5.30. a.m. <lb/> Imagine that! and actually by twenty — <lb/> five to eight there wasn't a person up <lb/> or down the road. I'd never have thought <lb/> Dublin people would be so obedient to 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_8"/>
             8   a proclamation. I forgot to mention we <lb/> have had no gas since Monday so <sic>its</sic> pretty <lb/> miserable with candles, and today a <lb/> soldier went all along our side of the <lb/> road &amp; told us to pull down our blinds <lb/> in the back &amp; leave them down all day &amp; <lb/> at night to shut the shutters or at any <lb/> rate not to show any light. The <lb/> blinds down in the day time is so that <lb/> we won't see the prisoners being shot <lb/> in the barracks.     When we were at supper in the break— <lb/>fast room (of course there's firing near <lb/>&amp; far going on all the time) but all of <lb/> a sudden a <sic>bullit</sic> was fired down <lb/> the lane under the arch. I can tell <lb/> you we did jump, it sounded as if it <lb/> was right in the room. I don't wonder <lb/> Lil couldn't see for half an hour after <lb/> the <sic>bullit</sic> came into their room. Edith <lb/> got such a fright she wouldn't sleep <lb/> downstairs so she brought up her <lb/> mattress &amp; camped out on the landing. <lb/> After this when soldiers home on leave <lb/> or war book mentions the whiz of the <lb/> <sic>bullits</sic> flying past, the noise of the <lb/> machine gun or the dull <seg type="del">noise</seg> roar of the <lb/> artillery in the distance we can say <lb/> quite wisely "oh" yes, we know all about <lb/> it" We can tell at once quite off <sic>handidly</sic> <lb/> now whether a shot is rifle (Service or <seg type="foreign">Sinn</seg> <lb/> <seg type="foreign">Feinn</seg>) machine gun, artillery or guns from <lb/> a ship. In fact we have all become <lb/> quite war worn veterans. 
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_9"/>
             9   <hi rend="underline">Friday</hi>. <lb/>This morning there was much the same <lb/> fight for food but we had all we wanted <lb/> except bread, our breadman never came &amp; <lb/> you couldn't get bread for love or money <lb/> in Rathmines so mother had to turn <lb/> round &amp; bake soda Bread. We have <lb/> plenty of flour but not much coal, its <lb/> well its such lovely weather we don't <lb/> need fires. The firing was simply terrific <lb/> all last night the worst there's been <lb/> yet. Some English soldiers came in on <lb/> Wednesday afternoon with a lot of <lb/> machine guns &amp; artillery. Alan was <lb/> walking along with them &amp; one of them <lb/> asked him to "spell the name of what <lb/> we're going to fight." I'm not saying <lb/> anything about the fighting in town as <lb/> I'm sure you'll see it all in the papers <lb/> &amp; know more about it than we do ourselves <lb/>We've absolutely no outside <lb/> news as everyone says "the other war might <lb/> be over for all we know!" We really don't <lb/> know much about our own war either as <lb/> all we have to go by are eye witnesses <lb/> reports &amp; as they everyone differ it's very <lb/> hard to know what's what. The Irish <lb/> Times came out in town on Tues, Wed, &amp; <lb/>Thurs. but all it did was to comment on <lb/> our lack of news &amp; give the people good <lb/> advice about going home at 7.30 etc. It <lb/> also said it was very good to see such <lb/>absolute lack of panic everywhere, and <lb/>to see people walking about the streets 
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_10"/>
             10  <lb/>with bullets flying all round them as if nothing <lb/>was happening, but all the same it would <lb/>like to point out that the military were not <lb/>giving a public entertainment, &amp; people <lb/>would do a lot better to stay at home.   We're beginning to have spasms in <lb/>Rathmines now, when the soldiers get it <lb/>into their heads to clear Rathmines Rd. <lb/>(I suppose they think they see Sinn F's <lb/>in the crowd) &amp; they charge &amp; yell. You <lb/>should see the people flying up Leinster <lb/>Rd. its great fun, if they loiter round the <lb/>end of the road to see whats going on <lb/>in Rathmines, the soldiers line across <lb/>&amp; point their rifles at them &amp; then they <lb/>melt into thin air. Grosvenor Rd was <lb/>searched yesterday evening &amp; because <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Briscoe went to open the dining room <lb/>window from the bottom a soldier pointed <lb/>his rifle at her, I'm sure she had six <lb/>fits but history doesn't record.   There have been so many alarms &amp; <lb/>excursions &amp; Rathmines today &amp; the shoot - <lb/>ing sounds so very near ( the S.Fs are all <lb/ along the canal &amp; S.C.R. shooting at the <lb/>Barracks) that nobody likes to venture <lb/>far from home, and as its a glorious <lb/>day everyone's sitting on their front <lb/>steps. Never before have people been <lb/>so friendly with their neighbours, but <lb/>they're about the only people you can <lb/>visit with any safety now. Alan's  
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_11"/>
            <lb/>leave was up to-day so he insisted on going to <lb/>Portobello but he forgot to go until nearly seven. <lb/>The adjutant wasn't there so he was told to come <lb/>again in the morning. He saw two officers, one <lb/>told him to keep out of it if could, and <lb/>the other asked him between his intervals <lb/>of cursing the candle (imagine nothing but <lb/>candles in Portobello) why he hadn't come <lb/>sooner if he wanted to see some fun. He <lb/>thinks the first officer was English &amp; the <lb/>second Irish. They were all ducking &amp; <lb/>dodging about in the barracks to avoid <lb/>the bullets coming over the wall from <lb/>the canal. He had to get a pass from the officer then.  for being out after 7.30     I forgot to say that this morning Auntie <lb/>had one of her old attacks. Mother could <lb/>get nothing but corn beef for dinner yester - <lb/>day so it must have been that, but she <lb/>isn't very bad.   <hi rend="underline">Saturday</hi> <lb/>No bread to be had for love or <lb/>money, hundreds deep round every bakery <lb/>door. Sam &amp; Ethel were up &amp; they had no <lb/>bread either. In about an hour Sam <lb/>came back with loaves under each arm <lb/>if it had been bags of gold we couldn't <lb/>have been more delighted or astonished. <lb/>There had been an awful crowd round <lb/><seg type="unclear">Wiltons</seg> when the cart arrived &amp; you know <lb/>they keep the iron gate thing shut &amp; <lb/>serve the people over it, and the breadman <lb/>lifts in the trays of bread over the people's <lb/>heads to the girls in the shop. Sam was <lb/>near the front &amp; he said to the girls, if <lb/>you let me in I'll lift those trays for <lb/>you, so they let him in &amp; he was 
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_12"/>
             serving bread behind the counter for about <lb/>half an hour or until it was all finished. <lb/>of course he kept enough for himself &amp; us <lb/>we've enough now to do us over Sunday. <lb/>There was another spasm in Rathmines <lb/>today &amp; Mother if you please got stuck <lb/>between two sentries in Wynnfield Rd <lb/>&amp; neither would let her past, she was <lb/>running from one to the other till at <lb/>last one of them shouted to the other <lb/>"let her past for the time being".   Alan &amp; I started off for <seg type="unclear">Selskar Terr.</seg> &amp; <lb/>when we reached Rathmines found it <lb/>had been cleared, Alan insisted on <lb/>going on till we were stopped but you <lb/>feel horribly conspicuous &amp; a great <lb/>target for a bullet being the only <lb/>person in Rathmines, I was very glad <lb/>when we had safely turned into Castle — <lb/>wood Avenue. When we got to Ranelagh <lb/>we heard two women had been shot <lb/>just outside Johnson's five minutes <lb/>before. Lil &amp; Nesa came back <lb/>with me as they wanted some books, of <lb/>course by that time Rathmines was <lb/>if anything more crowded than ever, it <lb/>always is half an hour after it has <lb/>been cleared. We were standing on <lb/>our steps when we saw a crowd of <lb/>soldiers coming up the road &amp; more in <lb/>Rathmines going on to Portobello. <lb/>Just as the advance guard got as far <lb/>as our house they stopped for a rest
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_13"/>
             13   &amp; we went out to talk to them, they looked <lb/>awfully hot as they'd marched from <lb/>Kingstown, of course they were English <lb/>chaps &amp; had terrific English accents. <lb/>I went in &amp; got them all the oranges <lb/>there were in the house. They said they <lb/>thought this was a great country every <lb/>one had been giving them things all <lb/>the way from Kingstown till they <lb/>could hardly carry any more.   After they had gone we heard it was <lb/>all over, everyone was informing everyone <lb/>else that it was all over but we <lb/>hardly believed it as we still heard <lb/>shooting. As a matter of fact it was <lb/>all over in the city but they continued <lb/>firing in the suburbs for some time.   I forgot to say that we actually got <lb/>some English papers this morning. <lb/>There was a fearful rush for them &amp; you <lb/>had to pay 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> for 1/2 <hi rend="superscript">d</hi> papers. Some shop <lb/>in Ranelagh got hold of just about <lb/>six London "Times" &amp; charged 1/- each for <lb/>them &amp; got it too.   <hi rend="underline">Sunday</hi> Ethel has got measles, cer - <lb/>tainly things always come in a lump, <lb/>of course Baby is bound to get them, <lb/>as long as Sam doesn't it will be <lb/>all right.   We had church same as usual 
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_14"/>
            <lb/>this morning, &amp; had a lot of the green <lb/>people as of course they had no church. <lb/>Alan went down to the adelaide to see <lb/>if he could get some of his belongings <lb/>(I forgot to mention that they turned him <lb/>out on  last  Tuesday they were so full up) <lb/>He forgot to bring back any of his things <lb/>so he had one pair of pyjamas there &amp; <lb/>had sent to Southwold for his other <lb/>pair also socks etc &amp; expects that they <lb/> were in the G.P.O. so he'll not see <lb/> them again.   We had church at 6 in the evening <lb/>so as to be home by 7.30 but just <lb/>as Fr. Alley was beginning his sermon <lb/>just getting warmed up you know at <lb/>the beginning to fling his arms about, <lb/>the military sent a polite request that <lb/>everyone would go home so everyone <lb/>departed. The shooting near us has <lb/>never been so bad as this evening. <lb/>Father &amp; I were standing at the gate <lb/>talking to Mr. <seg type="unclear">Cordnen</seg> who was hold — <lb/>ing forth on the ridiculous nervousness <lb/>of his wife &amp; daughter jumping at every <lb/>shot as if it was meant for them, if <lb/>people would only have some common- <lb/>sense! etc! etc! etc! etc! when whiz bang <lb/>a bullet landed in the hawthorn tree <lb/>beside us &amp; you <hi rend="underline">should</hi>have seen Mr <lb/><seg type="unclear">Cordnen</seg> skip, he said good bye &amp; was <lb/>half way to the Square before we'd realised <lb/>he had gone.  
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_15"/>
              we have lots of flour but no coal scarcely.   15   <hi rend="underline">Monday</hi> No bread again. Alan &amp; I had to <lb/>walk over to Ballsbridge (Johnson &amp; Mooneys) <lb/>for some. and I can tell you its <hi rend="underline">some</hi> <lb/>walk there &amp; back without a rest &amp; a <lb/>couple of loaves to carry back &amp; a very <lb/>hot day. But the joke of it was everyone <lb/>thought they go early to avoid the <lb/>crush &amp; some started off at six in the <lb/>morning &amp; had to wait in a queue for <lb/>about an hour &amp; then only got two <lb/>loaves, we started at eleven, hadn't <lb/>to wait at all &amp; got four loaves. <lb/>But you should have seen the stream <lb/>of people you might almost say a <lb/>procession that we met coming <lb/>back when we were going, everyone <lb/>had loaves tucked under their arm <lb/>of course without any paper, some <lb/>people bought pillow cases in which <lb/>they put the bread &amp; then slung it <lb/>over their shoulders. Of course for <lb/>people to carry bread without paper <lb/>is nothing now. You've seen people <lb/>this week, who before wouldn't have <lb/>carried a nice neat parcel out of <lb/>town, with a cabbage tucked under <lb/>one arm minus paper of course, &amp; <lb/>a slice of meat in the other hand <lb/>and equally minus paper. Really &amp; <lb/>truly that wasn't a bit an unusual <lb/>sight. Nothing much happened 
            <pb n="16" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_16"/>
             16   today &amp; no shots were heard at all until <lb/>about 6.30 when they were fast &amp; furious <lb/>till dark. They say there are snipers on <lb/>the roofs of these houses.   You've no idea how funny it is about <lb/>twenty five to eight to see people scurrying <lb/>home for all their worth, who before <lb/>wouldn't have thought of scurrying at <lb/>twenty five to twelve. Then by about <lb/>half eight or as soon as it has got dark <lb/>you feel as if you were up in the middle <lb/>of the night nobody passes up or down <lb/>&amp; the only thing you hear are rifle shots <lb/>&amp; if you look out all the houses are dark <lb/>as the people in the opposite side of the <lb/>road all migrate to the back of the <lb/>house. If it only hadn't been for <lb/>this half seven dodge we'd have had <lb/>a grand time &amp; so exciting but the <lb/>evenings are fearfully boring &amp; quite <lb/>counteract the excitement of the day — <lb/>time. Everyone goes to bed at nine <lb/>so there aught to be plenty <seg type="del"></seg> of beauty <lb/>in Dublin now everyone has had <lb/>so much beauty sleep. 
            <pb n="17" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_17"/>
             17   <hi rend="underline">Tuesday</hi> about 8 I woke up &amp; heard soldiers <lb/>marching up the street I got up to watch them <lb/>&amp; they went into a house beside the lane leading <lb/>to the Barracks. I thought if they were going <lb/>to search all the houses I'd better get dressed, <lb/>so I did. They got two prisoners in that <lb/>house (No 31) &amp; marched them off, the officer <lb/>had a lot of papers under his arm. They <lb/>searched a lot of the houses round here this <lb/>morning, there was so much sniping last <lb/>night but they didn't search us. I was <lb/>quite disappointed it would have been fun.   The English soldiers here are quite en — <lb/>joying themselves, someone heard a sentry <lb/>in Rathmines remark that in London <lb/>you never <seg type="del">got</seg> were  <seg type="del">never</seg> given a cigarette but <lb/>since he came over here he got so <lb/>many he wished he could smoke ten <lb/>at once &amp; as for drinks he could get <lb/>full up at that public house as often <lb/>as he wanted, he thought it was a grand <lb/>country but he didn't see what they <lb/>wanted to be fighting for. But the English <lb/>are always so dense that it's utterly im - <lb/>possible to make them understand <lb/>the why or the wherefore of the rebellion or <lb/>who or what the Sinn Feiners are. <lb/>Another soldier said to Alan that he <lb/>couldn't understand this country, one <lb/>day they gave you cigarettes &amp; drinks <lb/>&amp;anything you wanted &amp; next day <lb/> they shot you.   You can go into town now if you
            <pb n="18" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_18"/>
             18   like to see the sights' but there are sentries at <lb/> all the bridges &amp; even have to have a pass <lb/> except men (note the men!) under 14 &amp; <lb/> over 65 so Father just says 65 &amp; walks past <lb/> the sentries. The whole thing has done <lb/> Father heaps of good, I suppose with bullets <lb/> flying round &amp; artillery thundering you forget <lb/> you have bronchitis &amp; a heart. Anyway he <lb/> walked down to Sackville St (no trams yet) <lb/> walked round there &amp; walked back again, <lb/> and it hardly took anything out of him.   I went down town this afternoon <lb/> with Lil &amp; Nesa &amp; its simply awful, Sackville <lb/> St. is a wreck, but I suppose you see <lb/> pictures of it in the paper. The office is the <lb/> first house standing in Eden Quay but <lb/> its quite all right has only one bullet <lb/> through it.   However the rebellions over now so <lb/>so will this letter be. We'll have quite <lb/> an exciting time now finding out about <lb/> everyone 'cause of course we know nothing <lb/> about anyone. Mollie Haggard went to <lb/> Kerry for Easter &amp; I don't know if she got <lb/> back, we don't know whether Hilda &amp; Babs got <lb/> back from Newcastle &amp; I don't know if <lb/> anything happened Robert Northridge or <lb/> Grovie Morgan as of course they were fight — <lb/> ing, in fact all the world except Rathmines <lb/> might be dead for all we know. 
            <pb n="19" facs="L1916_2823_img_2239_19"/>
              Mrs Meyer, <lb/>Gleaneen <lb/>Rostrevor <lb/>Co. <hi rend="underline">Down</hi>   <!-- Stamped Aberdeen 6.45 pm 9th Aug 1929 -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>