<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3799">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Thompson to the President & Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 30 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Henry Thompson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Henry Thompson (1861-1929) to the President &amp; Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) regarding Thompson&#39;s choice to volunteer as a temporary assistant in lunatic asylums in England and Scotland. Thompson volunteers himself in the hope that his offer will relieve the number of asylum vacancies due to the war or free men of military age to sign up.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T74</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3799</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0877">William Henry Thompson</persName>
              <date>1916-05-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2038">Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1929</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3799_img_3182_1"  type="Letter"  url="6a46b1448d38d00734a14aaee5153479.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3799_img_3182_2"  type="Letter"  url="12e9770e127360256187e85e9fce59c2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3799_img_3182_1"/>
             School of Physiology <lb/>Trinity College.   30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916   Dear Sirs,   Having learned that great <lb/>difficulty is experienced in finding <lb/>temporary assistants in Lunatic Asylums <lb/>in England &amp; Scotland, to take the place <lb/>of the younger medical men who are <lb/>called up for military service, I volun- <lb/>teered, if granted leave of absence, to do <lb/>such work, if by doing so it would relieve <lb/>a man to join the R.A.M.C. A plan was <lb/>drawn up and submitted to the Board <lb/>of Trinity College by which, conjointly with <lb/>D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lamb, who is also over military age. <lb/>The work of the Department here as well <lb/>as that of an assistancy at an Asylum <lb/>in England or Scotland, could be carried out. <lb/>(Briefly the suggestion was that D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lamb <lb/>could take charge of the work of the first <lb/>or <sic>Michaelmas</sic> Term and also of the Trinity <lb/>or Summer Term here. That of the Hilary <lb/>Term, or January to March (inclusive) to be done <lb/>by myself. During this term D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Lamb would <lb/>relieve me in the Asylum work. By this <lb/>arrangement the heavy term including <lb/>the March examinations, would be in my <lb/>own hands. A condition was also  to be  made <lb/>that I should be given permission to return <lb/>for the June and October examinations. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3799_img_3182_2"/>
             the Board has agreed to this arrangement <lb/>and has granted me leave of absence <lb/>for the duration of the war.)    Within a month, no less than four <lb/>requests reached me to take up Asylum <lb/>Assistance work and I have accepted <lb/>and been appointed to act as Temporary <lb/>Assistant Physician and Pathologist <lb/>At the Crichton Royal Institution Dum <lb/>fries, to take up work on 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> July next.    I therefore beg to ask the President and <lb/>Fellows of teh Royal College of Physicians <lb/>to satisfy the permission granted to me <lb/>by the Board of Trinity College. I should <lb/>add that I hold a Diploma in Mental Diseases <lb/>and in my younger days did Asylum <lb/>work. I may also state that the authorities <lb/>at Dumfries are agreeable to give me <lb/>permission to carry out the duties of the <lb/>examinerships I hold, other than those <lb/>in the School of Physic.   I am <lb/>Your obed. servt   W.H. Thompson   To The President &amp; Fellows of the <lb/>Royal College of Physicians in <lb/>Ireland. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>