<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2834">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John R. Moorhead to Sir Robert Chalmers, 29 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John R. Moorhead</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter written by John R. Moorhead(1859-1936), crown solicitor for Belfast. The letter is addressed to the under-secretary for Ireland, Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned, along with chief secretary Augustine Birrell, in the aftermath of the Easter Rising in 1916. 

The letter concerns compensation payment for travel expenses incurred by a witness to a case heard at the previous Spring Assizes. The accused had been a captain in the army and a representative of Cox &amp; Co, the military bankers, was required to attend as a witness for three days. Believing the expenses claim to be excessive, Moorhead writes seeking the direction of the under secretary as to the correct course of action. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary’s Office Registered papers, CSO-RP-1916-5615-11091-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2834</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1437">John R. Moorhead</persName>
              <date>1916-06-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1495">30 Rosemary Street, Belfast, Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir. Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1936</item>
               <item n="tag">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2834_img_2249_1"  type="Letter"  url="cc98354edf4d0ba405601a704a5e37dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2834_img_2249_1"/>
             Counties of Antrim &amp; Belfast Crown Solicitors Office. <lb/>30 Rosemary Street, <lb/>Belfast   29th. June 1916   MOORHEAD &amp; WOOD. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Solicitors</hi> <lb/>JOHN R.MOORHEAD, <lb/><hi rend="underline">Crown Solicitor.</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Telephone N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>605</hi>  <HEAD>THE UNDER SECRETARY/</HEAD>  SIR/  <hi rend="underline">The King v Wheeler</hi>  This case was heard at the last spring Assizes when the <lb/>accused pleaded guilty to passing a worthless cheque on Mr. Fred <lb/>W. Henry of this City. The accused was a Captain in the Army <lb/>at the time and by direction of Senior Crown Counsel I caused a <lb/>Crown Office Writ of Summons to issue for the attendance of a <lb/>representative from Messrs Cox &amp; Co. the Military Bankers, to pro— <lb/>duce a certified copy of accused's Banking A/c. Mr. Henry H. <lb/>Billetter. Bank Clerk, attended and he was in attendance at the <lb/>Assizes 3 days and 2 nights. At the Assizes he furnished me with <lb/>an A/c. amounting at £3. 13. 0., for travelling expenses, but I <lb/>did not certify anything for him. I informed him that he should <lb/><sic>sent</sic> me a detailed statement of his expenses with a view to <lb/>getting your directions as to payment.   He has now furnished <lb/>this statement which I think is excessive, and I should be glad to <lb/>have your directions as to what amount, if any, should be allowed him. <lb/> He <sic>travelled</sic> to the Head Office, Charing Cross,London.   I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedt. servant   John R <hi rend="underline">Moorhead</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>