<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5559">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 3 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 

Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.

James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.

This letter is written after after James&#39;s visit to May&#39;s home, May is trying to tie down their plans for Easter, whether will she visit him or whether he will visit her. Alternatively they may go together to the races. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5559</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-03-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5559_img_655_1"  type="Letter"  url="f3f2394fb5c29bdde98cddd9c35f956c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5559_img_655_2"  type="Letter"  url="4422d88ef65956f90f495d055d15e7fa.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5559_img_655_1"/>
             Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar   3<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rd</hi></hi> March, 1916    My dearest James,   I got your letters today &amp; yesterday<lb/>alright I can tell you I was very glad to get them to<lb/>brighten me up I have been in low spirits since Sat  <lb/>I got <sic>neuralgy</sic> a continual <sic>num</sic> pain over my right-<lb/>eye with a very frequent sting from a broken tooth I<lb/>slept each night between the stings you know the way<lb/>they take you I have a <seg type="unclear">gum boil</seg> now &amp; I hope as it gets<lb/>bigger this nagging pain will go I have not got any<lb/>trouble with my teeth this six months but all the time I lived<lb/>in dread of them the only thing is they are no serious<lb/>harm.   Like yourself I am looking forward to your visit<lb/>at Easter but I don’t know what to say to my visit<lb/>to the city I’m not going to go now between this &amp; Easter<lb/>&amp; by the time you are gone back after Easter it will be<lb/>only a month from that until the 1st of June &amp; a<lb/>month is very short passing in preparation for something<lb/>very pleasant to think of &amp; I expect to be very busy I was<lb/>consulting my Mother yesterday she said it would be a very 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5559_img_655_2"/>
             foolish trip so near our marriage &amp; having people talking<lb/>(perhaps say you were trying to back out of it) Don’t think<lb/>me awful now to be changing my mind but I did not<lb/>realize how near we were to our marriage at Easter<lb/>neither did you. I think — if you saw me nearer than a<lb/>month of our own marriage there would be no novelty at all in<lb/>getting married, but if nothing turns up to prevent me<lb/>for I will go to the races I hope you won’t be disgusted<lb/>with this changing but it is hard to decide on anything<lb/>till it is almost at hand  You are very good to be thinking of giving me something<lb/>to show how you love me but indeed I have proof enough<lb/>you should not be giving yourself the trouble in case you<lb/>do tho’ I would like a pair of gloves any sort I’m not<lb/>very particular. About being nice to you at Easter of course<lb/>I will a <hi rend="underline">nice</hi> but sure I’m always nice &amp; too nice<lb/>for my peace of mind.  I have <seg type="del">not</seg> not a word of news. Yes Tom Macken<lb/>Marlinstown will probably <hi rend="underline">win</hi> with Francis <hi rend="underline">O’Neill</hi>.<lb/>Your Mother may know the gent I think.  I will conclude with fondest &amp; warmest love<lb/>to my dearest James  <lb/> from your own old girl<lb/>May<lb/>Eire M.   The break in the weather was a great<lb/>disappointment to the farmers in general    </p
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>