<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3342">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from H A Thomas to Nicholas Lamb, 3 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>H A Thomas</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from H A Thomas to Nicholas Lamb asking for an allocation of emergency funds for the restoration of 
a collapsed gas tank. 
Nicholas Lamb (b. 1861) was the Town Clerk of Longford and served on the Longford Urban District Council. The Longford Urban District Council was the towns local authority and was renamed the Longford Town Council in 2002. H. A. Thomas worked in the Longford Gas Works.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Longford County Archives Service</repository>
                  <collection>LUDC-1-3-1916-3-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3342</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0158">H A Thomas</persName>
              <date>1916-03-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0799">Gas Works, Longford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Nicholas Lamb</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0823">Longford Urban District Council, Longford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3342_img_2754_1"  type="Letter"  url="b96649180bfd0759666f3f32ab97d8dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3342_img_2754_1"/>
             Gas Works<lb/>Longford   3   <hi rend="superscript" style="font-style:" italic=""> rd </hi>  :3:16   N Lamb<lb/>Town Hall   Dear Sir  — In order to meet an emergency<lb/>which has arisen in connection with my Gas Holder<lb/>tank I am in urgent need of about 80,000 gallons<lb/>of water. My tank has fallen about 4tr below<lb/>water level and in order to enable me to tide over<lb/>the difficulty and bring me on to the time when it<lb/>would better suit me to let down the holder I would<lb/>deem it a great favor if your Council could see<lb/>its way to letting me have the above mentioned<lb/>quantity of water from their supply at as<lb/>reasonable a rate as possible.<lb/>I might add that providing the leak does<lb/>increase and I have no reason to think that it should<lb/>I estimate that my own water pump from the river<lb/>ought enable me keep pace with the leakage -<lb/>I would also feel greatly obliged if your Council<lb/>could see its way towards giving my application<lb/>its very earliest attention as it is a matter of<lb/>urgency   Yours <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg><lb/>H A Thomas<lb/>Manager  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>