<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3543">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Deborah Webb to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 14 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Deborah Webb</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Deborah Webb to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington about her recent letter from Sheehy-Skeffington and to discuss suffragette matters. 

Deborah Webb was a member of the Irish Women&#39;s Franchise League and a nationalist. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946)  suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; ms 33,604/17-20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3543</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0173">Deborah Webb</persName>
              <date>1916-03-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0443">9 Garville Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3543_img_2947_1"  type="Letter"  url="f1e1e8bb2806d47c43650d59d174272f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3543_img_2947_2"  type="Letter"  url="2371981f57d5f11b8fe3eadd0a0c6ae5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3543_img_2947_3"  type="Letter"  url="ba13b28d851b3e3fd8b6571e1851adc6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3543_img_2947_4"  type="Letter"  url="b19c9347583deb68fff862e189e6a017.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3543_img_2947_1"/>
             9 Garville Road   March 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   1916   Dear Hanna   It was good to hear from <lb/>you. I am sending your letter <lb/>on to J.C. She had told me <lb/>about your sister &amp; her <lb/>beautiful children &amp; I know <lb/>she will be sorry for what <lb/>you tell. Your troubles &amp; joys <lb/>are always more or less <lb/>troubles &amp; joys to me too. <lb/>I can sympathize with you <lb/>about losing your Mary &amp; <lb/>do hope she will have a <lb/>worthy succession.    That was such a serious
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3543_img_2947_2"/>
            operation that although <lb/>successful it will take a <lb/>long time to recover from.   I can now creep into the <lb/>sitting room but do not <lb/>yet with my own letters. <lb/>You will like to know that <lb/>a very kind &amp; congenial <lb/>friend is homing with me <lb/>which very much adds to <lb/>my happiness.   The doctors say that I shall <lb/>gradually gain ground. Be <lb/>sure that when able I shall <lb/>much enjoy seeing you <lb/>but that will not be for <lb/>a while &amp; we understand <lb/>each other. I look forward
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3543_img_2947_3"/>
            <lb/>to the I.C. tomorrow   Yours affectionately   D.W.  <lb/>for C.W.H.  My good doctor J.C. Purser <lb/>says he is not only a <lb/>suffragist but a suffragette, as <lb/>he sympathizes on that point <lb/>a on many others. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3543_img_2947_4"/>
            <P>marriage dangerous trade.    Economic problem at root.  <lb/>Women face a <seg type="unclear">proposition</seg> to economic <lb/>independence.  <lb/>Risks <seg type="unclear">excluded</seg>. <lb/>Marriage marked C. <seg type="unclear">Herrulto</seg> <lb/>Prostitution <lb/>Intensified by war. <lb/>Polygamy &amp; <seg type="unclear">independence</seg>.    How to be achieved  1) Woman continues her work <lb/>No longer <seg type="unclear">trained</seg> to marry.   2) If she specializes let her <lb/>be paid   <hi rend="underline">Objections</hi>: <lb/>Sentiment - Mar. Wom's Prop. <lb/>Difficulty of <seg type="unclear">diviser</seg>   Mrs. <seg type="unclear">Gilma</seg> <lb/>To her a German said. <lb/><seg type="unclear">unreputable</seg>. <lb/>unoccupied.   Giving a present <lb/>office. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>