<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3866">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 1 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Fletcher-Vane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane (1861-1934) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) regarding the political fallout in London in the aftermath of Francis Sheehy Skeffington&#39;s death. According to Vane there is a sense of panic among the British administration as they attempt to control the extent of the damage done to their reputation in the wake of Bowen-Colthurt&#39;s actions. Before signing off Vane discusses the possibility of going to America as he is quite well known there and would not mind a change. 

Major Sir Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane was a British officer in command of Portobello Barracks. When he learned about the activities of Captain J.C.Bowen-Colthurst during Easter Week he reported the matter to his superiors but, sensing a cover-up, he went to London and reported it directly to Lord Kitchener and Maurice Bonham Carter, Private Secretary to the Prime Minister. Although Bowen-Colthurst was court-martialled and found guilty, Vane was &#39;retired&#39; from the military for his actions. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,608/1-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3866</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0659">Francis Fletcher-Vane</persName>
              <date>1916-08-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1846">National Liberal Club, Whitehall Place, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3866_img_3246_1"  type="Letter"  url="eecbc9985e472e437610df58d6e10bf3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3866_img_3246_2"  type="Letter"  url="f1e343ac813e266668f7ddd8dfe5513b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3866_img_3246_3"  type="Letter"  url="79d11469d10306f88ea97567d0e16e68.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3866_img_3246_1"/>
              National Liberal Club <lb/>Whitehall Palace S. W.    1st August 1916    My Dear Mrs Skeffington,  <lb/>We had the first skirmish of <lb/>my particular side of your War to day <lb/>as you will have seen by your papers. <lb/>I have never seen any people so tied <lb/>up as thet were — so entirely futile. <lb/>I had a most amusing interview with <lb/>the Military Secretary yesterday — <lb/>and he was so nervous that he <lb/>accused me of stealing his letters and then apologised. It is almost <lb/>pitiable how completely they put themselves <lb/>in the wrong and how wonderfully <lb/>surprised they are where the World <lb/>realises their wrong doing. They become
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3866_img_3246_2"/>
            <lb/>pained and insulted by such a realisation. <lb/>Well in a Country in Shed it is necessary <lb/>to day fudges <seg type="del">co</seg> altogether exorbitant <lb/> salaries to insure (or try to) impartial <lb/> judgments no one need be surprised. <lb/>A <seg type="unclear">Driude fudge</seg> of wheat gets £700 a<seg type="unclear">avast</seg> <lb/> our £5000!!   I asked many members where our inquiry <lb/>would come off and all said very <lb/>soon. within a couple of weeks. <lb/>I am glad to think the </gap? <lb/>Freeman was right. It was horribly <lb/>badly edited. But the meaning is <lb/>clear enough. Would you send me <lb/>any commentaries upon it. I have <lb/>the most rotten paper cutting agencies <lb/>please —   Alas I am to blame. I find in all these <lb/>exciting times the Pax Britannica <lb/>did not go off. Tomorrow it will
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3866_img_3246_3"/>
            <lb/>be dispatched.   I expect tomorrow in Dublin there will <lb/>be a one ask in the Nationalist Papers <lb/>over the matter in the House Today. <lb/>Please tell me what they say. <lb/>I have half a mind to go to America <lb/>for a town, for Ireland — I have <lb/>often been asked to go there to lecture <lb/>and, if they do not want me to fight, <lb/>it would be a pleasant change.   In a way I am rather well known there <lb/>as a the founder of the World Scout <lb/>Movement and through my ancestor <lb/>for Harry who is a past hero.   My best love to Owen — and <lb/>my homage to yourself — and Lady O's <lb/>love.    Yours sincerely <lb/> Francis Patrick Vane <lb/> of Hutton.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>