<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3642">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fellow & Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to the Precentor, St. Patrick's Cathedral, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) to the precentor of St. Patrick&#39;s Cathedral in Dublin requesting twelve tickets for the Kitchener Memorial Service taking place in the cathedral the following Tuesday. 

In 1916 Reverend Hugh Jackson Lawlor (1860-1938) was the acting precentor of St. Patrick&#39;s Cathedral Dublin. Lawlor held the position from 1902 until 1924. Aside from his role as a clergyman Lawlor was well regarded for his learning and an active member of the Royal Irish Academy. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-173</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3642</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0845">Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Jackson Lawlor</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0809">St. Patrick's Cathedral, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3642_img_3039_1"  type="Letter"  url="d743697ac3f1b4599467fc75f66b4e9d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3642_img_3039_2"  type="Letter"  url="e098eb407a059431d1c8953b40d19443.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3642_img_3039_1"/>
             9th JUNE 16.   The Revd.The Precentor, <lb/>St.Patrick's Cathedral, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   The President and Fellows of the Royal College of <lb/>Physicians of Ireland desire to attend the Kitchener <lb/>Memorial Service in your Cathedral on Tuesday next the 13th <lb/>instant and I shall feel greatly obliged if you will kindly <lb/>let me have 12 admission tickets and reserve a pew for the <lb/>College representatives.   I remain, <lb/>Yours faithfully,  Fellow &amp; Registrar.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3642_img_3039_2"/>
             Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. <lb/>Kildare Street, <lb/>Dublin.   3rd JUNE 1916.   A. Millere 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>