<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5916">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Gerald O'Driscoll to his father Denis, 24 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Gerald O&#39;Driscoll</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Gerald O&#39;Driscoll (d. 1946) to his father. O&#39;Driscoll writes of his shock at the &#39;rebellion in Dublin,&#39; noting that &#39;our fellow country-men at the front felt it all the more keenly&#39;. His reaction is typical of many Irish soldiers in the British army; he laments the destruction of Sackville Street and refers to one of the rebels as a &#39;half-demented, crazy, misguided fool.&#39; O&#39;Driscoll writes about family matters and an annual boxing tournament.O&#39;Driscoll served in the British Navy aboard the H.M.S.Temeraire. The Temeraire was a Bellerophon class battleship, it saw service at the Battle of Jutland (May-June 1916), the largest naval engagement of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Denis McGrath</repository>
                  <collection>Private collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5916</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0890">Gerald O&#39;Driscoll</persName>
              <date>1916-05-24</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0229">Denis O&#39;Driscoll</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5916_img_429_1"  type="Letter"  url="7fcf9749625d690e9f52b319b43ca735.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5916_img_429_2"  type="Letter"  url="7d3307fc9f788a6381b46591c67b06af.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5916_img_429_1"/>
              *Must be 1916    H.M.S. Temeraire,  Grand Fleet,  c/o G.P.O. London    24/5/6*   My dear Father,   In a letter from Maggie I was very <lb/> pleased to learn of Fineen's arrival home and also <lb/> to be assured of his general health &amp; fitness. I have <lb/> not replied to Maggie yet as for some time past I <lb/> have been too busy altogether. I was of course <lb/>shocked by the Dublin rebellion and indeed not a <lb/> little anxious for the safety of those near and dear to <lb/> me. I was worried and restless. The possibility of <lb/> Maggie &amp; Barbara being in the danger zone, and this <lb/> coupled with the temporary stoppage of mails &amp; <lb/> communication of every description increased my <lb/> solicitude. But I will not waste time in dogmatising <lb/> on such madness; we and our fellow countrymen at <lb/> the front felt it all the more keenly. It would <lb/> seem as if the temple of glory built by our brave <lb/> Irish regiments, had been pulled down by their <lb/> own kindred. In a paper that Maggie sent me <lb/> I notice the name  &amp; address  of Dot's brother as one of <lb/> the rebels deported. I wonder what his ow <lb/>n brother Jack will say when he hears the news at <lb/> the front. That half-demented, crazy, misguided  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5916_img_429_2"/>
              fool Willie Halpin is also one of them. Patriotism! <lb/> My God! and he knows as much about Irish <lb/> History as a Fiji cannibal. The outcome of it <lb/>was death and sorrow, and the destruction of the <lb/> finest and statliest street in Europe; — a street <lb/> that every Dublin <hi rend="underline">man</hi>, <hi rend="underline">must</hi> have been justly proud.   Things up here are very much the same, as far as I <lb/> am at liberty to disclose. In order to relieve the tenor of <lb/> a <choice> rather <seg type="del">ratl</seg></choice> multifarious routine, the annual boxing tournament took <lb/> place recently; a sort of inter—ship for the championship <lb/> of the squadron. Our friend Bob Hanley <seg type="del">took</seg> won the <lb/> lightweight championship of our own particular squadron after <lb/> four fights. It appeared to me to be an easy thing for <lb/> him. He is a skilful and clean fighter, a hard hitter, <lb/> and I have little doubt that he will win the championship <lb/> of the Grand Fleet <hi rend="underline">should that competition</hi> ever come off.   I had a field service post card this morning from <lb/> Fineen in which I am assured that he is quite well.   I was not aware that he <seg type="del">was</seg> is a full corporal but <lb/> was certainly not surprised. I passed a preliminary exam <lb/> recently with a fairly decent margin of marks. I am the more <lb/> elated because I was totally unprepared for such. It in no way <lb/> embraced  the  category of my present study. The latter is varied <lb/> and complicated but I have every confidence for the ultimate <lb/> result. That is all. It is late and I am for duty. <seg type="foreign">Adieu </seg>for <lb/> the present with love to Mother and Babs.  <seg type="closer"> Your affectionate Son,  <hi rend="underline">Gerald</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>