<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4016">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to The Town Clerk, Dundalk Urban District Council, 30 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>The Town Clerk, Dundalk Urban Town Council</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter acknowledging the receipt of the letter containing a copy of the resolution adopted by the Dundalk Urban District Council at their meeting on the 22nd of August.

The letter includes the copy of the resolution:   The members of the Dundalk Urban District Council unanimously agreed that the Irish members of Parliament should demand that the Irish prisoners connected with the revolution held in Frangoch should be given the option of a public trial in Ireland.  Signed M Comerford (Dundalk Town Clerk)

Matthew Comerford (ca. 1857-1934) was Town Clerk of Dundalk</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5623-15168-1 NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5623-15168-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4016</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0771">The Town Clerk, Dundalk Urban Town Council</persName>
              <date>1916-08-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Chief Secretary&#39;s Office, Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0595">Dundalk Urban District Council, Town Hall, Dundalk, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4016_img_3400_1"  type="Letter"  url="9e5cbced17670a32ae498c312db689f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4016_img_3400_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="3d1ee06ac6b37bee6a3b8c4af41410dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4016_img_3400_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>  30th August, 1916.   Dear Sir,   I am desired by the Chief Secretary to acknowledge <lb/>the receipt of your letter of the 28th instant <lb/>transmitting copy of a resolution adopted by the <lb/>Dundalk Urban District Council at their meeting held <lb/>on the 22nd instant.   Yours faithfully,    (Sd.) A.P.M.    The Town Clerk, <lb/>Dundalk Urban District Council, <lb/>Town Hall, <lb/>DUNDALK.   Office <lb/>A.P.M. <lb/>30/8   WMC <lb/>31/8/16 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4016_img_3400_2"/>
             DUNDALK URBAN DISTRICT COUNCIL. <lb/>Town Clerk's Office, <lb/>TOWN HALL, DUNDALK,   28th day of August 1916   Sir,   At a Meeting of the Dundalk Urban District Council <lb/>held on the 22<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="superscript">nd</hi></hi>inst, the following resolution was unanimously <lb/>adopted, and a copy of same directed to <seg type="unclear">be</seg> forwarded to you, —   Proposed by Mr Peter Hughes,   Seconded by Mr M. <seg type="unclear">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coy, and resolved: —   That we the members of the Dundalk Urban District Council <lb/>enter an emphatic protest against the continued detention of <lb/>local men arrested in connection with the Insurrection believing <lb/>as we do that these men are entirely innocent.   That we request the Irish Members of Parliament <lb/>to demand that the Prisoners at present detained at Frongoch be <lb/>given the option of public trial by by a Civil Court in Ireland."   Yours truly   W. Comerford <hi rend="underline">Town Clerk.</hi>   The Right Hon. H.E. Duke KC. <lb/>Chief Secretary for Ireland <lb/>The Castle <lb/><hi rend="underline">Dublin.</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>