<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2506">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jane Cobden Unwin to Jane Coffey, 19 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jane Cobden Unwin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Jane Cobden Unwin to her friend Jane Coffey (née l&#39;Estrange) (1857-1921). She first asks for the address of Mrs Bury so she can arrange a visit and then mentions that she would write more but fears that her letters would not reach their destination as martial law was in place in the aftermath of the Easter Rising. She refers to an old shoe maker was arrested after the Rising even though he would not have &#39;the strength to shoulder a rifle&#39; and also mentions others who were arrested but who had nothing to do with the Rising. She claims Dublin Castle have made a mess of things and hopes for the time when Ireland would have its own parliament.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Coffey &amp; Chenevix Trench Papers, Collection List No 153; Ms. 46302/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2506</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1127">Jane Cobden Unwin</persName>
              <date>1916-06-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0550">3 Adelphi Terrace, Strand, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0106">Jane Coffey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2506_img_194_1"  type="Letter"  url="971b26961a1ddadf1b9f9173c33ebd8e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2506_img_194_2"  type="Letter"  url="e3f77279d81cbeee5b5ed818bae68581.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2506_img_194_3"  type="Letter"  url="ce87789059c465b5bfa3826e8d5dcbca.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2506_img_194_1"/>
             3, ADELPHI TERRACE, <lb/>STRAND.   June 19<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> 1916.   My dear M<hi rMend="superscript">rs</hi>. Coffey   Will you send me <lb/> M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Bury's present address &amp; <lb/>I will then fix a day with her <lb/> on which to come here, or on <lb/> which I may go and see her? <lb/>I would like to know her — <lb/>There is so much I would <lb/>like to write to you about, but I <lb/> never feel these letters will <lb/> reach their destination <seg type="del">th</seg> in <lb/> Ireland now martial law
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2506_img_194_2"/>
            has the island in its grip —    How thankful I shall be when <lb/> a Parliament is established <lb/> in Dublin, &amp; when the Irish <lb/> are left to themselves. What a <lb/> muddle Easter Week has made <lb/> of things. I was at Wandsworth <lb/>Gaol the week before last &amp; saw <lb/>some of the Irishmen detained <lb/> there - among these a poor old <lb/> shoemaker from <seg type="unclear">Dungarvan</seg> <lb/> who wouldn't have the strength <lb/> to shoulder a rifle. He was <lb/> taken out of bed, handcuffed, <lb/>&amp; taken to Dublin - leaving <lb/> a wife and 4 children behind <lb/>him. At present I have <lb/> promised to look after them. <lb/> There are many there who <lb/> had nothing to do with the <lb/> rebellion — and there they <lb/>are for heaven knows how <lb/> long - until Home Rule is <lb/> established I imagine — <lb/> Ulster or no Ulster let it <lb/>come as soon as possible! <lb/>I hope you &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Coffey are <lb/>keeping well - and that
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2506_img_194_3"/>
            Dearmid is with you - <lb/>And with my love to you all.   Yours affectionately,    Jane Cobden Unwin   M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bailey seems to have written <lb/>an interesting book —   M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Bury did ask me to have <lb/> tea with her at the nursing <lb/>home one Saturday when she <lb/> was there, but unfortunately we <lb/> were leaving town that day <lb/> and I could not go - and <lb/> now the case is no longer <lb/>there — 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>