<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2439">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kerin & Hickman to the Under Secretary, 3 August, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kerin &amp;amp; Hickman</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from The Solicitors Kerin &amp; Hickman  to the Under Secretary. Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) succeeded Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), who resigned on 3 May 1916 due to his failure to prevent the Easter Rising. 

The letter concerns the summons that Kerin &amp; Hickman issued   a summons to recover £8.8.1  against a member of Kilrush (Clare) District Council. They are concerned that that it is unlikely in this case that the required two Magistrates will attend the relevant Petty Session. They suggest that, under the circumstances, it would be appropriate for the CSO to allocate a second Resident Magistrate.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5620/13361</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2439</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0731">Kerin &amp;amp; Hickman</persName>
              <date>1916-08-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0601">Ennis, Co. Clare, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2439_img_1878_1"  type="Letter"  url="6d7aac6c7d9f50abc895ecb2680bd0b5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2439_img_1878_1"/>
             KERIN &amp; HICKMAN,<lb/>Solicitors.<lb/><seg type="unclear">FREDERICH G. KERIN</seg><lb/>FRANCIS W. [...]-HICKMAN.<lb/>TELEPHONE No. 12. ENNIS.   Ennis<lb/>Co. Clare.    3rd August 1916.    The Under Secretary,<lb/>Dublin Castle,<lb/>Dublin.    Sir,   We have issued a Summons  at suit of W Boughey    against Mr John O’Dwyer<lb/>of Market Square Kilrush, a member of the Urban District<lb/>Council of Kilrush, to recover a sum of £8.6.1 balance<lb/>of a larger sum with which Mr O’Dwyer and other members<lb/>and officials of the Urban Council were surcharged.  This case aroused a considerable amount of public<lb/>interest, and we understand that it is extremely unlikely<lb/>that the two Magistrates will be in attendance at the Kilrush<lb/>Petty Sessions on Monday next, the 7th instant, which is<lb/>the day on which the defendant is summoned to appear.  <lb/>In previous cases of this kind, where any likelihood<lb/>arose of a second Magistrate not attending, the Government<lb/>ordered a second Resident Magistrate to be in attendance,<lb/>and we respectfully submit that a second Resident Magistrate<lb/>will in all probability be required on the hearing of this<lb/>case.  We believe, from information we have received, that<lb/>none of the local Magistrates will adjudicate, and the case<lb/>requires two Magistrates.  The hour of the Petty Sessions at Kilrush is 12.30   We are Sir<lb/>Your obedient Servants, <lb/> KERIN &amp; HICKMAN  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>