<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4173">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Ellen Spender, 13 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spenderr (1876 - 1960)  to his mother, Ellen.

Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1//157A-B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4173</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-13</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4173_img_3546_1"  type="Letter"  url="b392293de0e5cc9b4bb9d653b178fd8c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4173_img_3546_2"  type="Letter"  url="6118d324c32e1e6d017c0c3f41e96f14.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4173_img_3546_3"  type="Letter"  url="81b5a0951db5cbc63f6afc6cce954ccb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4173_img_3546_4"  type="Letter"  url="2ccc357cd5e1473e0c74eeed1f4bbe47.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4173_img_3546_1"/>
             <seg type="del"><Edel</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Mab</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Rex</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Lily</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Maters</seg>   Nov 13   My dear Mater.    As Lily tells me that she will be staying <lb/>with you in the ever hospitable old home I shall write this <lb/>to you &amp; let you pass it on to her by way of a change!    I am glad to think she is under your &amp; Jessie's kind care whilst <lb/>she makes up her mind as to the future plans about which I <lb/>am longing to hear.    My news is nil. We are going on in much the old <lb/>routine at present, &amp; in the kind of weather we are having <lb/>must consider ourselves lucky in being in such comfortable <lb/>quarters instead of wallowing in deep mud further forward, but <lb/>we shall doubtless take our turn at the mud soon &amp; will <lb/>then wish for spring as much as any small bird or beastie <lb/>in the field.   My usual day's routine at present is rather monoton- <lb/>ous. Every letter that comes to this office for one of the 14 staff <lb/>officers I see, &amp; split up into the right sections of the staff, <lb/>being responsible that Russell the Chief of the Staff is made <lb/>aware of all important decisions, &amp; that all the staff are <lb/>working on the same lines. Letters &amp; telegrams come in at <lb/>all hours of the day or night - the largest lot about 10 pm <lb/>but those which come between 11 pm &amp; 7 am are shown to <lb/>the officer on night duty &amp; I only mark them out at 7.30 <lb/>on my way to breakfast. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4173_img_3546_2"/>
             In some ways there is not more to do than there was in <lb/>Belfast, in fact except on occasions there is sometimes less though <lb/>when we move or are in engaging the enemy there is much more <lb/>of course. Now we have <seg type="del">14</seg> <hi rend="superscript">18</hi> officers to deal with what we <lb/>then had only 4  or even only 3  sometimes to deal with.  <lb/>The Staff of the Division is as follows: <lb/>General Oliver Nugunt <lb/>General Staff 1 Lt Colonel Hon A Russell Responsible for general <lb/> direction of Division, ie <lb/> " " 2 Capt W B Spender } all plans of operations, <lb/> movements of troops, <lb/> " " 3 " Richardson intelligence, censoring, etc. <lb/> Administrative Staff <lb/>AAQMG Lt Col Comyn Responsible for Discipline <lb/> Billets &amp; supplies of food <lb/>DAAQMG Major Singleton } forage horses ammunition <lb/>DAQMG Capt Mayne &amp; waggons. <lb/>ADC 1 Lord Farnham Responsible for Camp &amp; <lb/> Quarters of H Q <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> &amp; for Mess etc <lb/>ADC 2 Lt Henry Bars Horses of staff <lb/> servants <lb/>ADMS Lt Col Craig Principal Medical Officer <lb/>DADMS Major Boylan Smith Sanitary officer who <lb/> inspects all Sanitary arrangements <lb/> in billets <lb/>DADOS Capt Brummell Supply of clothing ammunit <lb/> ion &amp; blankets <lb/>DADRS Major Webb Principal Veterinary officer <lb/> of the 5500 horses we have <lb/>Asst Provost Marshal Capt Appleton Deals with police &amp; prisoners <lb/> &amp; French offenders. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4173_img_3546_3"/>
            Claims Officer Capt Hon O'Neill MP deals with payment for <lb/> damage &amp; claims of French inhabit <lb/> ants. <lb/>French liaison off Captain Duc de Luynes Arranges things with the (he has now left) French Mayors <lb/>French Interpreter Lt Beamish Head of the interpreters  I am usually in during the morning unless I go out <lb/>on a Divisional day with the General or inspect one of the <lb/>bombing schools when our Grenadiers are trained. During this <lb/>time I get the correspondence arranged &amp; afterwards as now <lb/>write letters, which are interrupted every few minutes by callers <lb/>&amp; messages, &amp; which are in consequence very disconnected. <lb/>This is I think the worst of this kind of life. From 7 AM till <lb/>11 pm one is never off duty, &amp; even at meal times messages <lb/>continually come; one never gets 10 consecutive minutes to oneself <lb/>nor except when one is out for exercise any time alone. However <lb/>I do not mean to grumble as there must be thousands now <lb/>who would envy my life, &amp; my own 2 room companions <lb/>Russell and Richardson are both very nice indeed, tho' I find some <lb/>of the others hard to get on with.   The French houses we are in are all rather dilapidated, not <lb/>due to the Germans who passed through too quickly to do much
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4173_img_3546_4"/>
            damage, but because the French (quite rightly) have no word <lb/>home , nor any idea of it. My own bedroom is uncommonly <lb/>nice compared to most  but , being over an arch &amp; facing North is <lb/>rather damp, but my bed is comfortable, &amp; that is the main <lb/>thing, whilst Douglas can keep the boards clean. The old <lb/>dame is very suspicious of the 2 men but on the whole gets <lb/>on with them quite well &amp; I fancy they give her a good deal <lb/>more in the way of help than they get, but she watches <lb/>like a cat to see that they don't touch any of her possessions <lb/>coal, wood, etc.   The new Cabinet war Council is out — mostly old men <lb/>&amp; none of them master minds —. Perhaps this means less interfer- <lb/>ence with the Military &amp; Naval officers in the conduct of affairs, &amp; if <lb/>these are <seg type="del">true</seg> good men &amp; <seg type="del">g</seg> true — not political job hunters — it maybe <lb/>all right. I don't see K coming back to the new organisation <lb/>though, &amp; I expect he will direct operations in the East for <lb/>some time, &amp; then I hope come here.    I am anxious to hear both your news of how <lb/>you think each other are looking.   Best of love  <lb/>Your loving son  Wilfrid B. Spender   No mail came yesterday nor today. I hope for several letters tonight mine may be delayed. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>