<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3768">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to Clara Davidson, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary (b.1852). James writes to thank his mother for his congratulations on James&#39; engagement, agreeing that he and Eileen will be very happy together. James hopes to request another lot of leave, but doubts the possibility in the near future. He briefly mentions the death of British Secretary of State for War, Lord Kitchener (1850-1916), describing it as a great blow to the army at a critical time. He closes with a description of life at the front, that the weather has been terrible and many of the men have no bedding or changes of clothing.

This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>PRONI-D3642-B-8-54</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3768</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1115">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3768_img_3154_1"  type="Letter"  url="5022a7c7f0215dab66c0a890b68b2585.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3768_img_3154_2"  type="Letter"  url="bc61e85c14699b76f213b6f22e609bf3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3768_img_3154_3"  type="Letter"  url="37fa6af3a8a88a5f4d8f817ca2eb3bf6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3768_img_3154_4"  type="Letter"  url="ed468a0447e05aa7bdb9da5157be178d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3768_img_3154_5"  type="Letter"  url="238d28ddefa1826f6d0347f98c0eeb5b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3768_img_3154_1"/>
             9/6/16    My dearest Mother    Ever so <lb/> many thanks for your <lb/> dear kind letters about <lb/> my engagement to Eileen. <lb/> Yes we have been such good chums &amp; known <lb/> each other so long that <lb/> I feel sure we shall <lb/> be very happy together <lb/> when the time comes. <lb/> Just wish I could see <lb/> some possibility of <lb/> getting away for a <lb/> second leave soon — <lb/> I fear it is very much <lb/> in the dim distance. <lb/> My Coy did not go <lb/> back with the Brigade <lb/> as we of course expected <hi rend "superscript"> to </hi>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3768_img_3154_2"/>
            but remained where we <lb/>were &amp; I think it is now <lb/> very unlikely we shall <lb/> be relieved at all. <lb/> Personally I really don't <lb/>much mind for unless <lb/>one goes back a long <lb/>way it means very little <lb/>rest and to me the line is <lb/>much more interesting. <lb/>am feeling better <sic>tho</sic> <lb/>last few days— it was <lb/>just a slight chill I had <lb/>— but weather is quite <lb/>depressing, rain every <lb/>day and quite cold. The <lb/>poor men have had <lb/>rather a bad time of <lb/>it as all their blankets <lb/>were withdrawn and they <lb/>only have their greatcoats
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3768_img_3154_3"/>
            for extra coverings at <lb/>nights. Of course they <lb/>sleep in their clothes <lb/>but they get no stray <lb/>or anything to lie on <lb/>so it is not a comfortable <lb/>bed they have. Just <lb/>wish some of those lazy <lb/>strikers at home could <lb/>be put into similar <lb/>quarters. What a <lb/>sad thing that was <lb/>about Lord Kitchener <lb/>and what a great blow <lb/>to the Army at such <lb/>a critical time!   The lining for my <lb/>waterproof has just <lb/>arrived — thanks <lb/>dear mother for <lb/>sending it. Will
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3768_img_3154_4"/>
            post back the other <lb/>one. The parcel of <lb/>shirts also arrived <lb/>safely. Am so <lb/>glad you seem to be <lb/>happily fixed up in <lb/>the kitchen dept. Do <lb/>hope you won't have <lb/>any more trouble. <lb/>Now dear Mother Finish <lb/>Close.    With my fondest <lb/>love <lb/>your loving son   Jim 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3768_img_3154_5"/>
             On Active Service.    Written 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June Wed 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   Mrs. S.C. Davidson <lb/>Seacourt <lb/>Bangor <lb/>Co Down. Ireland   Jim Davidson 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>