<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3836">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Thompson to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 10 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Thompson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Thompson (1867-1936) to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) requesting permission to use the college&#39;s hall for a series of lectures on the Roman Empire.

Aside from being secretary of the Classical Association Thompson was the headmaster if Dublin High School and one of the founding members of the Dublin French Society. He was also a member of the Royal Irish Academy. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T93</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3836</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0083">John Thompson</persName>
              <date>1916-10-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1021">40 Harcourt Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="death">1936</item>
               <item n="tag">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3836_img_3215_1"  type="Letter"  url="80d74736b7a4b69a13123c6acbe9b896.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3836_img_3215_1"/>
            <head.The Classical <hi rend="underline">Association</hi> of Ireland<seg type="head"> <lb/>President for 1915 &amp; 1916 : Prof. J. I. BEARE M.A., F.T.C.D. <lb/>Hon. Treasurer : R. A. S. MACALISTER, Esq., M.A. Litt.D., F.S.A., Newlands, Clonskeagh, Co. Dublin. <lb/>Hon. Secretary : J. THOMPSON, Esq., M.A., M.R.I.A., 40 Harcourt Street, Dublin.  <hi rend="underline">Oct 10</hi> 191<hi rend="underline">6</hi>   To the Registrar <lb/>Royal College of Physicians,   Dear Sir   Your Council have in former years very kindly granted to <lb/>our Association the use of <seg type="del">it's</seg> your hall for courses of <lb/>lectures on Classical subjects &amp; as we are proposing to <lb/>hold a course this winter on The Roman Empire I have <lb/>been requested to ask whether your Council would <lb/>again do us the honour of allowing us the use of your <lb/>hall. We propose to have four lectures, two before &amp; <lb/>two after Christmas &amp; if your Council are willing, we <lb/>can arrange the dates later.   I am yours faithfully  <lb/>J. Thompson <lb/>Hon. Sec.   Dates arranged <lb/>Wednesday 29. Nov., 13 Dec., 28 Feb. and 14 March. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>