<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5495">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Roger Casement to Dr. Theobald von Bethmann Hollweg, Imperial Chancellor of Germany, 11 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Roger Casement </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Roger Casement (1864-1916) to the German Imperial Chancellor, Theobald von Bethmann Hollweg. Roger Casement, born in Sandycove was a former British Consul who, disillusioned with British imperialism became an Irish Nationalist. On his return to Ireland from Germany on Good Friday 1916 he was arrested at Banna Strand. He was tried for high treason  and hanged at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916. 
In this letter Roger Casement writes to Theobold von Bethmann Hollweg looking for assurance that the members of the Irish Brigade in Germany will not be mistreated after his departure to Ireland. 
He makes reference to an interview the two men had on 18 December 1914 with regards to German Policy towards Ireland and an agreement dating from 23-28 December that the volunteers of the Irish Brigade, now at Zossen, would not be harmed. 
The Irish Brigade was mad up of Irish soldiers who had served in the British army but were captured by the German Imperial army and were now prisoners of war. Casement suggested that these men would form an Irish Brigade and go to Ireland to fight against the British army there. However, there was very little uptake among the Irish prisoners of war, only 53 as Casement mentions in the letter. 
Casement does not agree with the German Government that these low numbers have rendered the agreement guaranteeing the safety of the Irish Brigade null in void, and reminds the chancellor of the terms of the agreement. 
He trusts that the von Bethmann Hollweg will honour the terms of the agreement. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,085 /9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5495</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0141">Roger Casement </persName>
              <date>1916-04-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0840">Berlin, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Theobald von Bethmann Hollweg</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0840">Berlin, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5495_img_528_1"  type="Letter"  url="681cdb02d168763b6f06732bae714187.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5495_img_528_2"  type="Letter"  url="2e019778c0153f33f929cba3b7c6982c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5495_img_528_3"  type="Letter"  url="c25786c7a1817d9ae4fb2bb736c4b919.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5495_img_528_4"  type="Letter"  url="01fededa107b0e95d7466cc6bfbb92dc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5495_img_528_5"  type="Letter"  url="122c60e5774a8874abed9b65d72d5789.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5495_img_528_1"/>
             Berlin   11<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> April 1916.   Excellency,   <seg type="del">I venture</seg> On the point <lb/>of leaving Germany on a mission the <lb/>voice <seg type="del">definitely</seg> probably cut me off from <lb/><seg type="del">all</seg> further communication with <lb/>this country — at least during the <lb/>course of the war — I venture to <lb/>bring to you Excellency's notice <lb/>the situation of the small body <lb/>of Irish soldiers, who volunteered <lb/>to form an Irish <seg type="del">brigade</seg> corps to fight <lb/>for Irish freedom with the whole— <lb/>hearted support and approval of <lb/>the Imperial German Govt.   The terms on which they agreed <lb/>to serve and<seg type="del">ton</seg>  the observancy  which the Imperial <lb/> Govt. pledged its good faith in <lb/> the most formal way are embodied <lb/> in the agreement drawn up by <lb/> myself on 23 Dec<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> 1914 and accepted <lb/>by the Under Secretary of State — <hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">Here</seg></hi> <lb/>on 28 Dec<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> 1914.   I need not refer your Excellency to that <lb/>Document, since it was so fully
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5495_img_528_2"/>
            within your Excellency's cognizance <lb/>following the interview on the <lb/>subject of German policy toward <lb/>Ireland I had the honour to have <lb/>with your Ex. on 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Decr. <lb/>1914.   Now that I am leaving <lb/>Germany, as I hope for Ireland <lb/>in order to help <seg type="del">us the best <lb/>in my power</seg> in the very <lb/>critical circumstances in <lb/>which events <seg type="del">(over which I have <lb/>had no control)</seg> seem to push <lb/>my country, I cannot depart <lb/>without recalling the <seg type="del">pledges   bound   <lb/>of the Imperial German Govt.</seg> <lb/> situation  of <seg type="del">to</seg> these Irish soldiers who <seg type="del">might</seg> <lb/>volunteered for the cause of <lb/>Ireland  under the pledge of that agreement  and begging that <lb/>nothing should be allowed to <lb/>interfere with <seg type="del">their</seg> it strict <lb/>fulfilment in their regard. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5495_img_528_3"/>
             These men remain, <seg type="del">in honour</seg> <lb/>a charge <seg type="del">of honour</seg> confided <lb/>to the honour of the German Govt. and <lb/>German people. They are guests of <lb/>Germany in the highest sense <lb/>of the word and are entitled to <lb/><seg type="del">be treated with</seg> the scrupulous fulfilment <seg type="del">regard</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">for</seg> the <seg type="del">stipulations</seg> terms of the Agreement <lb/>under which they threw off their <lb/>allegiance <seg type="del">to the</seg> and entered into <lb/>rebellion. The German Govt. was <lb/>a full consulting party to that <lb/>act of their and did all in <lb/>its power through its military <lb/>chiefs, to assure these men <lb/>that their "treason" was honourable <lb/>in itself, since it was for their <lb/>oppressed country, and  assured them  that they <lb/>should be most honourably treated <lb/>during the period of their stay <lb/>on German soil.   Today <seg type="del">these military chiefs</seg> <lb/> through the channel of the Political <lb/>Section of the Gr. General Staff, <lb/><seg type="del">assure me</seg> I am informed that <seg type="del"> they regard</seg> the <lb/> agreement of 23-28 Decr. 1914 <seg type="del">is</seg> <lb/>null and void and <seg type="del">having</seg> has no binding <lb/>force <seg type="del">on their salary</seg> in relation to the men. That the Irish <lb/>soldiers now at Zossen, to this
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5495_img_528_4"/>
            number of some 53 <seg type="del">4</seg> <seg type="del">(a</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">list of which I append)</seg> are <lb/>"Deserters", or "prisoners of war" <lb/>and may be treated in any way <lb/>that seems <seg type="del">easiest for</seg> fitting <seg type="del">for</seg>to the military <lb/>authorities.    Dissenting  profoundly  from this point <lb/>of view, I am forced to refer <lb/>the treatment of these Irish<seg type="del">men soldiers</seg> volunteers <lb/>to your Excellency as the highest <lb/>representative of the Imperial <lb/>Gr. Govt. <seg type="del">whose good faith is <lb/> then called in question by a <lb/>main Department of one <lb/>of the Depts of State, but <lb/>not doubted by family, <lb/>and to beg that</seg> in the firm <lb/>conviction that every stipulation <lb/>of the agreement of 23—28 Decr. 1914 <lb/>in so far as it affects the <lb/>men, their status here in Germany <lb/>and their ultimate <seg type="del">treatment</seg> disposal <lb/>on the conclusion peace will <lb/>be faithfully fulfilled by <lb/>the <seg type="del">highest authorities of <lb/>the <seg type="del"> Country and </seg>Government <seg type="del">and</seg> or this great <lb/>country. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5495_img_528_5"/>
             To <hi rend="underline">Chancellor</hi>   11 April <hi rend="underline">1916</hi>   I have requested my friend <lb/>Mr.T.St John Gaffney, former <lb/>U.S Consul at Munich to have <lb/>a kindly interest in the <lb/>men so far as this may be <lb/>possible and am recommending <lb/>him in this capacity to <lb/>Count Georg von Wedel of the <lb/>German Foreign Office whose <lb/>assurances to me on behalf <lb/>of the men I recall with <lb/>gratitude and confidence.   I have the honour to be, <lb/>Excellency, <lb/>Your Excellency's <lb/>most obedient <lb/>humble servant,   Roger Casement   His Excellency, <lb/>Dr. von Bethmann Hollweg <lb/>Imperial Chancellor Berlin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>