<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3795">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alfred Miller to Thomas Kirkpatrick, 20 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alfred Miller</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Alfred Miller (1884-1942) to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) the format of examinations for chemistry and physics.

Alfred Miller served as both the registrar of the Royal College of Surgeons (1910-1938) and as secretary to the Conjoint Board of the College of Physicians and College of Surgeons. At the outbreak of the Rising Miller instructed James Duncan, the college porter, to lock the college doors in order to deter Michael Mallin&#39;s occupying rebel force in St. Stephen&#39;s Green. 

 From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T71</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3795</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0696">Alfred Miller</persName>
              <date>1916-04-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1615">Royal College of Surgeons, Stephen&#39;s Green, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1942</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3795_img_3179_1"  type="Letter"  url="e7c6ca8031f3007fb7f53bfe7ff26e4c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3795_img_3179_1"/>
             CONJOINT BOARD IN IRELAND <lb/>OF THE <lb/>Royal College of Physicians and the Royal College <lb/>of Surgeons.   OFFICES OF COMMITTEE OF MANAGEMENT <lb/>ROYAL COLLEGE OF <seg type="del">PHYSICIANS</seg> SURGEONS <lb/><seg type="del">KILDARE STREET</seg> STEPHEN'S GREEN <lb/>DUBLIN,   20/4/1916   ALFRED MILLER <lb/>Secretary   Dear Sir,   The Committee of Management recommend that the mode of <lb/>conducting the Examination in Chemistry &amp; Physics be altered as <lb/>follows:-   That the Oral Examination in Chemistry be given up, and that <lb/>the marks be allotted as follows:- Chemistry, Paper - 100; <lb/>Practical - 200; Physics, Paper - 100; Oral - 100; and that <lb/>two and a half hours be allowed for the answering of each paper.   I am, <lb/>Yours faithfully,   Alfred Miller.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">Secretary</hi>  T. P. C. Kickpatrick, Esq. M.D. <lb/>Royal College of Physicians</adress>  MaerC <lb/>2.VI.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>