<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4328">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arthur Maxwell to Edward Carson, 18 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur Kenlis Maxwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Arthur Kenlis Maxwell, 11th Baron Farnham (1879-1957) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Maxwell was a Unionist MP and Lieutenant Colonel of the North Irish Horse during the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4328</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0879">Arthur Kenlis Maxwell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1957</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4328_img_3688_1"  type="Letter"  url="37291ce0493e2417eb4b650e6e9bdb4b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4328_img_3688_2"  type="Letter"  url="8586141343c3829937d44f3f9f8294e5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4328_img_3688_1"/>
             D1507/A/17/22  87   June 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   My dear Sir Edward,  I have received a letter today<lb/>from Saunderson which fills me with concern<lb/>&amp; misgiving. I understand from him that our<lb/>Unionist Leaders in the Cabinet knew nothing<lb/>of Loyd georges statement that the HR. question<lb/>must be settled now, that there was no<lb/>Cabinet meeting about it. And that their<lb/>opinion is that to set up a Parliament in<lb/>Dublin now, of any kind, would be pure<lb/>madness, &amp; that any settlement which could<lb/>be arrived at, was only with a view to<lb/>getting the amending Bill passed <hi rend="underline">after the<lb/>War</hi>. I am absolutely at a loss to understand<lb/>this, as our action was based on your definite<lb/>statement to the contrary. And I understood that<lb/>our Unionist leaders had directed us, &amp; were<lb/>prepared to force HR on Ireland after the War<lb/>if a settlement was not come to now. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4328_img_3688_2"/>
             88  Of course if this is not the case the whole<lb/>situation is altered. And the decision of<lb/>the Ulster Council was come to under<lb/>an entirely false impression.  Our Resolution was only drawn up on the understanding<lb/>that it was an Imperial necessity to settle <hi rend="underline">now</hi><lb/>an apparently this is not the opinion of<lb/>some of the Unionist Leaders in the Cabinet, &amp;<lb/>they are opposed to any settlement now.  I have incurred a very heavy Responsibility<lb/>by our action, and I am most anxious to<lb/>know the true state of affairs, as of course<lb/>if there has been a <sic>mis understanding</sic> the<lb/>situation should be cleared at once.  I would be very obliged if you would<lb/>write to me at once &amp; let me know what<lb/>has happened, as I feel very uneasy in my<lb/>mind at present.   Hoping to hear from you soon<lb/>Yours sincerely<lb/>Farnham   HQ 36<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division<lb/>B.E.F    </p
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>